<?xml version="1.0"?>
<Item TextType="CompleteItem" SchemaVersion="1.2" id="WEB012105" ACSPageNumber="1" ACSTemplate="Generic_A4_Unnumbered" ACSCourseItem="T184" LastRendering="VLE Preview" DiscussionAlias="Discussion" SessionAlias="" SecondColour="None" ThirdColour="None" FourthColour="None" Logo="colour"><CourseCode>T184</CourseCode><CourseTitle>Robotics and the meaning of life: a practical guide to things that think</CourseTitle><ItemID>T184</ItemID><ItemTitle>Lesson 2</ItemTitle><Unit><UnitID>Lesson 2 Introduction</UnitID><UnitTitle>Lesson 2 Introduction</UnitTitle><ByLine>Prepared for the module team by Jeffrey Johnson and Tony Hirst, updated by Jon Rosewell</ByLine><Session><Title>Lesson 2: Moving and sensing</Title><Paragraph><i>Prepared for the module team by Jeffrey Johnson and Tony Hirst, updated by Jon Rosewell</i></Paragraph><Paragraph>Welcome to Lesson 2. This week we will look at how robots move and sense.  To help us we will be using a &#x2018;model&#x2019; of intelligent machines that we will call the reactive, or &#x2018;sense&#x2013;act&#x2019;, model.</Paragraph><Paragraph>There are other models of intelligent systems, and you will meet some of these later in the module. However, the sense&#x2013;act robot model provides a good starting point for thinking about robotic systems. The idea behind the sense&#x2013;act model is that intelligent machines get information from their environment through sensors and this determines how they will act. Robots built to the sense&#x2013;act model &#x2018;act&#x2019; reactively or reflexively as a direct consequence of the sensor information. This is different from the sense&#x2013;think&#x2013;act robots that will be considered in Lesson 3. These act deliberatively, that is they &#x2018;think&#x2019; about what to do before performing an action. In this lesson we will focus on sensing and moving, and how these can be connected to produce characteristic robot behaviours.</Paragraph><Paragraph>Lesson 2 follows the same pattern of web, book and lab-based work you met in Lesson 1. The study sessions are listed to the left of this page.</Paragraph><Section><Title>Learning outcomes</Title><Paragraph>At the end of Lesson 2 you should have an understanding of:</Paragraph><BulletedList><ListItem>perception and actuation subsystems of intelligent machines;</ListItem><ListItem>how the sense&#x2013;act model can be applied to robots;</ListItem><ListItem>how robots can be made to move;</ListItem><ListItem>models of movement and sensing in the natural world;</ListItem><ListItem>how robots can be made to sense themselves and their environment;</ListItem><ListItem>how sensing and motion are linked in animals and machines.</ListItem></BulletedList></Section></Session><Session><Title>2.1 The sense&#x2013;act model</Title><Paragraph>The sense&#x2013;act model can be described in terms of perception and actuation subsystems.</Paragraph><Figure><Image src="\\dog\PrintLive\Courses\t184\web\e1i1\published\images\lesson_2\t184_lesson2_f01.jpg" height="" width="100%" alt="" id="" webthumbnail="" x_imagesrc="t184_lesson2_f01.jpg" x_imagewidth="479" x_imageheight="169"/><Caption/></Figure><InternalSection><Heading>Perception subsystem</Heading><Paragraph>What we typically think of as our five senses (sight, sound, touch, taste, smell) are part of what is referred to as our perception subsystem. In a robot, sensory information about its physical environment is provided by sensors. There is a wide range of sensors available to robot designers, and you will come across several of them in this module.</Paragraph></InternalSection><InternalSection><Heading>Actuation subsystem</Heading><Paragraph>The actuation subsystem is the means by which the machine interacts with its environment, generally changing its relationship with the environment, and sometimes changing its environment. A special part of the actuation subsystem, known as the mobility subsystem, is used to move the robot. Whenever a robot does something in or to its environment, we say that it has performed an action. For example, a robot may move itself from one location to another. Alternatively, it might use a manipulator arm to move an object. Using the sensors of its perception subsystem the robot detects these changes, which starts the cycle all over again.</Paragraph></InternalSection><InternalSection><Heading>Reflexes and reaction</Heading><Paragraph>Sometimes we perform an action or series of actions without thinking, like pulling our hand away from very hot water, or jumping out of the path of a speeding bicycle. These so-called reflex actions seem to involve no thought at all, and often we are surprised by them. This is because some actions are &#x2018;hard wired&#x2019; locally in our bodies. The sensor inputs pass directly to the actuators, bypassing the brain, and saving time in dangerous situations. In this case, it is normal to consider robots in terms of the sense&#x2013;act model.</Paragraph><Paragraph>In contrast to hard-wired reflexes, reactive behaviour is not only automatic, but is <b>learned.</b> For example, in a dangerous situation a car driver will automatically apply the brakes. Although the experienced driver&#x2019;s reactions are automatic, this behaviour has to be learned. Reaction is a special case of the sense&#x2013;think&#x2013;act model, which we will meet in Lesson 3. In this case the &#x2018;thinking&#x2019; is very fast because the learned response usually involves no further processing, such as reasoning, before the response is given.</Paragraph></InternalSection></Session><Session><Title>2.2 Moving matters</Title><Paragraph>We will start looking at the actuation subsystem and particularly at ways of making mobile robots. A number of ingenious mechanisms have been explored in robotics and we will summarise these later. First you can explore some different examples on the DVD and in the wiki.</Paragraph><Activity><Heading>Watch</Heading><Timing><Hours>1</Hours></Timing><Question><Paragraph><InlineFigure><Image src="\\dog\PrintLive\nonCourse\design_templates\ICONS\Web\png's\42_pixels\video_dvd_42.png" height="" width="100%" alt="" id="" webthumbnail="" x_imagesrc="video_dvd_42.png" x_imagewidth="42" x_imageheight="42"/></InlineFigure> <i>James May&#x2019;s Big Ideas: Man&#x2013;Machine</i>. You may want to skim through this program again to remind yourself of the different mobility systems you saw. Note down for each example:</Paragraph><BulletedList><ListItem>what sorts of motions are displayed</ListItem><ListItem>what actuators are used</ListItem><ListItem>what power source is used.</ListItem></BulletedList><Paragraph>A full <olink targetdoc="James May DVD transcript">transcript for the DVD</olink> is available. You can also open it from the <olink targetdoc="More resources">More resources</olink> section of the website.</Paragraph></Question></Activity><Activity><Heading>Wiki</Heading><Question><Paragraph><InlineFigure><Image src="\\dog\PrintLive\nonCourse\design_templates\ICONS\Web\png's\42_pixels\wiki_42.png" height="" width="100%" alt="" id="" webthumbnail="" x_imagesrc="wiki_42.png" x_imagewidth="42" x_imageheight="42"/></InlineFigure> Explore the <olink targetdoc="Robopedia wiki">module wiki</olink>, looking for examples of different mobility systems.</Paragraph><Paragraph>Think about what methods robots use to move:</Paragraph><BulletedList><ListItem>on land</ListItem><ListItem>in water</ListItem><ListItem>in the air.</ListItem></BulletedList><Paragraph>If you know of an interesting example that is not in the wiki, why not add a short page describing it?</Paragraph></Question></Activity><SAQ><Heading>SAQ 1</Heading><Question><Paragraph>What methods do robots use to move on land, in water and in the air?</Paragraph></Question><Answer><Paragraph>The methods of moving shown on the DVD and on the module wiki include:</Paragraph><BulletedList><ListItem>wheeled robots</ListItem><ListItem>tracked robots</ListItem><ListItem>walking robots<UnNumberedSubsidiaryList><SubListItem>hexapods with tripod gait</SubListItem><SubListItem>quadrupeds, e.g. Sony AIBO dogs</SubListItem><SubListItem>bipeds &#x2013; humanoids such as ASIMO</SubListItem></UnNumberedSubsidiaryList></ListItem><ListItem>swinging (brachiator) robots</ListItem><ListItem>hoppers</ListItem><ListItem>snake robots</ListItem><ListItem>swimming robots, e.g. fish</ListItem><ListItem>flying robots<UnNumberedSubsidiaryList><SubListItem>planes</SubListItem><SubListItem>helicopters</SubListItem><SubListItem>ornithopters.</SubListItem></UnNumberedSubsidiaryList></ListItem></BulletedList></Answer></SAQ><Section><Title>Degrees of freedom</Title><Paragraph>A useful idea when considering robot motion is that of degrees of freedom. Consider the &#x2018;elbow&#x2019; joint of a simple robot arm. This can rotate about a single axis, and so we say that it has a single degree of freedom. Adding more joints that move independently &#x2013; at shoulder and wrist for example &#x2013; would add more degrees of freedom, each of which requires an actuator that must be controlled.</Paragraph><Figure><Image src="\\dog\PrintLive\Courses\t184\web\e1i1\published\images\lesson_2\t184_lesson2_f02.jpg" height="" width="100%" alt="" id="" webthumbnail="" x_imagesrc="t184_lesson2_f02.jpg" x_imagewidth="457" x_imageheight="197"/><Caption>The Shadow Robot Hand</Caption><SourceReference>&#xA9; <a href="http://www.shadowrobot.com/">Shadow Robot Company</a></SourceReference></Figure><Paragraph>Now consider how many degrees of freedom there are in the human hand. Each joint of each finger contributes a degree of freedom; more if you allow for joints that swivel as well as bend. A similarly flexible robot hand could have perhaps 20 degrees of freedom; each requires an actuator, and coordinating the control of each joint becomes very complex.</Paragraph><Paragraph>Another way of thinking about degrees of freedom is to count one degree of freedom for <b>translational</b> (that is, back and forth) movement along an axis, and one degree of freedom for <b>rotation </b>about each axis. A mobile robot driving around the floor moves in two dimensions and so has two degrees of freedom in translation, but can also turn to face any direction so has one degree of freedom in rotation, making three degrees of freedom altogether. A robot arm that can reach any point in three dimensional space, and also point in different directions once there, will have at least six degrees of freedom in total. It may have more, however, partly to provide additional flexibility (e.g. to reach around an obstacle) and partly to compensate for constraints between joints that do not move independently (for example, the joints along a human finger are not completely independent).</Paragraph></Section><Section><Title>Movement and mechanisms</Title><Paragraph>As you have seen, there are many ways of making robots move. Creating mechanisms for implementing them can require considerable ingenuity.</Paragraph><Paragraph>Electromechanical drive systems, based on electrical motors and gearing mechanisms, are commonly used in robots today. Some robots use pneumatic drive systems based on compressed air, while hydraulic drive systems are also popular, particularly for systems such as robot &#x2018;arms&#x2019; used in manufacturing. Hydraulic cylinders and motors are compact and allow high levels of force and power, together with accurate control.</Paragraph><Paragraph>The &#x2018;human exoskeleton&#x2019; that you saw on the <i>Man-Machine</i> DVD has pneumatic actuators. Another way of using pneumatics is to create artificial muscles for robots. If you want to find out more, take a look at the product article <a href="http://www.shadowrobot.com/airmuscles/">Air Muscles</a>.</Paragraph><Paragraph>Unlike animals, the robots in RobotLab are assumed to be powered by electric motors that give rotational motion. It is easy to see how motors can be used to drive wheels that form part of a mobility subsystem. Motors can also be used to produce motion along a straight line (linear motion) or motion that goes backwards and forwards along a straight line (reciprocating motion). One common approach to transforming a rotation into linear motion is the rack-and-pinion mechanism, illustrated below. Here, rotating the pinion gear wheel in one direction makes the toothed rack move in a straight line to left or right. Rotating the gear wheel the other way makes the rack move in the opposite direction. (You may need to hit your Refresh page key to start the animation below.)</Paragraph><MediaContent src="\\dog\PrintLive\Courses\t184\web\e1i1\published\images\lesson_2\t184_lesson2_f03.swf" type="flash" width="400" height="250"/><Activity><Heading>Watch</Heading><Question><Paragraph><InlineFigure><Image src="\\dog\PrintLive\nonCourse\design_templates\ICONS\Web\png's\42_pixels\video_42.png" height="" width="100%" alt="" id="" webthumbnail="" x_imagesrc="video_42.png" x_imagewidth="42" x_imageheight="42"/></InlineFigure>In this video clip of a robot jazz band, the trombone player uses a rack-and-pinion mechanism to move the trombone slide in and out. To control this, the motor rotates the circular toothed pinion in one direction for a given time, then rotates it in the opposite direction.</Paragraph><MediaContent src="\\dog\PrintLive\Courses\t184\web\e1i1\published\Jazz Band.flv" type="videolow"><Caption>Jazz band at RoboCup Junior</Caption></MediaContent></Question></Activity></Section><Section><Title>Gears</Title><Paragraph>Electric motors often go very fast but deliver relatively little power. For a robot like Pedro, used in RobotLab, the requirement is that the axles driving the wheels go relatively slowly, but with sufficient power to move the robot consistently. This is achieved by gearing. Gears provide a way to trade-off speed and power: speeding up rotation comes at the cost of reduced torque (turning force) but conversely if gears are used to reduce the speed of rotation, greater torque is obtained.</Paragraph><Paragraph>In order to give a slower axle speed, Pedro uses two standard gearing mechanisms. The first is a worm drive which has a screw thread that meshes with a toothed gear wheel. The second is a smaller gear meshing with a larger gear.</Paragraph><Figure><Image src="\\dog\PrintLive\Courses\t184\web\e1i1\published\images\lesson_2\t184_lesson2_f04.jpg" height="" width="100%" alt="" id="" webthumbnail="" x_imagesrc="t184_lesson2_f04.jpg" x_imagewidth="512" x_imageheight="292"/><Caption>Parts of Pedro showing the gearing mechanisms</Caption></Figure><Paragraph>The figure below shows a worm drive meshing to a 20-tooth gear wheel. One revolution of the worm drive moves the gear wheel forward by one tooth. Since this gear wheel has 20 teeth, it takes 20 revolutions of the worm wheel for one complete turn of the gear wheel. In other words, the gear wheel goes 20 times slower than the shaft through the worm drive. The turning force of the gear wheel is 20 times greater than the turning force (torque) of the motor drive. (You may need to hit your Refresh page key to start the animation below.)</Paragraph><MediaContent src="\\dog\PrintLive\Courses\t184\web\e1i1\published\images\lesson_2\t184_lesson2_f05.swf" type="flash" width="370" height="250"/><Paragraph>For some purposes, the ratio of 20 to 1 is larger than is required for Pedro. To increase the speed a smaller gear wheel can be meshed with the larger gear wheel, as illustrated below. This gear wheel has eight teeth, so every revolution of the larger 20-tooth gear wheel results in two and a half turns of the smaller gear wheel (20/8 = 2.5). (You may need to hit your Refresh page key to start the animation below.)</Paragraph><MediaContent src="\\dog\PrintLive\Courses\t184\web\e1i1\published\images\lesson_2\t184_lesson2_f06.swf" type="flash" width="400" height="200"/><Paragraph>With a bit of practice, it is quite easy to calculate the ratios of the speeds of the various components. For example, given:</Paragraph><Paragraph>speed of the motor = <i>r</i> revolutions per second</Paragraph><Paragraph>speed of the worm drive = <i>r</i> revolutions per second</Paragraph><Paragraph>number of teeth on large gear wheel = 20</Paragraph><Paragraph>number of teeth on small gear wheel = 8</Paragraph><Paragraph>then:</Paragraph><Paragraph>speed of the large gear wheel = <i>r</i>/20 revolutions per second</Paragraph><Paragraph>speed of the small gear wheel = speed of large gear wheel &#xD7; 20/8 = <i>r</i>/20 &#xD7; 20/8 = <i>r</i>/8</Paragraph><Paragraph>So the large gear wheel goes at one twentieth of the speed of the motor and the small gear wheel goes at one eighth of the speed of the motor. Subject to losses of power through friction, the large gear wheel has 20 times the torque of the motor shaft and the small gear wheel has eight times the torque of the motor shaft.</Paragraph><Activity><Heading>Activity</Heading><Question><Paragraph><InlineFigure><Image src="\\dog\PrintLive\nonCourse\design_templates\ICONS\Web\png's\42_pixels\off_act_42.png" height="" width="100%" alt="" id="" webthumbnail="" x_imagesrc="off_act_42.png" x_imagewidth="42" x_imageheight="42"/></InlineFigure> Explore some different arrangements of gears. Can you create gear arrangements that speed up rotation? That slow down rotation? Can you predict the ratio of speeds of different gears arrangements?</Paragraph><Paragraph>If you have the LEGO Mindstorms kit, you will have a range of gears available that you can mesh together to experiment with different gear ratios.</Paragraph><Paragraph>Alternatively, you can use the interactive gear wheel simulator below.</Paragraph><Paragraph>Tabs along the bottom allow you to see paired gears with different ratios, simple gear trains with three or more gears, and to create your own arrangements. Using the DIY option, drag gears on to the work surface; place them against each other to mesh them. The simulator will count rotations for you so that you can check your predictions of gear ratio.</Paragraph><MediaContent src="\\dog\PrintLive\Courses\t184\web\t184 lesson 2\t184gears.swf" type="flash" width="480" height="360" webthumbnail="false"/><Paragraph>(Click the following link for a larger version of the same simulator.)</Paragraph><MediaContent src="\\dog\PrintLive\Courses\t184\web\t184 lesson 2\t184gears.swf" type="flash" webthumbnail="true" width="780" height="585" x_smallfullsrc="\\dog\PrintLive\Courses\t184\web\t184 lesson 2\t184gears.swf.jpg" x_smallsrc="t184gears.swf.jpg" x_smallnotfound="y"/></Question></Activity><SAQ><Heading>SAQ 2</Heading><Question><Paragraph>For the following combination of gears, how fast will the second gear turn relative to the first:</Paragraph><NumberedList class="lower-alpha"><ListItem>An 8-tooth gear is meshed to a 16-tooth gear.</ListItem><ListItem>A 16-tooth gear is meshed to an 8-tooth gear.</ListItem><ListItem>An 8-tooth gear is meshed to a 20-tooth gear.</ListItem></NumberedList></Question><Answer><Paragraph>If a small gear is connected to a large gear, the small gear will turn faster than the large gear.</Paragraph><NumberedList class="lower-alpha"><ListItem>For every turn of the 8-tooth gear, the 16-tooth gear will only complete half a turn; the 16-tooth gear thus turns at half the speed.</ListItem><ListItem>For every turn of the 16-tooth gear, the 8-tooth gear will complete two turns; the 8-tooth gear thus turns at twice the speed.</ListItem><ListItem>For every turn of the 8-tooth gear, the 20-tooth gear will only complete 8/20 = 2/5 turns; the 20-tooth gear thus turns at two-fifths the speed.</ListItem></NumberedList></Answer></SAQ><SAQ><Heading>SAQ 3</Heading><Question><Paragraph>The Pedro robot has a motor with worm that meshes with a large gear wheel with 24 teeth and this meshes in turn with a small gear wheel with 8 teeth (see figure above).</Paragraph><Paragraph>If the large gear wheel revolves once every eight seconds: </Paragraph><NumberedList class="lower-alpha"><ListItem>How fast is the motor going?</ListItem><ListItem>How fast is the small gear wheel going?</ListItem></NumberedList></Question><Answer><NumberedList class="lower-alpha"><ListItem>The large wheel goes 24 times slower than the worm drive and its shaft. Therefore the motor speed is 24/8 = 3 revolutions per second.</ListItem><ListItem>The small gear wheel goes 24/8 = 3 times faster than the large gear wheel. Therefore the small gear wheel rotates 3 times every 8 seconds (or once every 2.7 seconds).</ListItem></NumberedList></Answer></SAQ><Paragraph/></Section><Section><Title>Wheeled robots</Title><Paragraph>Cars typically have four wheels, one pair of which move to steer. Modern cars use a rack-and-pinion mechanism for the steering, as illustrated below. As the steering wheel is turned from the initial position (a), the rack moves and turns the wheels (b).</Paragraph><Figure><Image src="\\dog\PrintLive\Courses\t184\web\e1i1\published\images\lesson_2\t184_lesson2_f07.jpg" height="" width="100%" alt="" id="" webthumbnail="" x_imagesrc="t184_lesson2_f07.jpg" x_imagewidth="258" x_imageheight="286"/><Caption/></Figure><Paragraph>This kind of steering suits human beings very well. As we drive we use a constant correction feedback system. Our eyes sense what is in front and using this information we turn the steering wheel, often without consciously thinking about it. We could call this a &#x2018;learned reflex&#x2019; or a developed reaction. Sometimes people with things on their minds drive long distances, and when they arrive, have no recollection of the journey. In some sense, they did the journey on &#x2018;autopilot&#x2019;.</Paragraph><Paragraph>Steering mechanisms like this are seldom used in robotics because they need a turning circle, which would make robots less manoeuvrable in confined spaces. There are many other simple mechanisms that form part of the mechanical engineer&#x2019;s toolbox. You can see examples of some of these at the <a href="http://www.flying-pig.co.uk/mechanisms/">Flying pig</a> and <a href="http://www.brockeng.com/mechanism/index.htm">Brock Institute for Advanced Studies</a> websites.</Paragraph><InternalSection><Heading>Differentially steered robots</Heading><Paragraph>Many small robots have only two wheels, each driven by an electric motor, and are fitted with skids or a freely rotating &#x2018;dolly wheel&#x2019; to maintain balance. An example of a symmetric, differentially steered robot with centrally positioned wheels and skids is illustrated below.</Paragraph><Figure><Image src="\\dog\PrintLive\Courses\t184\web\e1i1\published\images\lesson_2\t184_lesson2_f08.jpg" height="" width="100%" alt="" id="" webthumbnail="" x_imagesrc="t184_lesson2_f08.jpg" x_imagewidth="214" x_imageheight="116"/><Caption/></Figure><Paragraph>The beauty of this kind of robot is the simplicity of its control system. Each motor (and hence each wheel) is controlled independently of the other.</Paragraph><Paragraph>By driving each motor appropriately with respect to the other, it is possible to get the robot to move forwards or backwards in a straight line, turn clockwise or anticlockwise in a forwards or backwards direction, or even turn on the spot. </Paragraph><Paragraph>By driving each wheel at a different speed and/or in a different direction, a whole range of motions can be produced. This approach is known as differential steering. It is the approach used to turn a wheelchair or a tracked vehicle such as a tank.</Paragraph><Figure><Image src="\\dog\PrintLive\Courses\t184\web\e1i1\published\images\lesson_2\t184_lesson2_f09.jpg" height="" width="100%" alt="" id="" webthumbnail="" x_imagesrc="t184_lesson2_f09.jpg" x_imagewidth="344" x_imageheight="202"/><Caption/></Figure><Paragraph>With differential steering it is possible to move between any positions and orientations via a sequence of forward movements and rotations about the mid-point of the centre-line of the two wheels, as shown below.</Paragraph><Figure><Image src="\\dog\PrintLive\Courses\t184\web\e1i1\published\images\lesson_2\t184_lesson2_f10.jpg" height="" width="100%" alt="" id="" webthumbnail="" x_imagesrc="t184_lesson2_f10.jpg" x_imagewidth="244" x_imageheight="273"/><Caption/></Figure><Paragraph>This is the approach used by RobotLab. We will use two-wheeled robots capable of moving each wheel independently.</Paragraph><Activity><Heading>Optional reading</Heading><Question><Paragraph><InlineFigure><Image src="\\dog\PrintLive\nonCourse\design_templates\ICONS\Web\png's\42_pixels\book_42.png" height="" width="100%" alt="" id="" webthumbnail="" x_imagesrc="book_42.png" x_imagewidth="42" x_imageheight="42"/></InlineFigure>If you want to know more about differential steering, read this <a href="http://rossum.sourceforge.net/papers/DiffSteer/DiffSteer.html">article by G.W. Lucas</a>.</Paragraph></Question></Activity></InternalSection><InternalSection><Heading>Tracked robots</Heading><Paragraph>Tracked robots have the same manoeuvrability as symmetric, two-motor wheeled robots. They too can be controlled by a sequence of forward or backward commands, and rotations around their centre-point. However, because the tracks create a lot of friction, control commands cannot be implemented with great precision.</Paragraph><Figure><Image src="\\dog\PrintLive\Courses\t184\web\e1i1\published\images\lesson_2\t184_lesson2_f11.jpg" height="" width="100%" alt="" id="" webthumbnail="" x_imagesrc="t184_lesson2_f11.jpg" x_imagewidth="400" x_imageheight="300"/><Caption/></Figure><Paragraph>Tracked robots are less efficient in terms of power consumption than wheeled robots. Moving the track takes a lot of energy because there is a lot of friction to overcome, both within the track mechanism and between the tracks and the ground. The great advantage of tracked robots is that they can negotiate rough terrain, where most wheeled robots would get stuck. </Paragraph></InternalSection></Section><Section><Title>Walking</Title><Paragraph>Legs make robots more mobile on natural, unmade surfaces. This is because legs need only a small surface area to support them, and can be lifted over small obstacles and put down on surfaces of different heights. This allows an animal or robot to climb.</Paragraph><Paragraph>The gait of a legged robot describes how the legs move with respect to one another. You will probably be familiar, for example, with the various gaits of a horse: trotting, cantering or galloping. Other four-legged gaits are also possible, such as pacing, or pronking (springing up and down).</Paragraph><InternalSection><Heading>Hexapods</Heading><Paragraph>One particular gait, that of a hexapod (six legged) robot, is illustrated in the following animation.</Paragraph><Figure><Image src="\\dog\PrintLive\Courses\t184\web\e1i1\published\images\lesson_2\t184_lesson2_f12.gif" height="" width="100%" alt="" id="" webthumbnail="" x_imagesrc="t184_lesson2_f12.gif" x_imagewidth="250" x_imageheight="150"/></Figure><Paragraph>The magenta circles indicate that the three green legs are touching the ground. The other (blue) legs are lifted up and then moved forward. When fully forward the blue legs are lowered to the ground. At about the same time the three green legs are lifted off the ground. The red circles indicate that the blue legs are now on the ground. And so on. Throughout the motion there are always three legs on the ground and three legs off it. The three on the ground form a tripod. When the centre of gravity of the robot is within the tripod, the robot is stable, which allows the other three legs to move to a new position to make another tripod. This method of moving is called a tripod gait. </Paragraph><Activity><Heading>Watch</Heading><Question><Paragraph><InlineFigure><Image src="\\dog\PrintLive\nonCourse\design_templates\ICONS\Web\png's\42_pixels\video_42.png" height="" width="100%" alt="" id="" webthumbnail="" x_imagesrc="video_42.png" x_imagewidth="42" x_imageheight="42"/></InlineFigure>Watch this video which shows two six-legged robots engaged in a tango dance.</Paragraph><MediaContent src="\\dog\PrintLive\Courses\t184\web\t184 lesson 2\Tango.flv" type="videolow"><Caption>Tango dancers</Caption></MediaContent></Question></Activity></InternalSection><InternalSection><Heading>Quadrupeds</Heading><Paragraph>There is a good deal of interest in four-legged robots, for example in the RoboCup Legged League in which robot dogs play soccer with each other. As with many other robot competitions, this kind of challenge spurs on engineers and scientists to produce better robots. These dog footballers don&#x2019;t run because they cannot move their legs fast enough and they have unconventional methods of &#x2018;kicking&#x2019; the ball! They also move very slowly on the pitch for another reason &#x2013; their vision system, which can find it hard to see and make sense of the ball, the goal, the pitch and the other robots. </Paragraph><Activity><Heading>Watch</Heading><Question><Paragraph><InlineFigure><Image src="\\dog\PrintLive\nonCourse\design_templates\ICONS\Web\png's\42_pixels\video_42.png" height="" width="100%" alt="" id="" webthumbnail="" x_imagesrc="video_42.png" x_imagewidth="42" x_imageheight="42"/></InlineFigure>This video clip shows the footballers in action.</Paragraph><MediaContent src="\\dog\PrintLive\Courses\t184\web\t184 lesson 2\Robodog ftbll.flv" type="videolow"><Caption>Football dogs</Caption></MediaContent></Question></Activity><Paragraph>&#x2018;BigDog&#x2019; is a larger quadruped, designed as a robotic pack mule, intended to carry loads in support of armed forces operating over difficult terrain. If you watch video of BigDog in action you can see how it is able to keep its balance even on unstable ground.</Paragraph><Activity><Heading>Watch</Heading><Question><Paragraph> <InlineFigure><Image src="\\dog\PrintLive\nonCourse\design_templates\ICONS\Web\png's\42_pixels\video_42.png" height="" width="100%" alt="" id="" webthumbnail="" x_imagesrc="video_42.png" x_imagewidth="42" x_imageheight="42"/></InlineFigure> Watch a video of BigDog.</Paragraph><MediaContent src="youtube:k-AGWq0k_Mo" type="embed"><Caption>The Boston Dynamics BigDog</Caption><SourceReference><ItemRights><OwnerRef/><ItemRef/><ItemAcknowledgement>Boston Dynamics/YouTube</ItemAcknowledgement></ItemRights></SourceReference></MediaContent><Paragraph>BigDog is a quadruped, the size of a large dog or small mule. It is powered by a small petrol engine providing hydraulic power to the legs. Each pair of legs looks like the hind pair of a horse and the usual gait is a continual, high-stepping trot. BigDog is shown climbing steep slopes, walking through loose rubble, and trotting through snow. When it looses its balance on an icy patch, or as a result of a hefty kick from a researcher, its legs spread and its feet scrabble for purchase until it recovers its balance. Besides trotting, a variety of other four-legged gaits are shown, including pacing and pronking; another sequence shows BigDog jumping. </Paragraph></Question></Activity></InternalSection><InternalSection><Heading>Bipeds</Heading><Paragraph>One of the major challenges for two legged (biped) robots is balance. There are two aspects to this: <b>static</b> stability means the robot is stable at rest or even mid-stride (as a tripod gait is stable in a hexapod walker); <b>dynamic</b> stability means that the robot maintains its stability by continuous correcting movements (the approach shown by the quadruped BigDog).</Paragraph><Paragraph/><Paragraph>A number of early biped robots tried to maximise their static stability, but this tends to give a slow, deliberate movement which is quite different to the natural movements of a human walking. The motion of humans can be very dynamic, with limbs swinging and keeping their otherwise unstable bodies upright. A swinging limb acts like a pendulum, and this is of great interest to robot designers.</Paragraph><Paragraph>An intriguing example of a dynamically stable walking robot is the Tinkertoy robot. The following extract from an article in <i>Biomedical Engineering</i> explains:</Paragraph><Quote><Paragraph>It doesn&#x2019;t have a brain or a heart, and its walk is a little like the scarecrow&#x2019;s, but a little headless, armless, trunkless two-legged robot, developed at Cornell University, can walk, wobble, hobble, limp, stride and stagger. But it can&#x2019;t stand still in any position without falling over.</Paragraph><Paragraph>The fact that this robot, made of plastic Tinkertoy parts and a few odds and ends, is stable in motion is giving mechanical engineers here new thoughts about how humans walk.</Paragraph><Paragraph>Michael J. Coleman, a lecturer in mechanical engineering at Cornell, says the little walker, by using gravity on a gentle slope &#x2018;performs repeatable, chattering, human-like stable steps without falling over.&#x2019; Coleman, who earned his doctorate in February, says, &#x2018;We believe this is the first two-legged, statically unstable 3-D passive-dynamic walker that can walk stably down a slope without any control system whatsoever.&#x2019;</Paragraph></Quote><Paragraph>Click on your Refresh button to see the Tinkertoy robot walk.</Paragraph><Figure><Image src="\\dog\PrintLive\Courses\t184\web\e1i1\published\images\lesson_2\t184_lesson2_f13.gif" height="" width="100%" alt="" id="" webthumbnail="" x_imagesrc="t184_lesson2_f13.gif" x_imagewidth="160" x_imageheight="120"/><Caption>Tinkertoy</Caption><SourceReference><i>Biomedical Engineering, 1998</i></SourceReference></Figure><Paragraph>One of the more successful bipedal robots is Honda&#x2019;s <a href="http://world.honda.com/ASIMO/">ASIMO</a> which you have seen on the <i>Man-Machine</i> DVD.</Paragraph><Activity><Heading>Watch</Heading><Timing><Minutes>10</Minutes></Timing><Question><Paragraph><InlineFigure><Image src="\\dog\PrintLive\nonCourse\design_templates\ICONS\Web\png's\42_pixels\video_dvd_42.png" height="" width="100%" alt="" id="" webthumbnail="" x_imagesrc="video_dvd_42.png" x_imagewidth="42" x_imageheight="42"/></InlineFigure> <i>James May&#x2019;s Big Ideas: Man-Machine</i>. Watch the segment covering walking and ASIMO; this runs from about 15:00 to 22:00 minutes.</Paragraph><Paragraph>What features of ASIMO&#x2019;s walking are claimed as novel? </Paragraph><Paragraph>A full <olink targetdoc="James May DVD transcript">transcript for the DVD</olink> is available. You can also open it from the <olink targetdoc="More resources">More resources</olink> section of the website.</Paragraph></Question><Answer><Paragraph>ASIMO is a dynamically stable walker that will be momentarily off balance during its movements; ASIMO &#x2018;is constantly with every step adjusting the weight and the centre of gravity and predicting that movement before it happens.&#x2019;</Paragraph><Paragraph>ASIMO is able to &#x2018;move and turn on a curve&#x2019;. It is able to smoothly merge different gaits and directions.</Paragraph><Paragraph>ASIMO can climb stairs.</Paragraph><Paragraph>ASIMO can run; at some points in his stride, both feet are off the ground.</Paragraph></Answer></Activity><Paragraph>One of the most dramatic uses of the pendulum effect can be seen in the brachiator robot of Professor Toshio Fukuda of Japan&#x2019;s Nagoya University. </Paragraph><Activity><Heading>Watch</Heading><Question><Paragraph><InlineFigure><Image src="\\dog\PrintLive\nonCourse\design_templates\ICONS\Web\png's\42_pixels\video_42.png" height="" width="100%" alt="" id="" webthumbnail="" x_imagesrc="video_42.png" x_imagewidth="42" x_imageheight="42"/></InlineFigure>You can see the brachiator robot in action in this video.</Paragraph><MediaContent src="\\dog\PrintLive\Courses\t184\web\t184 lesson 2\LearningProcess[1].flv" type="videolow"><Caption>Swinging robot</Caption><SourceReference><font val="Verdana"><language val="">Toshio Fukuda</language></font></SourceReference></MediaContent></Question></Activity><Paragraph>The brachiator robot is interesting because it <b>learns</b> how to swing. As you can see in the video, it swings its legs much like a human would, and reaches out to catch its hand on the next rung of the ladder.</Paragraph></InternalSection><SAQ><Heading>SAQ 4</Heading><Question><NumberedList class="lower-alpha"><ListItem>What is the advantage of differential steering using symmetrically placed, independently driven wheels over rack-and-pinion steering?</ListItem><ListItem>What is the main disadvantage of caterpillar tracks for a robot?</ListItem><ListItem>What is the advantage of the tripod gait for hexapod robots?</ListItem></NumberedList></Question><Answer><NumberedList class="lower-alpha"><ListItem>The advantage of differential steering using symmetrically placed independently driven wheels is that it allows the robot to move on a circular trajectory, and even to rotate on the spot. Such a robot can get from any position to any other by combinations of rotating on the spot and linear motions. This makes it easy to control. In contrast rack-and-pinion steering does not permit turning on the spot, so a turning circle is required, and three-point turns may be necessary to move into certain positions. This makes this form of steering less manoeuvrable, especially in confined spaces.</ListItem><ListItem>Caterpillar tracks are relatively inefficient, and they consume a lot of energy. Also, measuring how far each track has turned for dead-reckoning may not be very precise, since there can be a lot of slippage between the track and the surface it moves on.</ListItem><ListItem>The tripod gait in a hexapod robot has the advantage that the centre of gravity of the robot can always be kept within the triangle made by the three legs on the ground. This makes the robot very stable.</ListItem></NumberedList></Answer></SAQ></Section><Section><Title>Other methods of moving</Title><Paragraph>On this module we focus mainly on wheeled and legged mobile robots. However, there have been many ingenious alternatives proposed and prototypes built. You will have seen examples in the module wiki; this section summarises a few of the main methods that have been explored.</Paragraph><InternalSection><Heading>Hopping</Heading><Paragraph>Hopping robots have been developed at <a href="http://www.ai.mit.edu/projects/leglab/robots/3D_hopper/3D_hopper.html">MIT</a>. (It may be worth noting that Marc Raibert, who created this particular robot, later founded Boston Dynamics, the company that developed BigDog, the quadruped you met earlier.) </Paragraph><Paragraph>Although hopping appears to be an unusual means of moving for a robot, Sandia National Laboratory in the USA also conducted research in this area. Their prototype grapefruit-sized robot can hop 1 m high and 2 m forward, and has enough fuel for 4000 hops. In principle, such a robot could hop a distance of 8 km!</Paragraph><Paragraph>Hopping robots have also been proposed for planetary exploration.</Paragraph></InternalSection><InternalSection><Heading>Climbing</Heading><Paragraph>Many robot applications require robots to be able to climb into inaccessible places. When this involves climbing up glass windows or smooth surfaces, suction devices like those shown below work well. However, rough surfaces can be difficult for robots to climb.</Paragraph><Figure><Image src="\\dog\PrintLive\Courses\t184\web\e1i1\published\images\lesson_2\t184_lesson2_f14.jpg" height="" width="100%" alt="" id="" webthumbnail="" x_imagesrc="t184_lesson2_f14.jpg" x_imagewidth="198" x_imageheight="161"/><Caption/></Figure></InternalSection><InternalSection><Heading>Snake robots</Heading><Paragraph>Several research teams have investigated robots that move like snakes. A snake robot could operate in small, confined spaces where wheels or legs would get in the way. The flexible body of a snake robot would also be able to climb through and around obstacles in a way that a solid bodied robot could not. A snake robot can be made of many identical modules so its construction can be straightforward; however, each segment introduces additional degrees of freedom and controlling such a robot becomes complex.</Paragraph><Paragraph>You can read more about snake robots here: <a href="http://www.snakerobots.com/">snakerobots.com</a></Paragraph><Figure><Image src="\\dog\PrintLive\Courses\t184\web\e1i1\published\images\lesson_2\t184_lesson2_f15.gif" height="" width="100%" alt="" id="" webthumbnail="" x_imagesrc="t184_lesson2_f15.gif" x_imagewidth="160" x_imageheight="120"/><Caption>A snake robot with vertical motion</Caption><SourceReference><font val="Verdana"><language val="">Sensor Based Planning Lab, Carnegie Mellon University</language></font></SourceReference></Figure></InternalSection><InternalSection><Heading>Swimming robots</Heading><Paragraph>You can find out more about swimming robots at these websites:</Paragraph><Paragraph><a href="http://www.nmri.go.jp/eng/khirata/fish/index_e.html">Japan&#x2019;s National Maritime Research Institute (NMRI)</a></Paragraph><Paragraph><a href="http://www.nmri.go.jp/eng/khirata/fish/general/principle/index_e.html">Principles of the swimming fish robot (NMRI)</a></Paragraph><Paragraph>The <a href="http://web.mit.edu/towtank/www/">MIT Towing Tank website</a> has movies of several fish robots. </Paragraph><Paragraph>Closer to home, researchers at the <a href="http://cswww.essex.ac.uk/staff/hhu/jliua/videogal.htm">University of Essex</a> often take their robotic fish out for a swim. </Paragraph></InternalSection><InternalSection><Heading>Flying robots</Heading><Paragraph>Finally, you can visit these websites for more information on flying robots:</Paragraph><Paragraph><a href="http://www.ornithopter.org/">Ornithopterzone</a></Paragraph><Paragraph><a href="http://www.epson.co.jp/e/newsroom/news_2004_08_18.htm">Epson Micro-Flying Robot</a></Paragraph></InternalSection></Section></Session><Session><Title>2.3 Sensing the world</Title><Paragraph>In this session you will reflect on the capabilities of sensors that enable us to build and control the actions of robots. You will see what information those sensors can deliver and how a robot can interpret the sensor information and act on it. Biological inspiration is now a well-established principle in robotics, so you will also consider how living animals have specialised sensors adapted to the way they live in their environments.</Paragraph><Activity><Heading>Wiki</Heading><Question><Paragraph><InlineFigure><Image src="\\dog\PrintLive\nonCourse\design_templates\ICONS\Web\png's\42_pixels\wiki_42.png" height="" width="100%" alt="" id="" webthumbnail="" x_imagesrc="wiki_42.png" x_imagewidth="42" x_imageheight="42"/></InlineFigure> Explore the <olink targetdoc="Robopedia wiki">module wiki</olink>, looking for examples of different sensors.</Paragraph><Paragraph>Can you identify a sensor that:</Paragraph><BulletedList><ListItem>Is similar to human senses?</ListItem><ListItem>Is similar to other animal senses?</ListItem><ListItem>Has no counterpart in the biological world?</ListItem></BulletedList><Paragraph>If you know of an interesting example that is not in the wiki, why not add a short page describing it?</Paragraph></Question></Activity><Section><Title>What do sensors sense?</Title><Paragraph>In the same way that humans and animals have a range of senses, so do some robots. Each of the external human senses (vision, hearing, touch, taste, smell) refers to a different &#x2018;sensory modality&#x2019;. Each sense responds to a particular physical property. </Paragraph><InternalSection><Heading>Electromagnetic spectrum</Heading><Paragraph>One of the most common carriers of sensory information is the electromagnetic spectrum. Only one small part of this spectrum is visible to humans (the &#x2018;visible&#x2019; spectrum), but we can design sensors to detect others, for example X-ray machines and devices that use infrared light. Some animals can see outside the &#x2018;visible&#x2019; spectrum. For example, some fish can see infrared and penguins can see ultraviolet light.</Paragraph><Figure><Image src="\\dog\PrintLive\Courses\t184\web\e1i1\published\images\lesson_2\t184_lesson2_f16.jpg" height="" width="100%" alt="" id="" webthumbnail="" x_imagesrc="t184_lesson2_f16.jpg" x_imagewidth="498" x_imageheight="215"/><Caption>The electromagnetic spectrum</Caption></Figure><Paragraph>Below is a cross-section of the human eye. Light enters through the transparent cornea, and is focused by the lens onto the centre of vision at the fovea. This is where the light-sensitive cells, the intensity-sensitive rods and the colour-sensitive cones, are most dense.  Our eyes usually make rapid jerky movements several times per second, called saccades. They have to do this because the rods and cones need changing levels of illumination to work. Saccades are used to move the focus of attention when interesting new events occur in the visual field.</Paragraph><Figure><Image src="\\dog\PrintLive\Courses\t184\web\e1i1\published\images\lesson_2\t184_lesson2_f17.jpg" height="" width="100%" alt="" id="" webthumbnail="" x_imagesrc="t184_lesson2_f17.jpg" x_imagewidth="468" x_imageheight="238"/><Caption>Cross-section of the human eye</Caption></Figure><Paragraph>The frog&#x2019;s visual system is specially tuned to catch flies. When an object the size of a fly moves across the visual field in its perception subsystem, a tightly integrated reflex causes the frog&#x2019;s tongue in its actuation system to shoot out and catch the fly. This tight coupling is necessary because everything happens very quickly, and there is no time for the frog&#x2019;s brain to cogitate on whether and how to catch the fly with its tongue. The frog doesn&#x2019;t have to recognise that it has seen a fly at all.</Paragraph><Paragraph>By looking for reflections of high-frequency electromagnetic radio pulses that are invisible to the human eye, we can use radar to build up a picture of what is around us up to several miles distant. For example, radar can be used to make weather maps. The picture below is a computer-generated radar image which uses different colours to show where there is a radar echo of falling rain droplets. The brighter the colours, the heavier the rain.</Paragraph><Figure><Image src="\\dog\PrintLive\Courses\t184\web\e1i1\published\images\lesson_2\t184_lesson2_f18.jpg" height="" width="100%" alt="" id="" webthumbnail="" x_imagesrc="t184_lesson2_f18.jpg" x_imagewidth="250" x_imageheight="256"/><Caption>Radar map of rainfall</Caption><SourceReference><font val="Verdana"><language val="">Crown copyright </language></font><ItemRights><OwnerRef/><ItemRef/><ItemAcknowledgement><font val="Verdana"><language val="">Met office. Reproduced under licence number MetO/IPR/2.</language></font></ItemAcknowledgement></ItemRights></SourceReference></Figure></InternalSection><InternalSection><Heading>Sound</Heading><Paragraph>Sound is another physical phenomenon that robots can utilise through their sensors. What we experience as sound is vibration through the air, as illustrated below. A loudspeaker generates sound by moving a paper cone backward and forward at the required frequency. This causes a pressure wave to be transmitted through the air. The more squashed up the blue waves are horizontally, the higher is the frequency of the sound. The larger the amplitude of the sound the higher are the blue waves vertically.</Paragraph><Figure><Image src="\\dog\PrintLive\Courses\t184\web\e1i1\published\images\lesson_2\t184_lesson2_f19.jpg" height="" width="100%" alt="" id="" webthumbnail="" x_imagesrc="t184_lesson2_f19.jpg" x_imagewidth="351" x_imageheight="347"/><Caption/></Figure><Paragraph>Sound has a spectrum of frequencies. The human ear can detect frequencies as low as 15 vibrations per second, and as high as 20,000 vibrations per second. Dogs can detect frequencies around 50,000 vibrations per second, which is outside the human hearing range. Bats can detect even higher frequencies of about 100,000 vibrations per second. By emitting high frequency sound at about 50,000 vibrations per second and listening for an echo, bats can locate objects in front of them.</Paragraph><MediaContent src="\\dog\PrintLive\Courses\t184\web\e1i1\published\images\lesson_2\t184_lesson2_f20.swf" type="flash" width="290" height="250"/><Paragraph>These frequencies, beyond the human hearing range, are called ultrasound. There are ultrasound devices which act as range finders. These devices emit a ping of ultrasound and measure the time taken to receive an echo; by using the velocity of sound, it is possible to calculate the distance to the object. This technology was used in early autofocus cameras and devices are cheap enough to be used in hobby robots such as the LEGO Mindstorms NXT.</Paragraph><Paragraph>Sound travels through liquid and solids as well as air. SONAR is the sound equivalent of radar and is used for undersea navigation. Ultrasound can also be used for making images as shown below.</Paragraph><Figure><Image src="\\dog\PrintLive\Courses\t184\web\e1i1\published\images\lesson_2\t184_lesson2_f21.jpg" height="" width="100%" alt="" id="" webthumbnail="" x_imagesrc="t184_lesson2_f21.jpg" x_imagewidth="300" x_imageheight="233"/><Caption>Ultrasound image of an unborn baby</Caption><SourceReference>Cool Science Images</SourceReference></Figure><Paragraph>Laser rangefinders are also now available which work on a similar principle to an ultrasound rangefinder, but with a tightly focused laser beam their directionality and accuracy is much higher. When the laser beam is scanned back and forth, it is possible to build an image; this is called LIDAR by analogy with radar and SONAR.</Paragraph><Paragraph>Stamford University&#x2019;s robotic car Junior, which you looked at in Lesson 1, is equipped with laser and radar sensors.</Paragraph><Activity> <Heading>Watch</Heading><Question><Paragraph><InlineFigure><Image src="\\dog\PrintLive\nonCourse\design_templates\ICONS\Web\png's\42_pixels\video_42.png" height="" width="100%" alt="" id="" webthumbnail="" x_imagesrc="video_42.png" x_imagewidth="42" x_imageheight="42"/></InlineFigure><i>James May&#x2019;s Big Ideas: Come Fly With Me</i>. This is a shorter clip of the video you watched in Week 1.</Paragraph><MediaContent src="\\dog\PrintLive\Courses\t184\web\e1i1\published\images\lesson_2\Clip 2.flv" type="videolow"><Transcript><Paragraph><font val="Verdana"><language val="">That&#x2019;s when most accidents are likely to happen, and that&#x2019;s when you need a more sophisticated system like this. Junior uses GPS to tell the car where it is, but also lasers and radar to detect hazards around it.</language></font></Paragraph><Paragraph><font val="Verdana"><language val="">So I&#x2019;m driving along on my way to the shops and there is a car parked by the side of the road in front, but there is also another car coming the other way. Junior can see all that happening, so it waits, the car&#x2019;s gone past, and there you go &#x2013; piece of cake. </language></font></Paragraph><Paragraph><font val="Verdana"><language val="">So, having detected objects, it has made an assessment of the situation and taken action, entirely autonomously. </language></font></Paragraph><Paragraph><font val="Verdana"><language val="">It can even handle a junction that baffles most Europeans &#x2013; and a few Americans &#x2013; the notorious four-way stop.</language></font></Paragraph><Paragraph><font val="Verdana"><language val="">We come to the four-way stop, stop and have a look, there is another car coming, which Junior has seen. He was there first, we&#x2019;ve come to a stop. He drives on &#x2013; that&#x2019;s the rule on American unmarked crossroads. He&#x2019;s gone, we can go! I think I&#x2019;ll have one of these. </language></font></Paragraph></Transcript></MediaContent></Question></Activity></InternalSection><InternalSection><Heading>Smell</Heading></InternalSection><Paragraph>Earlier we saw that animals such as dogs can hear much higher frequency sounds than humans; dogs also have a much better sense of smell. The carriers of smell are the air molecules which pass from the source of the smell to the nose. A dog&#x2019;s nose has more than ten times as many smell receptors as a human&#x2019;s nose, and some people speculate that a dog can &#x2018;smell an image&#x2019;. This may be true, but I would expect it to be very fuzzy because air currents can move in unpredictable ways. Other animals also detect smells and can do so with great sensitivity; for example, the male silkworm moth can detect the pheromones emitted by the female moth at a range of 10 km.</Paragraph><Paragraph>Researchers are beginning to make progress in the development of &#x2018;artificial noses&#x2019;. There are considerable challenges to creating detectors with the versatility of a human or dog&#x2019;s nose, but simple portable detectors are becoming available that can detect a single chemical compound. For example, your home may have an alarm that detects carbon monoxide gas. &#x2018;Smelly&#x2019;, a robot developed by the University of Portsmouth, could sense alcohol; two tubes and small pumps allowed the robot to &#x2018;sniff&#x2019; to left and right. There have been proposals for &#x2018;robotic moths&#x2019; for be used for environmental monitoring.</Paragraph><Paragraph>More sophisticated detectors may contain an array of, say, 20 different sensors, each of which detects a particular compound; software is then used to detect characteristic patterns that identify particular smells. Detectors like this have been developed that can detect traces of explosive.</Paragraph><InternalSection><Heading>Noise</Heading><Paragraph>Noise is an issue that roboticists must face when dealing with any sensor input: sensor input is rarely perfect and usually contains some spurious information that we call noise. Technically, noise is spurious unwanted energy in an electronic or communication system. White noise is random noise across the spectrum of a signal, for example making loudspeakers hiss. Impulse noise is caused by single momentary disturbances, which make loudspeakers click. Noise on sensors means that the signal they give has some spurious information, and this has to be filtered out by some form of information processing. Some of the images used in RobotLab come from a scanner and these have low levels of noise so that, for example, &#x2018;white&#x2019; may not be 100% bright and &#x2018;black&#x2019; may not be 0% bright. You will explore this further in RobotLab 6.</Paragraph></InternalSection><SAQ><Heading>SAQ 5</Heading><Question><NumberedList class="lower-alpha"><ListItem>What are the human senses, and which is dominant?</ListItem><ListItem>Give an example of animals having better sensors than humans.</ListItem><ListItem>Give examples of common robot sensors.</ListItem></NumberedList></Question><Answer><NumberedList class="lower-alpha"><ListItem>The human senses are vision, touch, hearing, smell, taste and, arguably, balance. Vision is the dominant sense, followed by hearing. We also have several &#x2018;internal&#x2019; senses such as temperature, and feelings of hunger.</ListItem><ListItem>Bats and dogs can sense higher frequency sounds than humans. Birds of prey have more acute eyesight. Dogs have a more acute sense of smell. Pigeons have a better developed sense of direction. Dolphins can use echolocation in water, but humans can&#x2019;t.</ListItem><ListItem>Robot sensors can include ultrasound detectors, sound detectors (microphones), cameras, laser imagers, chemical detectors (e.g. alcohol), infrared detectors, touch sensors, light sensors, compasses, and tilt switch sensors.</ListItem></NumberedList></Answer></SAQ></Section><Section><Title>Connecting sensors to actuators</Title><Paragraph>When it started in the 1950s, artificial intelligence put a high premium on the reasoning and planning actions of the cognition subsystem. This approach was driven from the computer science end of the spectrum, where computers were seen as logical machines able to perform complex sequences of calculations.</Paragraph><Paragraph>However, at that time other scientists were thinking about artificial brains in a different way. One of them was the neuroscientist W. Grey Walter, who did some original work on perception and actuation in robots in the 1940s and 1950s.</Paragraph><InternalSection><Heading>Grey Walter&#x2019;s tortoises</Heading><Paragraph>Grey Walter is increasingly seen as ahead of his time in the development of robotics. Many of the approaches he advocated fifty years ago are close to the cutting edge of research today. Below is a version of Grey Walter&#x2019;s tortoise robot, Elsie, with a modern transparent shell. The robot is driven and steered by the front wheel. The robot has a light sensor and the shell is connected to a touch sensor.</Paragraph><Figure><Image src="\\dog\PrintLive\Courses\t184\web\e1i1\published\images\lesson_2\t184_lesson2_f22.jpg" height="" width="100%" alt="" id="" webthumbnail="" x_imagesrc="t184_lesson2_f22.jpg" x_imagewidth="408" x_imageheight="315"/><Caption/><SourceReference><font val="Verdana"><language val="">The Smithsonian Institution</language></font></SourceReference></Figure><Paragraph>Speaking of his idea for the tortoise in a radio talk show in 1948, Grey Walter said the following.</Paragraph><Quote><Paragraph>I&#x2019;ve been planning to make just such a plaything and when it is finished I challenge anyone to tell whether or not it is living, without prolonged observation. In shape it would be rather like a tortoise. [You] could tell that it disliked cold, damp weather, because it would moan pitifully at temperatures below 40&#xB0;, and humidities above 80%. What is more, it would run towards any source of warmth, but would avoid great heat and bright lights. In the evening, it would come out from under the sofa and sit by the fire, or nestle against your leg, but it would scuttle back to its hiding place at a loud sound or sudden movement and could only be enticed out again by a low whistle. When the door bell rang, it would potter out into the hall to look at the visitor, but would have an aversion to men in blue and a liking for silk stockings. It would recognise its master&#x2019;s voice and learn a few simple tricks, such as coming to heel, and begging. At intervals it would become petulant and whine and would nose around for an electric power socket into which it would plug its antennae to recharge its batteries. While feeding in this way it would resent interference by yelping and giving the intruder a mild electric shock. It would need an occasional drink of distilled water, and might I&#x2019;m afraid sometimes make little messes in corners. It would rest for part of the day, when alone, and would only be active in company when it would tend to emit a rhythmic purring sound; but if you teased it by too many contradictory stimuli it would become neurotic and sulk for days, or even break down altogether. The most difficult thing to incorporate in our mechanical pet [would be] the power to reproduce.</Paragraph></Quote><Quote><Paragraph>There is no doubt that even relatively simple machines often display unpredicted properties, and do <i>useful</i> things that their inventors never expected them to do, as well as <i>useless</i> ones of course. This sort of accidental originality is sometimes quite eerie and awe-inspiring.</Paragraph></Quote><Paragraph>Dr Owen Holland of Essex University, a leading expert on Grey Walter, writes:</Paragraph><Quote><Paragraph>An idea that had interested Grey Walter for some time, and that he probably first heard from Craik, was that a control system operating in a complex world would have to be able to represent that complexity internally. ... It was clear that the brain itself, with its vast number of neurons, was enormously complex, and so it was easy to assume that it was capable of representing the external world adequately because of its sheer size. From the beginning, Grey Walter realised the impossibility of building a device with anything like the number of functional units that the brain appeared to possess, and so he began to wonder if there was any way in which internal complexity could be achieved using relatively small numbers of components. By 1948 he thought he had found a suitable method, and he had begun to wonder if the brain used this method, rather than relying on its immense number of components.</Paragraph><SourceReference>Holland, 2001</SourceReference></Quote><Paragraph>Grey Walter&#x2019;s idea focused on connections in the brain. He observed that the brain has a very large number of neurons, but it has a much greater number of connections between neurons. This led him to the idea of connecting light and touch sensor outputs via some intermediate circuitry directly to the motor actuator controlling the tortoise robots. In this way he demonstrated that the behaviour of the machine depends on the way its sensors and actuators are connected. His robots therefore fit the sense&#x2013;act model of behaviour very well.</Paragraph><Activity><Heading>Watch</Heading><Question><Paragraph><InlineFigure><Image src="\\dog\PrintLive\nonCourse\design_templates\ICONS\Web\png's\42_pixels\video_42.png" height="" width="100%" alt="" id="" webthumbnail="" x_imagesrc="video_42.png" x_imagewidth="42" x_imageheight="42"/></InlineFigure>Owen Holland has an extensive archive of materials on Grey Walter, and one of the most interesting of these is a newsreel recorded in the early 1950s.</Paragraph><MediaContent src="\\dog\PrintLive\Courses\t184\web\t184 lesson 2\torty.flv" type="videolow"><Caption>Grey Walter&#x2019;s tortoise robot</Caption><Transcript><Paragraph>In a simple villa on the outskirts of Bristol lives Dr Grey Walter, a neurologist, who makes robots as a hobby. They are small and he doesn&#x2019;t dress them up to look like men. He calls them tortoises, and so cunningly have their insides been designed that they respond to the stimuli of light and touch in a completely lifelike manner.</Paragraph><Paragraph>This model is named Elsie and she &#x2018;sees&#x2019; out of a photo-electric cell which rotates above her body. When light strikes the cell, a driving and steering mechanism sends her hurrying towards it. But if she brushes against any object in her path contacts are operated that turn the steering away, and so automatically she takes avoiding action.</Paragraph><Paragraph>Mrs Walter&#x2019;s pet is Elma, Elsie&#x2019;s brother, in the darker vest. He works in exactly the same way.</Paragraph><Paragraph>Dr Walter says that his electronic toys work exactly as though they have a simple two-cell nervous system and that with more cells they would be able to do many more tricks. Already Elsie has one up on Elma. When her batteries begin to fail she automatically runs home to her kennel for charging up and in consequence can live a much gayer life.</Paragraph></Transcript></MediaContent></Question></Activity><Figure><Image src="\\dog\PrintLive\Courses\t184\web\e1i1\published\images\lesson_2\t184_lesson2_f23.jpg" height="" width="100%" alt="" id="" webthumbnail="" x_imagesrc="t184_lesson2_f23.jpg" x_imagewidth="404" x_imageheight="373"/><Caption>An annotated drawing of Grey Walter&#x2019;s tortoise</Caption><SourceReference>Owen Holland</SourceReference></Figure><Paragraph>The construction of the tortoises can be seen in the diagram above. Below is a diagram showing how the sensors were connected to the motors in Grey Walter&#x2019;s tortoise robots. In scan mode the light sensor and front wheel would rotate as the robot moved. On detecting a light source the robot would move towards it. When the robot got too close to the light source it would be dazzled, and a reflex would make it move away again.</Paragraph><Paragraph>The following diagram shows how the sensors pass through &#x2018;normal&#x2019; circuitry to control the front wheel speed and direction.</Paragraph><Figure><Image src="\\dog\PrintLive\Courses\t184\web\e1i1\published\images\lesson_2\t184_lesson2_f24.jpg" height="" width="100%" alt="" id="" webthumbnail="" x_imagesrc="t184_lesson2_f24.jpg" x_imagewidth="424" x_imageheight="92"/><Caption/></Figure><Paragraph>Grey Walter set up behaviours for his robots to seek power, analogous to an animal searching for food, and, inspired by Pavlov&#x2019;s dogs, he taught a later robot, <i>Machina docilis</i>, to respond to a whistle after training it.</Paragraph><Paragraph>Grey Walter&#x2019;s approach is firmly in the tradition of the sense&#x2013;act model, and many of his ideas were reformulated in the 1980s by Rodney Brooks (who was unaware of Grey Walter&#x2019;s work). Brook&#x2019;s approach to robotics can be summed up in his phrase &#x2018;the world is its own best model&#x2019; (Brooks, 1990). His idea is that linking sensing more directly to behaviour could be as effective as a robot having a complex internal model representing the external world. Both Brooks and Grey Walter took inspiration from much simpler animals that surely lack a brain as complex as that of humans and yet show quite rich behaviours. </Paragraph></InternalSection><InternalSection><Heading>Braitenberg&#x2019;s vehicles</Heading><Paragraph>Valentino Braitenberg was another researcher in the 1980s who was exploring the sense&#x2013;act model, and who was unaware of Grey Walter&#x2019;s earlier work. Braitenberg&#x2019;s vehicles were originally presented as &#x2018;thought experiments&#x2019; in his book <i>Vehicles: Experiments in Synthetic Psychology</i>. However, since its publication in 1984, many researchers have created simulated or real versions of some of the vehicles to demonstrate the rich behaviour that can be achieved from a very simple control system. (You will explore a Braitenberg vehicle in RobotLab 4.)</Paragraph><Paragraph>One of Braitenberg&#x2019;s basic ideas is illustrated below. A light sensor is wired directly to each of two motorised wheels. The idea is that the more intense the sensor reading, the faster the wheel to which it is attached rotates. Thus, if the intensity is the same for both sensors, the vehicle moves forward.</Paragraph><Figure><Image src="\\dog\PrintLive\Courses\t184\web\e1i1\published\images\lesson_2\t184_lesson2_f25.jpg" height="" width="100%" alt="" id="" webthumbnail="" x_imagesrc="t184_lesson2_f25.jpg" x_imagewidth="318" x_imageheight="163"/><Caption/></Figure><Paragraph>However, if there is a bright light to the left of robot (a), it turns away from the light because the left wheel rotates faster than the right wheel. Similarly, if there is a bright light to the right of the robot it turns away from the light because the right wheel rotates faster than the left. So, robot (a) has a light-avoiding behaviour.</Paragraph><Paragraph>If there is a bright light to the left of robot (b), it turns towards the light because the right wheel rotates faster than the left wheel. Similarly, if there is a bright light to the right of the robot it turns towards the light because the left wheel rotates faster than the right wheel. So, robot (b) has a light-seeking behaviour.</Paragraph><Paragraph>The surprising thing about Braitenberg&#x2019;s robots is that their behaviour clearly emerges from the way the sensors and the motors are connected. There is no logical process or reasoning of the form &#x2018;if left sensor is illuminated more than right sensor then power the left wheel more than the right wheel&#x2019;, even though this behaviour is &#x2018;embodied&#x2019; within the robot. What is not explicitly represented anywhere are the goals &#x2018;turn towards light&#x2019; or &#x2018;avoid light&#x2019;. In some sense, the robot &#x2018;just does it&#x2019;, because it is wired up that way.</Paragraph><Paragraph>These sort of behaviours are found in animals: a moth is attracted to light, a woodlouse avoids bright light. This response by movement of the animal towards or away from a stimulus is called <i>taxis</i> (pronounced &#x2018;tacksiss&#x2019;). More specifically, movement towards light is called positive phototaxis, and away from light negative phototaxis.</Paragraph><Paragraph/><Paragraph>It does not take a great leap to realise that evolution could work on such mechanisms. If an animal evolves that happens to be &#x2018;connected up&#x2019; in a way that suits its environment, it has a better chance of survival than other members of its species that don&#x2019;t. So it could be selected on the basis of having appropriate reflexes, thereby propagating the physical connections that give rise to those reflexes. In one of the most exciting areas of current robotics, researchers are looking at ways of &#x2018;co-evolving&#x2019; sensors, controllers and actuators to exploit the rich, and often unpredictable, behaviours that can be obtained from certain relationships between these subsystems.</Paragraph><Activity><Heading>Optional reading</Heading><Question><Paragraph><InlineFigure><Image src="\\dog\PrintLive\nonCourse\design_templates\ICONS\Web\png's\42_pixels\book_42.png" height="" width="100%" alt="" id="" webthumbnail="" x_imagesrc="book_42.png" x_imagewidth="42" x_imageheight="42"/></InlineFigure>If you would like to know more about Braitenberg&#x2019;s vehicles, and you have time, take a look at this review of <a href="http://www.bcp.psych.ualberta.ca/~mike/Pearl_Street/Margin/Vehicles/index.html">Braitenberg&#x2019;s vehicles</a> by Dr. Michael Dawson at the University of Alberta, Edmonton, Canada.</Paragraph></Question></Activity></InternalSection></Section></Session><Session><Title>2.4 RobotLab2</Title><Paragraph>In this session you will be doing lab activities using RobotLab2.</Paragraph><Activity><Heading>RobotLab</Heading><Question><Paragraph><InlineFigure><Image src="\\dog\PrintLive\nonCourse\design_templates\ICONS\Web\png's\42_pixels\robotlab_42.png" height="" width="100%" alt="" id="" webthumbnail="" x_imagesrc="robotlab_42.png" x_imagewidth="42" x_imageheight="35"/></InlineFigure> Download the lab guide for <olink targetdoc="RobotLab2">RobotLab2</olink>. Read the guide carefully and follow the instructions provided.</Paragraph></Question></Activity><Paragraph>When you have finished RobotLab2 have a go at the following SAQs.</Paragraph><SAQ><Heading>SAQ 6</Heading><Question><NumberedList class="lower-alpha"><ListItem>Apart from the Simulator window on the right, the RobotLab screen has three other important areas. What are they and what are they used for?</ListItem><ListItem>Write down a RobotLab program that will move a simulated robot forward for one second.</ListItem></NumberedList></Question><Answer><NumberedList class="lower-alpha"><ListItem>RobotLab has a <i>Command Window</i> on the left, under that is the <i>Key&#x2013;Value</i> window. To the right of these is the <i>Program Window</i>. Commands are dragged from the Command Window into the Program Window. When necessary, variable names and values can be changed in the Key Value window.</ListItem><ListItem><Paragraph>The following program will move a robot forward for one second:</Paragraph><Paragraph><InlineFigure><Image src="\\dog\PrintLive\Courses\t184\web\e1i1\published\images\lesson_2\t184_lesson2_f26.jpg" height="" width="100%" alt="" id="" webthumbnail="" x_imagesrc="t184_lesson2_f26.jpg" x_imagewidth="313" x_imageheight="151"/></InlineFigure></Paragraph></ListItem></NumberedList></Answer></SAQ><SAQ><Heading>SAQ 7</Heading><Question><Paragraph>What is a sequential computer program? Illustrate this by writing down a program that says &#x2018;red&#x2019;, followed by &#x2018;brick&#x2019;, followed by &#x2018;wall&#x2019;. Hint: the <b>send</b> codes for &#x2018;red&#x2019;, &#x2018;brick&#x2019; and &#x2018;wall&#x2019; are 21, 43 and 37, respectively.</Paragraph></Question><Answer><Paragraph>A sequential program is one that is made up of a list of commands which are executed by the computer one after the other. The following program illustrates this. It starts with a comment, which does nothing. Then control moves to the command which begins the main part of the program. After this the command <b>send 21</b> is executed, and a command is sent to the computer telling it to play wav file number 21, and say &#x2018;red&#x2019;. The command <b>wait 35</b> is executed after this, causing the computer to wait for 0.35 seconds before executing the next command. The remaining commands are executed in order until the final comment is reached. The net result of the program is that the computer says &#x2018;red brick wall&#x2019;, as required.</Paragraph><Figure><Image src="\\dog\PrintLive\Courses\t184\web\e1i1\published\images\lesson_2\t184_lesson2_f27.jpg" height="" width="100%" alt="" id="" webthumbnail="" x_imagesrc="t184_lesson2_f27.jpg" x_imagewidth="284" x_imageheight="189"/></Figure></Answer></SAQ></Session><Session><Title>2.5 Summary</Title><Paragraph>Lesson 2 has been practical in its orientation, getting to grips with some of the fundamentals of robot technology. In it you have studied motion and sensing in robots, in the context of the sense&#x2013;act and sense&#x2013;think&#x2013;act models of intelligent machines.</Paragraph><Paragraph>Session 2.2 gave an overview of the main robot mobility systems, including video clips that allow you to see various kinds of robot moving in different environments. You have also been introduced to the symmetric two-wheeled robots that will be used in RobotLab in later weeks.</Paragraph><Paragraph>Session 2.3 considered sensors, approaching this from the context of animal sensing and behaviour. In particular you have considered Grey Walter&#x2019;s early tortoise robots in some detail, and seen how his ideas remain at the research frontiers over 50 years later. In RobotLab4 you will experiment with Braitenberg&#x2019;s vehicles, where, as suggested by Grey Walter, their behaviour emerges from the way the sensors and motors are connected.</Paragraph><Paragraph>As well as considering theoretical aspects of robotics, in RobotLab2 you met some of the fundamental computer programming structures. These include the nature of sequential programs, constants, variables, loops and branching. If you are new to programming this may seem like a lot of ground. However, you should be beginning to get to grips with RobotLab and, hopefully, have used it to create a robot control program. If so, you can feel a justified sense of achievement.</Paragraph><Paragraph>Lesson 2 has covered many ideas, and it has included an introduction to robot programming. If these things were all new to you, there is a lot to take in. Even so, we hope that this lesson has been interesting, and fun.</Paragraph><StudyNote><Paragraph>Where next:</Paragraph><Paragraph>This is the end of Lesson 2. When you are ready go to <olink targetdoc="Lesson 3"><font val="Verdana"><language val="">Lesson 3</language></font></olink></Paragraph></StudyNote></Session></Unit><BackMatter><References><Reference><i>Mind and Machines, </i>BBC television programme, BBC West of England Home Service, 5 February 1948.</Reference><Reference> Braitenberg, V. (1984) <i>Vehicles: Experiments in Synthetic Psychology</i>, MIT Press, ISBN 0-262-02208-7.</Reference><Reference> Brooks, R.A. (1990) &#x2018;Elephants don&#x2019;t play chess&#x2019;, <i>Robotics and Autonomous Systems,</i> <b>6</b>, pp. 3-15. [Available online at <a href="http://people.csail.mit.edu/brooks/papers/elephants.pdf">http://people.csail.mit.edu/brooks/papers/elephants.pdf</a>]</Reference><Reference>Holland, O. (2001) &#x2018;From the imitation of life to machine consciousness&#x2019;, <i>Lecture Notes in Computer Science</i>, Vol. 2217, pp. 9&#x2013;10. </Reference><Reference>Lang, S. (1998), &#x2018;Wobbling, staggering Tinkertoy robots give insight into how humans walk&#x2019;, in <i>Cornell Chronicle</i>, 9 April 1998, vol. 29, no. 29. [Accessed online at: http://www.news.cornell.edu/Chronicle/98/4.9.98/tinkertoy_robots.html]</Reference></References></BackMatter><settings><numbering><Session autonumber="false"/><Section autonumber="false"/><SubSection autonumber="false"/><SubSubSection autonumber="false"/><Activity autonumber="false"/><Exercise autonumber="false"/><Box autonumber="false"/><CaseStudy autonumber="false"/><Quote autonumber="false"/><Extract autonumber="false"/><Dialogue autonumber="false"/><KeyPoints autonumber="false"/><Reading autonumber="false"/><StudyNote autonumber="false"/><Example autonumber="false"/><Verse autonumber="false"/><SAQ autonumber="false"/><ComputerDisplay autonumber="false"/><Summary autonumber="false"/><ProgramListing autonumber="false"/><ITQ autonumber="false"/><Tables autonumber="false"/><Figures autonumber="false"/><MediaContent autonumber="false"/><Chemistry autonumber="false"/></numbering><discussion_alias>Discussion</discussion_alias><session_prefix/></settings></Item>
