<?xml version="1.0"?>
<Item TextType="CompleteItem" SchemaVersion="1.2" id="WEB012112" ACSPageNumber="1" ACSTemplate="generic_unnumbered" ACSCourseItem="T184" LastRendering="VLE Preview" DiscussionAlias="Discussion" SessionAlias="" SecondColour="None" ThirdColour="None" FourthColour="None" Logo="colour"><CourseCode>T184</CourseCode><CourseTitle>Robotics and the meaning of life: a practical guide to things that think</CourseTitle><ItemID>T184</ItemID><ItemTitle>Lesson 9</ItemTitle><Unit><UnitID>Lesson 9 Introduction</UnitID><UnitTitle>Lesson 9 Introduction</UnitTitle><ByLine>Prepared for the module team by Jeffrey Johnson and Tony Hirst</ByLine><Session><Title>Lesson 9: Futures</Title><Paragraph><i>Prepared for the module team by Jeffrey Johnson and Tony Hirst, updated by Jon Rosewell</i></Paragraph><Paragraph>In this lesson we will consider the possible future of robots and societies in a world that is characterised by the extensive use of intelligent machines and intelligent systems. Today, humans construct and try to control systems of immense complexity, and these systems are becoming more intelligent and autonomous all the time.</Paragraph><Paragraph>For example, the Internet connects millions of computers around the world, and there are many billions of web pages, with the number growing each day.  No one has detailed knowledge of every computer connected to the Internet or the content of all the web pages on the World Wide Web. With the growth of intelligent software agents and automated web services, the Internet has become a &#x2018;complex system&#x2019;. Its behaviour is characterised by emergence, adaptation, and the &#x2018;co-evolution&#x2019; of its many intelligent autonomous parts.</Paragraph><Paragraph>New Internet phenomena are continually emerging and as they do, the system adapts. For example, when viruses emerge, the system adapts by creating virus detection programs.  &#x2018;Bursty&#x2019;, or uneven, load patterns of usage emerge from individuals&#x2019; behaviour as they go to and from work, and use the Net in different ways. You may have noticed that at different times of the day, the Internet appears to slow down. Just as the motorway system suffers bottlenecks at peak commuter times, so the Internet suffers digital traffic jams at different times of the day.</Paragraph><Figure><Image src="\\dog\PrintLive\Courses\t184\web\e1i1\published\images\lesson_9\t184_lesson9_f01.gif" height="" width="100%" alt="" id="" webthumbnail="" x_imagesrc="t184_lesson9_f01.gif" x_imagewidth="303" x_imageheight="300"/><Caption/><SourceReference><font val="Verdana"><language val="">www.cybergeography.com</language></font></SourceReference></Figure><Paragraph>Throughout this module we have considered the interaction between robots and humans in the context of Asimov&#x2019;s laws. The reality is that Asimov&#x2019;s positronic brains are a fiction, and we know no way of embedding his laws in real robots. Even so, because from some perspectives the laws are sensible and appropriate, robot designers may try to capture their essence in the design. Economic and social pressures are likely to minimise the opportunity for unethical researchers or companies to produce robots that do not conform to these laws, where appropriate. However, the military has already proved itself to be an exception, and others may follow.</Paragraph><Paragraph>In this lesson we are interested in the degree to which people are prepared to put themselves and their well-being under the control of machines. For example, when I am ill, I go to the doctor, whereupon I generally accept the diagnosis made and the treatment offered. Similarly, if I have committed some offence, I grudgingly let the police officer put me in a cell, and then listen to what the judge has to say. Whilst I may not be happy with the sentence, society effectively forces me to accept the judgment, and I bow to this authority.</Paragraph><Paragraph>Many professional decisions are supported by intelligent decision support systems (DSS), but it is generally the doctor or lawyer who actually makes the decision, not a computer. Would you be happy to accept a computer-assisted decision?</Paragraph><Paragraph>Now suppose that the doctor&#x2019;s or judge&#x2019;s decision were based solely on the questions provided by an intelligent computer system; and suppose further that the diagnosis, or sentence, were generated exclusively by that system, with no human arbiter.  How happy would you be to accept a judgement made entirely by machines?</Paragraph><Paragraph>Finally, suppose that a robot were asking questions and relaying them to a human doctor, who made the diagnosis and fed back the treatment recommendation to you using the robot as a mouthpiece?</Paragraph><Paragraph>These asymmetries help us realise just where we place our trust.  Generally, I suspect most people would opt for the human touch, even if the machine were sometimes more reliable!</Paragraph><Paragraph>Lesson 9 has a number of study sessions, listed at the left.</Paragraph><Section><Title>Learning outcomes</Title><Paragraph>By the end of Lesson 9 you should be able to:</Paragraph><BulletedList><ListItem>state some of the likely advances in robot technology;</ListItem><ListItem>discuss the possibility of us being a part of a gigantic, socio-technical robot;</ListItem><ListItem>explain the implications of a robot being a politician  or in a position of authority;</ListItem><ListItem>discuss the implications of human life being governed by benign machines;</ListItem><ListItem>state some of the likely developments in robotics and their implications for society.</ListItem></BulletedList></Section></Session><Session><Title>9.1 Future technical developments in robotics</Title><Paragraph>The future of robotics can be seen in terms of technical developments that improve performance and capabilities, and the ways that new breeds of robot will be used. Here we will briefly review some of the technological advances that can be expected, before considering the social implications in subsequent sessions.</Paragraph><Paragraph>As far as the physical aspects of robots are concerned, we can expect to see the following developments:</Paragraph><BulletedList><ListItem><b>Sensors:</b> robot sensors will get better, delivering not only the quality of information that we experience as humans, but also sensory information beyond the capabilities of our sensors.  One of the driving forces could be security applications &#x2013; the use of human operators for security purposes is expensive and unreliable.  For sensors to be useful in robots, they need to be made smaller and to consume less power.  The reduction of noise, along with reduction of costs also remain important issues.  Major technological progress remains to be made in sensor fusion &#x2013; combining the outputs of a number of sensors &#x2013; and the &#x2018;co-evolution&#x2019; of sensors with sensor mounts, robot morphology and control systems, and closing the gap between the sensor and how it is used.</ListItem><ListItem><b>Materials:</b> robotics provides many challenges to materials science, and is driving developments forward.  New materials will appear that combine strength with flexibility.  It seems certain that new and better artificial skin will be developed, being both tough and sensor-rich.  Space robotics will drive the search for strong, light materials.  Another development we can expect to see is better artificial muscles.  Major developments can be expected in the area of &#x2018;smart&#x2019; materials, allowing more intelligence to be embedded inside robot bodies.</ListItem><ListItem><b>Structures:</b> the body of a robot plays a great part in its performance.  We can expect to see many novel new mechanical structures in future, allowing robots to move in new ways with much greater dexterity.  There will also be reconfigurable robots &#x2013; robots built from relatively simple components that can autonomously configure and reconfigure themselves.</ListItem><ListItem><b>Power systems:</b> the problem of powering robots is so important that we can expect to see major developments in this area.  Advances in battery technology will be important, combined with low-power electronics, and low-power motors and actuators.   The development of non-battery technologies will also be important.</ListItem><ListItem><b>Nanotechnology:</b> nanotechnology is set for a massive investment in research and development in the foreseeable future, and we can expect many new innovative ideas.  These range from microscopic motors and gearboxes to tiny sensors.  Nanotechnology also permits much smaller subsystems to be built into larger robots.  The impact of nanotechnology will therefore be very significant.</ListItem><ListItem><b>Embodied intelligence:</b> biological systems such as the human body get much of their performance from the physical properties of its materials, such as rigid bones, elastic tendons and muscles. For example, if you hold your arm out straight and rotate your fist as far as you can, it will naturally twist back into place when you relax your muscles. Your arm does not need an intelligent controller to make it do this; this behaviour is an inherent property of the arm due to its materials and structure. &#x2018;Embodied intelligence&#x2019; does not just mean that cognitive intelligence has to exist somewhere. It means that &#x2018;intelligence&#x2019; is distributed throughout an intelligent system &#x2013; just as it is in our bodies. This principle is set to dominate robot design for the foreseeable future, and is likely to solve many problems that the sense&#x2013;think&#x2013;act model has not solved.</ListItem></BulletedList><Paragraph>As noted above, embodiment will become an important principle in robot design. Even so, the more abstract cognitive abilities of robots will remain important, and here we can also expect many developments, although sometimes the boundaries between sensing, cognition, and actuation may become artificial.  AI research will continue to examine problems that are theoretically difficult to analyse and solve algorithmically.  Of the many advances related to cognition, we can expect the following:</Paragraph><BulletedList><ListItem><b>Increased processing power:</b> Moore&#x2019;s law still has a long way to go, and we can expect a continuation in the dramatic increase of microprocessing power available.  This will be combined with a better understanding of parallel computation.  Quantum computers may also make a significant contribution to the processing power available for robot designers.</ListItem><ListItem><b>Improved neural processing: </b>neural information processing has proved to be very powerful and will be increasingly built into robots.  Developments will include new chips and software support systems, which will include circuitry that can be reconfigured &#x2018;on the fly&#x2019;, making robots much more flexible.</ListItem><ListItem><b>Natural language understanding: </b>understanding natural language is one of the major bottlenecks in robotics research.  There are already major research efforts to get robots to form their own vocabulary and constructs in order to understand and reason about their environment.  We can expect advances in this area, but progress may be slow.</ListItem><ListItem><b>Human</b>&#x2013;<b>robot interaction:</b> there will be a greater understanding of how people can interact with robots, enabling better robot&#x2013;human communication.</ListItem><ListItem><b>Data mining:</b> data mining (gathering electronically stored information) is in its infancy, and there will be major developments in this area.  In future, software agents will be able to inspect huge quantities of information and make connections much better than they do today.  This will allow better use of information to make predictions and determine behaviour.</ListItem><ListItem><b>Reasoning:</b> over the past 50 years there has been a lot of research into reasoning and the way humans do it so successfully.  This has given rise to many developments, including so-called fuzzy logic, which does not restrict the robot to true and false, but allows truth to be weighted, and non-monotonic logic, which allows the truth of propositions to change over time.  Better understanding of human reasoning may lead to more intelligent robots.</ListItem><ListItem><b>Learning:</b> it is increasingly realised that the robots of the future will learn and self-adapt rather than have everything programmed in.  Intensive research in this area is likely to produce robots that are easier to make, more intelligent and better able to adapt to changing environments.</ListItem><ListItem><b>Pattern recognition:</b> pattern recognition is fundamental in robotics, in both perception and cognition.  Pattern recognition is still quite poor in some areas, such as machine vision, but it is likely to get much better in the future.</ListItem><ListItem><b>Control:</b> robotics has generated many new ideas and novel control architectures.  These include the use of neural networks to control actuators, and other learning techniques.  It is certain that robot control will improve dramatically in future, as it must if humanoid robots are to become as mobile and dexterous as humans.</ListItem><ListItem><b>Planning and scheduling:</b> great progress has been made in robot planning and scheduling, but in future this will be done at a more strategic level and often involve communities of robots and intelligent agents.</ListItem><ListItem><b>Social intelligence and swarm robots:</b> the robots of the future are likely to communicate with each other to achieve their tasks.  Intensive research into the &#x2018;social intelligence&#x2019; that emerges from the interaction of many robots will continue.  There will be big improvements in our understanding of how to design swarm robots, robot teams and robot communities.  Future robots may have autonomous parts, e.g. a robot arm and its gripper, which behave in a swarm-like way.</ListItem></BulletedList><Paragraph>These improvements in sensing, cognition and actuation will enable much better robots to be built over the next 5 to 20 years.  They will certainly contribute to the development of robots built to perform specific functions. But what of the holy grail: the human-like humanoid robot?</Paragraph><Figure><Image src="\\dog\PrintLive\Courses\t184\web\e1i1\published\images\lesson_9\t184_lesson9_f02.jpg" height="" width="100%" alt="" id="" webthumbnail="" x_imagesrc="t184_lesson9_f02.jpg" x_imagewidth="203" x_imageheight="300"/><Caption>ASIMO</Caption><SourceReference><font val="Verdana"><language val="">&#xA9; 2003 Honda Motor Co. Ltd</language></font></SourceReference></Figure><Paragraph>As you have seen on this module, even the best examples of humanoid robots such as ASIMO are still relatively slow and cumbersome, have limited mobility and autonomy, and lack intelligence. Even in <i>Man&#x2013;Machine</i>, a program that featured the latest and the best in robotics, James May commented:</Paragraph><Quote><Paragraph>I have to be perfectly honest with you; what you&#x2019;ve been watching is a series of edited highlights. Every time we wanted a robot to perform a new task it had to be recalibrated, reprogrammed &#x2013; the whole thing had to be set up.</Paragraph><SourceReference>May, 2008</SourceReference></Quote><Paragraph>Making humanoid robots that are more mobile and dexterous is a great challenge, which will benefit greatly from advances in materials and mechanical structures, and new control methodologies. Certainly the move towards embodied intelligence will accelerate progress.  Improved power systems will help by reducing weight, and nanotechnology will also contribute. Making humanoid robots with human-like intelligence is the big challenge in AI.  Whether all the improvements anticipated here will result in human-like intelligence within our lifetimes remains to be seen.</Paragraph></Session><Session><Title>9.2 Complexity managed by machines that think</Title><Paragraph>Modern society is extremely complex and behaves in ways that we don&#x2019;t fully understand.  Many apparently unrelated things are connected by causal chains that can be very difficult to unravel.   For example, what is the best way to build the many thousands of new houses needed in Britain?  As well as houses, it is necessary to take into account the need for new schools, roads, shops and other local amenities, employment, commuter opportunities and so on.</Paragraph><Paragraph>How can we design coastal defences to withstand the changes in tides caused by global warming?  How can we run an economy in which everyone is employed?  How can we manage the road network to avoid widespread gridlock?  How can we organise a production line so that it performs at peak efficiency?  How can we reorganise the National Health Service in the UK to provide the best possible service and reduce inefficiency?</Paragraph><Figure><Image src="\\dog\PrintLive\Courses\t184\web\e1i1\published\images\lesson_9\t184_lesson9_f03.jpg" height="" width="100%" alt="" id="" webthumbnail="" x_imagesrc="t184_lesson9_f03.jpg" x_imagewidth="300" x_imageheight="180"/><Caption>Spaghetti junction</Caption><SourceReference><font val="Verdana"><language val="">&#xA9; BBC</language></font> </SourceReference></Figure><Paragraph>One of the many characteristics of complex systems is that their management involves the extensive use of computers.  Some of these computers are programmed to make autonomous decisions, such as whether to lend you money or not, based on the information you supply.</Paragraph><InternalSection><Heading>Are we part of a robotic organism?</Heading><Paragraph>If you cast your mind back to Lesson 1, we defined a robot as a machine that can sense its environment, process information from its sensors and other internal information, decide what to do next and execute that decision.  We refined this basic definition with the idea of robots being mobile, autonomous and intelligent.</Paragraph><Paragraph>To what extent do you think that modern society with all its infrastructure, buildings, roads, railways, the Internet, etc., can be thought of as a robot? Humans collect information and feed it into the system.  Humans load and drive trucks according to schedules produced by the system, and generally provide the interface between the system and the rest of the world.  Could it be that we have taken on the roles of the sensors and actuators of a robotic organism that partially guides our activities under robot control?  To what extent is our behaviour already influenced, guided or even controlled by computers and the physical environment?</Paragraph></InternalSection><Section><Title>Automated finance systems</Title><Paragraph>Suppose you telephone a bank to ask for a loan.  A computerised answering service like Emily, which you met in Lesson 4, may direct your call to what it thinks is the appropriate destination.  There, you might be asked for some information, such as your salary or postcode, by an automated system.  This information may be sent to another automated system, possibly on the other side of the world, to make various online checks, collecting information about you and comparing it to the information you provided.  On the basis of this, the machine may make the decision that you can have the loan. This decision may be communicated to other parts of the system, for example the part that writes you a letter offering you the loan.  That letter may automatically go to the post office, where another autonomous machine reads your address and directs the letter accordingly.</Paragraph><Figure><Image src="\\dog\PrintLive\Courses\t184\web\e1i1\published\images\lesson_9\t184_lesson9_f04.jpg" height="" width="100%" alt="" id="" webthumbnail="" x_imagesrc="t184_lesson9_f04.jpg" x_imagewidth="456" x_imageheight="330"/><Caption/></Figure><Paragraph>This whole process could take place without humans needing to be involved.  Each of the computers can be considered to be an autonomous agent. Some of them are relatively intelligent. Some of these computers have to cope with relatively unstructured information, such as the machine that searches the Web looking for your information.  No one can predict exactly what they will do in your case, because your case and your data are unique.  So this is a situation in which computers are acting on the basis of decisions made by other computers, and they are passing on their decisions to other computers.  There is clearly the possibility of unexpected behaviour here, and this behaviour may not be what the human system designer intended.</Paragraph><Paragraph>Of course this kind of financial system is not very intelligent, and the decisions it makes are not matters of life or death.  If you don&#x2019;t get a loan from one company, you try another.</Paragraph><Paragraph>This kind of automated system is not necessarily sensible. For example, a credit check may include a check on how many credit checks have been made against you. More is worse. When you are refused credit you need to find out why, but usually the automated system won&#x2019;t tell you.  Perhaps the only way to find out is to do a credit check on yourself &#x2013; but not too often!</Paragraph><Paragraph>In future, networked computers will make increasingly complicated decisions, based on better ways of representing complex information, and the decisions of one computer will be fed into others.  No one will understand fully the way some of the decisions are made.   Some decision support systems have explanation facilities that produce a decision audit trail showing how the answer was derived from the input. But some decisions may be untraceable.</Paragraph></Section><Section><Title>Data mining</Title><Paragraph>Data mining is a new term for an activity that has had a long history. The major aims of data mining are the discovery of patterns and relationships in data that are stored in one or more large databases.  Data mining uses intelligent software agents called robots that travel around the Web looking for combinations of data that are considered to be valuable.   It uses a variety of techniques from traditional statistical analysis to modern AI.</Paragraph><Paragraph>Another key aspect of data mining is the automated discovery of rules that identify common patterns across large amounts of data and enable the system to make predictions based on these patterns.</Paragraph><Paragraph>For example, if you have a Tesco loyalty card, or are a regular shopper at Amazon, you may have noticed that the recommendations and vouchers you receive are often personalised. This is based not only on the data the company has on your previous transactions, but also the shopping habits of other &#x2018;similar&#x2019; shoppers.</Paragraph><Paragraph>An area of increasing concern is the accuracy of stored personal data, and the ways these data are used. In the UK, this is the subject of legislation that defines, for example, that data should only be kept for as long as is necessary and that they should only be used for limited purposes. As the &#x2018;human actuators&#x2019; of a larger corporate machine, it is important that we are aware of how our personal data are processed and used to influence our behaviour.</Paragraph></Section><Section><Title>Robots on the stock market</Title><Paragraph>Investing in   the stock market involves buying shares when you think their price is low and about to rise, and selling shares when you think their price is high and about to fall. But how do people make the decision whether to buy or sell?</Paragraph><Paragraph>Sometimes shares are bought and sold on the basis of special knowledge, such as the track record of the new chairman, or the fact that a new product has passed its safety trials.  But often investors track the prices of their shares, and use this information to decide whether or not to sell.  If your shares have increased in price steadily over the last few weeks, you may decide to sell and take a profit while you can.  If your share price has been dropping recently you may decide to sell, before you lose too much.  Or you may have other strategies.</Paragraph><Paragraph>In a situation like this, the investor is making a classification decision like &#x2018;buy&#x2019; or &#x2018;sell&#x2019; on the basis of a sequence of numbers.  Does that sound familiar?  Recall that in RobotLab 8 the robot made a decision that stools were &#x2018;upright&#x2019; and &#x2018;fallen over&#x2019; on the basis of a sequence of two numbers.  Banks realised the importance of neural networks from an early stage, and have used them for making investment decisions for many years.</Paragraph></Section><Section><Title>Robots running the roads and railways</Title><Paragraph>In many towns and cities the road system is managed using networks of computers, sensors and actuators.  For example, traffic lights act as a kind of actuator, causing traffic to start and stop.  The behaviour of traffic can be very complex, and controlling it is often delegated to computers.  This can be at the level of an individual computer-controlled traffic light, or increasingly, lights that are linked together to optimise system-wide traffic flows.</Paragraph><Figure><Image src="\\dog\PrintLive\Courses\t184\web\e1i1\published\images\lesson_9\t184_lesson9_f05.gif" height="" width="100%" alt="" id="" webthumbnail="" x_imagesrc="t184_lesson9_f05.gif" x_imagewidth="495" x_imageheight="170"/><SourceReference><ItemRights><OwnerRef/><ItemRef/><ItemAcknowledgement><font val="Verdana"><language val="">www.traffic-wales.com. Crown copyright material is reproduced with the permission of the controller of HMSO.</language></font></ItemAcknowledgement></ItemRights>HMSO</SourceReference></Figure><Paragraph>Similarly, railways use computers to schedule the allocation of tracks to particular trains, including predicting where the trains will be at given times.  Railway systems are subject to all kinds of unexpected events, and the computers are constantly rescheduling to take account of this. Again, the signals on railway tracks can be considered to be actuators, as can the points that direct the trains onto given lines.</Paragraph><Paragraph>Who is in charge of these systems?  Is there a single human being who has an overview of all the networked computers that are collectively making the decisions about where people can drive their cars, or on which line a particular train can travel?  In general there is not.  The particular behaviour of the system at any time <i>emerges </i>from the interactions of the many autonomous agents within it.</Paragraph><Paragraph>Usually this emergence is well engineered, and the system behaviour falls within specified limits.  Sometimes the emergent behaviour of the system is outside the specification and, in extreme cases, may break down altogether.</Paragraph><Figure><Image src="\\dog\PrintLive\Courses\t184\web\e1i1\published\images\lesson_9\t184_lesson9_f06.gif" height="" width="100%" alt="" id="" webthumbnail="" x_imagesrc="t184_lesson9_f06.gif" x_imagewidth="495" x_imageheight="366"/><Caption/></Figure><Paragraph>We take for granted the right to travel and a transportation system capable of getting us where we want to go.  But this ability to go anywhere in the world is based on a huge infrastructure that is increasingly computer controlled.  How close are we to the &#x2018;machines&#x2019; in Asimov&#x2019;s stories?</Paragraph></Section><Section><Title>Is the Internet a robot?</Title><Paragraph>A really important feature of computers is that they can be networked.  This means that, in principle, huge amounts of information are available on any connected PC.  In other words, the world is covered by a gigantic swarm of computers, each being more or less autonomous, and each being more or less intelligent.  The interactions of all these machines can produce emergent behaviour that no one planned.  Not understanding why a computer or network behaves in a given way is a common experience.  With our PCs we try the things we know, scratch our heads, curse Microsoft, and reboot in the hope that the machine will restart in a normal state and become predictable again.</Paragraph><Paragraph>The Internet is fast becoming one of the most complex artificial systems on Earth.  It has many autonomous parts, and these self-organise to produce great complexity.  It is believed that there is great latent wealth in the uncollated data in the system, and data mining is becoming a big industry.</Paragraph><Figure><Image src="\\dog\PrintLive\Courses\t184\web\e1i1\published\images\lesson_9\t184_lesson9_f07.gif" height="" width="100%" alt="" id="" webthumbnail="" x_imagesrc="t184_lesson9_f07.gif" x_imagewidth="421" x_imageheight="298"/><Caption/><SourceReference><ItemRights><OwnerRef/><ItemRef><font val="Verdana"><language val="">All rights reserved.</language></font></ItemRef><ItemAcknowledgement/></ItemRights><font val="Verdana"><language val="">2003 WorldCom, Inc. </language></font></SourceReference></Figure><Paragraph>Can this huge system that we call the Internet be considered to be a robot?</Paragraph><Paragraph>Arguably, the Internet can sense the environment in many ways.  It is possible to attach web cams, microphones and many other sensors to the Internet.  The most common type of &#x2018;sensor&#x2019; remains the computer keyboard.  Based on this external information and other internal information, parts of the Internet can make decisions about what needs to be done next, and execute these decisions.</Paragraph><Paragraph>The Internet is not mobile, as such, but mobile agents can be connected through it.  Indeed, many of the domestic robots we have studied on this module are designed to interface with the Internet.    Maybe humans are the sensors and actuators of the &#x2018;Internet robot&#x2019;.</Paragraph><Paragraph>The Internet requires a lot of looking after by humans, but mostly it runs without human assistance, and it has great autonomy.  And the Internet can perform its function in the presence of great uncertainty, and so we consider it to be intelligent. However, the Internet is like a community of intelligent entities, or a swarm, rather than a single, intelligent entity.</Paragraph><Activity><Heading>Read</Heading><Question><Paragraph><InlineFigure><Image src="\\dog\PrintLive\nonCourse\design_templates\ICONS\Web\png's\42_pixels\book_42.png" height="" width="100%" alt="" id="" webthumbnail="" x_imagesrc="book_42.png" x_imagewidth="42" x_imageheight="42"/></InlineFigure>Read Chapter 9, &#x2018;The Evitable Conflict&#x2019;, of Asimov&#x2019;s book and answer the following SAQ.</Paragraph><Figure><Image src="\\dog\PrintLive\Courses\t184\web\e1i1\published\images\lesson_9\t184_lesson9_f08.gif" height="" width="100%" alt="" id="" webthumbnail="" x_imagesrc="t184_lesson9_f08.gif" x_imagewidth="107" x_imageheight="171"/><Caption/><SourceReference><font val="Verdana"><language val="">&#xA9; Harper Collins Publishers</language></font></SourceReference></Figure></Question></Activity><SAQ><Heading>SAQ 1</Heading><Question><NumberedList class="lower-alpha"><ListItem>What is the story about?</ListItem><ListItem>What is the main issue raised by the story?</ListItem><ListItem>Is this a source of concern?</ListItem></NumberedList></Question><Answer><NumberedList class="lower-alpha"><ListItem><Paragraph>The story is about the way the world is run, supported by &#x2018;the Machines&#x2019;: &#x2018;The Earth&#x2019;s economy is stable, and will <b>remain</b> stable, because it is based upon the decisions of calculating machines that have the good of humanity at heart through the overwhelming force of the First Law of Robotics.&#x2019; The Machines have positronic brains and &#x2018;in their own particular province of collecting and analysing a nearly infinite number of data and relationships thereof, in nearly infinitesimal time, they have progressed beyond the possibility of detailed human control.&#x2019;</Paragraph><Paragraph>Dr Susan Calvin, the robopsychologist talks to the Controller, Stephen Byerley, about small imbalances: World Steel is overproducing, the Mexican canal is behind schedule, and there are other similar problems. The machines seem to be making inexplicable errors, even though this is theoretically impossible.</Paragraph><Paragraph>Susan Calvin investigates and discovers that the problem is related to the Society for Humanity, an organisation that hates the Machines. Each of the corporations that is performing badly has people belonging to the Society. There are tensions between the sectors of the world, and the Northern Region where the Society is based, is in danger of losing influence. The suggestion is that these people are trying to destabilise the world to prevent this.</Paragraph><Paragraph>However, the Machines know that their instructions are being disobeyed and that humanity is in danger of economic disruption. So it is they that are causing the problems, in order to shake the anti-Machine people from their positions of power: &#x2018;Their first care, therefore, is to preserve themselves, for us. And so they are quietly taking care of the only elements left that threaten them. It is not the "Society for Humanity" which is shaking the boat so that the Machines may be destroyed. You have been looking at the reverse of the picture. Say rather that the Machine is shaking the boat &#x2013; <b>very</b> slightly &#x2013; just enough to shake loose those few which cling to the side for purposes the Machines consider harmful to Humanity.&#x2019;</Paragraph></ListItem><ListItem><Paragraph>The main issue of the story is that the Machines are running the human world, and humans don&#x2019;t understand how they are doing it, and cannot control it. Those who resist, like members of the Society for Humanity, are gently pushed out of their positions of power and neutralised. Stephen Byerley says &#x2018;But you are telling me, Susan, that the "Society for Humanity" is right; and that Mankind <b>has</b> lost its own say in its future&#x2019;, to which she replies: &#x2018;It never had any, really. It was always at the mercy of economic and sociological forces it did not understand &#x2013; at the whims of climate, and the fortunes of war. Now the Machines understand them; and no one can stop them, since the Machines will deal with them as they are dealing with the Society &#x2013; having, as they do, the greatest of weapons at their disposal, the absolute control of our economy. &#x2026; Think, that for all time, all conflicts are finally evitable [avoidable, not inevitable]. Only the Machines, from now on, are inevitable.&#x2019;</Paragraph></ListItem><ListItem><Paragraph>Viewed one way this is a source of concern for humanity. To what extent are humans really in control of the human world? As suggested in this lesson, to what extent are we already living in a great Internet-connected robot, serving it as its sensors and actuators? Our machines are getting progressively more intelligent all the time, and even now no-one really understands the details of what makes our socio-technical world work.</Paragraph><Paragraph>Viewed another way, this may not be a source for concern. We already live in this environment and most of us don&#x2019;t find it undermines our humanity. However, our machines don&#x2019;t have positronic brains with the first law built into them, so we cannot be sure that they will work towards the greater good of humanity. This suggests that, although there is no immediate threat of our machines taking over either actively or by default, we should be vigilant to make sure that humans retain control.</Paragraph></ListItem></NumberedList></Answer></SAQ><Paragraph>Asimov&#x2019;s story of the machines than run everything was remarkably prophetic, given that he wrote it at a time when the earliest computers were just being built by pioneers like Alan Turing.  In those days there were no office PCs and no networks.  Today, life without computers seems impossible, and many organisations could not function without them.</Paragraph><Paragraph>To what extent is modern society like the machines in this story?  Certainly our society is wired up, with millions of machines networked to each other.  Certainly there is a huge amount of information distributed between these machines.  And certainly these machines are making decisions that affect our lives and condition what we do.  These machines are networked to other parts of our physical infrastructure &#x2013; the roads, railways, and even the &#x2018;machines&#x2019; we live in that are our homes.</Paragraph><Paragraph>In some ways we are the hands and eyes of a massive autonomous system that has a life of its own.  But should we be concerned?  We may not feel that our individuality is challenged by being part of this enormous socio-technical system.  Even though machines do a lot of things autonomously, we can still feel that we are in control of our lives.</Paragraph></Section></Session><Session><Title>9.3 Cyborgs and super-humanoids</Title><Paragraph>In the previous session, I suggested that humans might be thought of as the sensors and actuators of some &#x2018;super-robot&#x2019;. In this session, you will look at a complementary idea &#x2013; that of machines being integrated into the human body.</Paragraph><InternalSection><Heading>Are we already cyborgs?</Heading><Paragraph>A few years ago I was walking with my friend Paul after a busy day. He was preoccupied because he had another commitment and was concerned another friend had not got the message that he would be late. On his ear he had a hands-free headset for his mobile phone. In his hands he had a notebook computer, which was picking up a wireless Internet signal allowing him to try to email his friend again. I thought to myself, is Paul a Cyborg? Although Paul&#x2019;s technological enhancements were not implants, they were improving his awareness and information processing capabilities.</Paragraph><Figure><Image src="\\dog\PrintLive\Courses\t184\web\e1i1\published\images\lesson_9\t184_lesson9_f09.jpg" height="" width="100%" alt="" id="" webthumbnail="" x_imagesrc="t184_lesson9_f09.jpg" x_imagewidth="350" x_imageheight="245"/><Caption/><SourceReference><font val="Verdana"><language val="">&#xA9; 2000 Wirth-Milyuns Productions.</language></font></SourceReference></Figure><Paragraph>What interests me about this is that Paul is not a technology freak, but he was prepared to attach objects to his body to enhance his performance, and I reflected on the argument we met in Lesson 4 of Ray Kurzweil, that people will augment their bodies with nanocomputers to make themselves superintelligent. Paul acted as though it was quite natural to extend his body and mind through his technological add-ons. How far is this from him going the whole way as Kurzweil suggests?</Paragraph><Paragraph>Many of us wear glasses, or have other aids to our senses that we consider quite normal. Many of us would be lost without our notebook computers and Internet connections. Are we already cyborgs? Presently none of these devices are hard-wired to bodies, but there are devices that can be connected to advantage. For example, artificial arms can be joined to nerves so that the user can control them consciously.</Paragraph><Paragraph>To some extent I think we are already cyborgs, in a minor way. I think it is very likely that some people will want to augment their abilities and become cyborgs with hard-wired add-ons. It&#x2019;s possible that some people will have almost all their bodies made of artificial parts, making the dividing line between human and robot more ambiguous.</Paragraph></InternalSection><Section><Title>Prosthetics and cyborgs</Title><Paragraph>Today it is routine to replace major parts of the human body with artificial parts. The technology of replacing a damaged hip joint is well established, and many people around the world have their lives considerably improved by such operations. Having a hip replaced seems as remote from being a robot as having one&#x2019;s teeth capped by the dentist.</Paragraph><Figure><Image src="\\dog\PrintLive\Courses\t184\web\e1i1\published\images\lesson_9\t184_lesson9_f10.jpg" height="" width="100%" alt="" id="" webthumbnail="" x_imagesrc="t184_lesson9_f10.jpg" x_imagewidth="197" x_imageheight="245"/><Caption>An artificial hip joint</Caption><SourceReference><ItemRights><OwnerRef/><ItemRef><font val="Verdana"><language val="">All rights reserved.</language></font></ItemRef><ItemAcknowledgement/></ItemRights><font val="Verdana"><language val="">HB Valdemar SURIN</language></font></SourceReference></Figure><Paragraph>Even the heart &#x2013; that part of the human machine essential for life &#x2013; can be replaced by a mechanical alternative, with increasing success. Somehow, these mechanical alternative &#x2018;spare parts&#x2019; don&#x2019;t seem to reduce our humanity in any way, or make us any more machine-like.</Paragraph><Figure><Image src="\\dog\PrintLive\Courses\t184\web\e1i1\published\images\lesson_9\t184_lesson9_f11.gif" height="" width="100%" alt="" id="" webthumbnail="" x_imagesrc="t184_lesson9_f11.gif" x_imagewidth="210" x_imageheight="210"/><Caption>An artificial heart</Caption><SourceReference><font val="Verdana"><language val="">Abiomed.</language></font></SourceReference></Figure><Paragraph>We seem to be prepared to accept that these distinctly non-biological replacement parts are acceptable within our bodies.</Paragraph><Paragraph>It seems that we can build and reconstruct almost every part of the human body. In the following clip from <i>Man&#x2013;Machine</i> a light sensitive microchip is inserted into a human eye to restore the function of a damaged retina.</Paragraph><Activity><Heading>Watch</Heading><Question><Paragraph><InlineFigure><Image src="\\dog\PrintLive\nonCourse\design_templates\ICONS\Web\png's\42_pixels\video_dvd_42.png" height="" width="100%" alt="" id="" webthumbnail="" x_imagesrc="video_dvd_42.png" x_imagewidth="42" x_imageheight="42"/> </InlineFigure> Watch the segment of Man&#x2013;Machine in which James May meets Dr Alan Chow and his retinal implant. This runs from about 8:56 to 12:33.  </Paragraph><Paragraph>A full <olink targetdoc="James May DVD transcript">transcript for the DVD</olink> is available. You can also open it from the <olink targetdoc="More resources">More resources</olink> section of the website.</Paragraph></Question></Activity><Paragraph>These examples have been prosthetics which repair damage and restore normal functioning to our bodies, but some people speculate that in the future we will enhance our bodies with artificial sensors and actuators that will greatly add to our capabilities.</Paragraph><Paragraph>So when does a human with prosthetic devices stop being a human and become a machine?</Paragraph><Paragraph>A cyborg is someone or something that is part animal and part machine: a combination of biological and mechanical components, lying somewhere on the spectrum between pure biological being and pure machine. The <i>Oxford English Dictionary Online</i> (1999) gives the following definition:</Paragraph><Quote><Paragraph>Cyborg. [Blend of CYB(ERNETIC a. and ORG(ANISM.] A person whose physical tolerances or capabilities are extended beyond normal human limitations by a machine or other external agency that modifies the body&#x2019;s functioning; an integrated man-machine system.</Paragraph><SourceReference>OED Online, 1999</SourceReference></Quote><Paragraph>By this definition, about 10% of the population are estimated to be cyborgs in the technical sense, including people with electronic pacemakers, artificial joints, drug implant systems, implanted corneal lenses and artificial skin.</Paragraph><Paragraph>One of the best known self-professed cyborgs is <a href="http://www.kevinwarwick.org/">Professor Kevin Warwick</a> of Reading University (who was mentioned in Lesson 4).</Paragraph><Quote><Paragraph>In 1998 [Kevin] shocked the international scientific community by having a silicon chip transponder surgically implanted in his left arm. A series of further implant experiments have taken place in which Kevin&#x2019;s nervous system was linked to a computer. ... Kevin&#x2019;s new implant experiment called &#x2018;Project Cyborg&#x2019; got underway in March 2002 and is providing exciting results.</Paragraph><Paragraph>The possibility exists to enhance human capabilities. To harness the ever increasing abilities of machine intelligence, to enable extra sensory input and to communicate in a much richer way, using thought alone. Kevin Warwick has taken the first steps on this path, using himself as a guinea pig test subject receiving, by surgical operation, technological implants connected to his central nervous system.</Paragraph><SourceReference><a href="http://www.kevinwarwick.com/">http://www.kevinwarwick.com</a></SourceReference></Quote><Paragraph>In Project Cyborg, Professor Warwick had a chip with a radio transmitter implanted into his arm and connected to his nervous system:</Paragraph><Quote><Paragraph>A number of experiments have been carried out using the signals detected by the array, most notably Professor Warwick was able to control an electric wheelchair and an intelligent artificial hand, developed by Dr Peter Kyberd, using this neural interface. In addition to being able to measure the nerve signals transmitted down Professor Warwick&#x2019;s left arm, the implant was also able to create artificial sensation by stimulating individual electrodes within the array. This was demonstrated with the aid of Kevin&#x2019;s wife Irena and a second, less complex implant connecting to her nervous system.</Paragraph></Quote><Paragraph>Professor Warwick sent electrical signals to his shoulder and back, and these were detected by electrodes taped onto his skin. He claimed that the implants made his experiment different from traditional techniques of controlling external actuators, such as prosthetic arms. A radical demonstration of the effectiveness of this technique was provided by the performance artist Stelarc, who used it to control a &#x2018;third arm&#x2019;. Stelarc also experimented with means of external control, using the Internet to trigger muscle spasms in his arms and legs. Take a look at Stelarc&#x2019;s work on <a href="http://www.stelarc.va.com.au/">his website</a>.</Paragraph><Figure><Image src="\\dog\PrintLive\Courses\t184\web\e1i1\published\images\lesson_9\t184_lesson9_f12.jpg" height="" width="100%" alt="" id="" webthumbnail="" x_imagesrc="t184_lesson9_f12.jpg" x_imagewidth="220" x_imageheight="331"/><Caption>The perfomance artist Stelarc</Caption><SourceReference><ItemRights><OwnerRef/><ItemRef/><ItemAcknowledgement><font val="Verdana"><language val="">Cyborg Frictions, Dampfzentrale, 1999. Photographer - Dominik Landwehr, Construction of Robot - F18, </language></font><font val="Verdana"><language val="">Hamburg</language></font><font val="Verdana"><language val="">. STELARC.</language></font></ItemAcknowledgement></ItemRights><font val="Verdana"><language val="">Landwehr, 1999</language></font></SourceReference></Figure><Paragraph>Another potential interface between man and machine is illustrated in the following video clip from <i>Man&#x2013;Machine</i>. The &#x2018;Mind-Enhanced Roving Chair&#x2019; is a wheelchair controlled by electrical activity picked up from the brain. The subject imagines making a movement and their brain activity is recorded; if two different &#x2018;thoughts&#x2019; can be distinguished, the wheelchair can be steered left and right.</Paragraph><Activity><Heading>Watch</Heading><Question><Paragraph><InlineFigure><Image src="\\dog\PrintLive\nonCourse\design_templates\ICONS\Web\png's\42_pixels\video_dvd_42.png" height="" width="100%" alt="" id="" webthumbnail="" x_imagesrc="video_dvd_42.png" x_imagewidth="42" x_imageheight="42"/> </InlineFigure> Watch the segment of <i>Man&#x2013;Machine</i> in which James May tries out Dr Christopher James&#x2019; Mind-Enhanced Roving Chair. This runs from about 27:25 to 32:08. </Paragraph><Paragraph>A full <olink targetdoc="James May DVD transcript">transcript for the DVD</olink> is available. You can also open it from the <olink targetdoc="More resources">More resources</olink> section of the website.</Paragraph></Question></Activity><Paragraph>The signals are picked up by external electrodes so no surgical intervention is necessary. However, it seems difficult in practice to determine distinct signals from the subject. Do you think further training would make this a more practical proposition? Would the interface be better if the electrodes were permanently implanted? Could it be used to control something more complex?</Paragraph><SAQ><Heading>SAQ 2</Heading><Question><Paragraph>Read the following extract from &#x2018;21st Century Lives: Kevin Warwick&#x2019;:</Paragraph><Quote><Paragraph>Professor Kevin Warwick has been thinking hard about the 21st century. His conclusion? That people won&#x2019;t have much of a role in it. &#x2018;I think humanity is, at the moment, obsolescent,&#x2019; Warwick says. &#x2018;It&#x2019;s on its way out. Either we can really suffer at the hands of machines more intelligent than we are, or we can look to upgrade humans and make ourselves more intelligent.&#x2019;</Paragraph><SourceReference>abc news, 2000 </SourceReference></Quote><NumberedList class="lower-alpha"><ListItem>Do you agree with Professor Warwick that people won&#x2019;t have much of a role in the 21st century?</ListItem><ListItem>Do you agree that we could or should upgrade ourselves to make ourselves more intelligent?</ListItem><ListItem>If I had a chip implanted and connected to my nervous system, and a similar chip embedded in my dog Tiggy, would I be able to feel what it is like to be a dog?</ListItem><ListItem>Is it possible for one cyborg to know what it feels like to be another cyborg, if both share the same implanted devices?</ListItem></NumberedList></Question><Answer><NumberedList class="lower-alpha"><ListItem>Professor Warwick predicted that robots will take over the world (Lesson 6). But intelligence is not a prerequisite for political or military power.  I agree with Whitby and Oliver (Lesson 4) that we should be vigilant, though I don&#x2019;t believe that robots will take over in the 21st century. I think human beings will continue to have the role they have always had. However, I think that some human beings will upgrade themselves with add-on hardware.</ListItem><ListItem>It is possible that we will use prosthetic devices to improve our abilities, as we already do with eye glasses, personal computers, telephones, and many other technologies.  There may be advantages in interfacing devices with our nervous systems.</ListItem><ListItem>I think it is impossible for any animal to know what any other animal feels.  I think we interpret the observations we make in terms of what we feel ourselves.  I don&#x2019;t think it is possible for me to know what it is like to be Tiggy, for the same reason that I will never know what it is like to be a robot.</ListItem><ListItem>I think it is possible to know what it&#x2019;s like to be a cyborg yourself, but even if another cyborg&#x2019;s devices give exactly the same signals as yours, you cannot know whether your nervous system responds in the same way as theirs.</ListItem></NumberedList></Answer></SAQ><Activity><Heading>Watch (optional)</Heading><Question><Paragraph><InlineFigure><Image src="\\dog\PrintLive\nonCourse\design_templates\ICONS\Web\png's\42_pixels\video_42.png" height="" width="100%" alt="" id="" webthumbnail="" x_imagesrc="video_42.png" x_imagewidth="42" x_imageheight="42"/></InlineFigure> If you wish, you can see a number of short <a href="http://podcast.open.ac.uk/oulearn/engineering-and-technology/podcast-t209-ict">clips about cyborgs</a>, including interviews with Kevin Warwick, at the <a href="http://podcast.open.ac.uk/">OU podcast site</a>. The same videos can be found at the <a href="http://www.youtube.com/user/oulearn">OU channel</a> on YouTube and the <a href="http://www.open.ac.uk/itunes/">OU channel of iTunes U</a>.</Paragraph></Question></Activity></Section><Section><Title>Super-humanoids</Title><Paragraph>The RoboCup Challenge is to make a team of humanoid football players capable of beating the World Cup holders by 2050. If this were to happen what would be the implications?</Paragraph><Paragraph>The improvement in technology implied by this would include:</Paragraph><BulletedList><ListItem>fast biped robots that can move at least as fast as humans;</ListItem><ListItem>soft robots that do not cause injury when humans collide with them;</ListItem><ListItem>strong robots that can withstand collisions with human players;</ListItem><ListItem>agile robots that twist, turn and stop, even when travelling at speed;</ListItem><ListItem>robots with energy and endurance;</ListItem><ListItem>robots with excellent vision, able to see the ball and other players;</ListItem><ListItem>robots able to navigate well and move around the football pitch quickly;</ListItem><ListItem>team robots with swarm organisation capabilities;</ListItem><ListItem>intelligent robots that can understand the rules and apply them;</ListItem><ListItem>robots that can learn how other teams play and change their strategies.</ListItem></BulletedList><Paragraph>To compete on their own terms with these &#x2018;super-humanoids&#x2019;, would we have to field teams of technology enhanced cyborgs? Is this the way that sport will go? Or will there be rules prohibiting cyber-augmentation, in the same way that body-enhancing drugs are illegal today?</Paragraph><Figure><Image src="\\dog\PrintLive\Courses\t184\web\e1i1\published\images\lesson_9\t184_lesson9_f13.jpg" height="" width="100%" alt="" id="" webthumbnail="" x_imagesrc="t184_lesson9_f13.jpg" x_imagewidth="200" x_imageheight="138"/><Caption/><SourceReference><font val="Verdana"><language val="">&#xA9; 2003 Honda Motor Co. Ltd.</language></font></SourceReference></Figure><Paragraph>What else might super-humanoids do apart from playing football. Would they be able to take the place of humans in human affairs? Would such a robot be able to hold a responsible position, such as being a local priest, doctor, or even the mayor?</Paragraph></Section></Session><Session><Title>9.4 Robots in charge</Title><Activity><Heading>Read</Heading><Question><Paragraph><InlineFigure><Image src="\\dog\PrintLive\nonCourse\design_templates\ICONS\Web\png's\42_pixels\book_42.png" height="" width="100%" alt="" id="" webthumbnail="" x_imagesrc="book_42.png" x_imagewidth="42" x_imageheight="42"/></InlineFigure> Read Chapter 8, &#x2018;Evidence&#x2019;, of <i>I, Robot</i> and answer the   following SAQ.</Paragraph><Figure><Image src="\\dog\PrintLive\Courses\t184\web\e1i1\published\images\lesson_9\t184_lesson9_f14.gif" height="" width="100%" alt="" id="" webthumbnail="" x_imagesrc="t184_lesson9_f14.gif" x_imagewidth="107" x_imageheight="171"/><Caption/></Figure></Question></Activity><SAQ><Heading>SAQ 3</Heading><Question><NumberedList class="lower-alpha"><ListItem>What is the above story about?</ListItem><ListItem>What is the main issue raised by the story?</ListItem><ListItem>Is this a source of concern?</ListItem></NumberedList></Question><Answer><NumberedList class="lower-alpha"><ListItem><Paragraph>The story is about the politician, Francis Quinn who goes to US Robotics to suggest that another politician, Stephen Byerley, is a robot because he has never been seen to eat, drink or sleep. Some days later Dr Susan Calvin confronts Byerley, and offers him an apple which he eats. But she says this proves nothing, since anyone capable of making such an excellent human-like robot would not neglect a few gadgets to take care of such things as eating, sleeping and elimination. Byerley is a lawyer and is standing for mayor, and plans to let his opponent Quinn make the accusation that he is a robot. Byerley boasts he has never prosecuted an innocent man, and he is against the death penalty. By prosecuting guilty individuals he &#x2018;protects the greater number and thus adheres to Rule One at maximum potential&#x2019;. When the news broke that Byerley might be a robot, the Fundamentalists, who require no reason to detest robots, became agitated and threatened violence. Quinn arranged for Byerley to be harassed at home, trying to prove he was a robot by illegal means, such as taking an X-ray photograph, but Byerley easily resists because of his expert knowledge as a lawyer.</Paragraph><Paragraph>Byerley had a &#x2018;crippled&#x2019; teacher, John, once a lawyer, with a government licence as a biophysicist with his own laboratory. Quinn suggests that John is the real Byerley and the other is his robot creation.</Paragraph><Paragraph>Byerley plans to speak to a Fundamentalist mob outside his home, against his campaign manager&#x2019;s advice. A man appears in the crowd and Byerley gets the police to allow him up to the balcony to put his question before the TV cameras. The man says &#x2018;Hit me! You say you&#x2019;re not a robot. Prove it. You can&#x2019;t hit a human, you monster.&#x2019; Byerley hits him, proving that he&#x2019;s not a robot because this would break the first law.</Paragraph><Paragraph>Some days later, when talking to mayor-elect Byerley, Dr Calvin says &#x2018;there is one time when a robot may strike a human being without breaking the First Law. Just one time ... When the human to be struck is merely another robot.&#x2019; The implication is that Byerley&#x2019;s creator also made the robot that challenged Byerley to hit him.</Paragraph></ListItem><ListItem><Paragraph>The main issue in this story is whether a robot can perform responsible human functions like being mayor. Dr Susan Calvin certainly thinks they can, and that they would do the job better than many humans because of the first law. There are other issues in the story, such as the exploitation of the predictable mob, and how easy it is to anticipate malign human behaviour &#x2013; because humans do not obey the three laws!</Paragraph></ListItem><ListItem><Paragraph>I find the prospect of a robot mayor difficult to comprehend. Like many people I am not impressed by most politicians, and the idea of a politician unable to act badly or foolishly is very attractive. However, I find the idea of surrendering power to a robot very worrying, so I suppose I&#x2019;d rather stick with the humans we have. There are exceptional human politicians driven by the highest motives, and that would be my ideal.</Paragraph></ListItem></NumberedList></Answer></SAQ><Paragraph>The story you have just read raises some disturbing questions about humans and robots. The doomsday predictions that robots will take over and treat us badly overlook the possibility that robots may actually run things better than us. After all, we do harm other humans. It is part of human nature to give offence to, be offended by or, worse, inflict physical harm on other people. Under the thin veneer of society, we are animals, and we are capable of behaving very badly to each other. By comparison, Asimov&#x2019;s robots are unable to harm a human, even down to hurting a human&#x2019;s feelings. Why shouldn&#x2019;t a robot mayor be driven by the highest motives which, combined with intelligence and hard work, would enable a robot politician to selflessly deliver what is best for the electors?</Paragraph><Paragraph>In this story, Dr Susan Calvin makes some remarkable observations about robots as compared to humans. When asked &#x2018;Are robots so different from men, mentally?&#x2019; she replies &#x2018;Robots are essentially decent&#x2019;, implying that humans are not.</Paragraph><Paragraph>Later she says:</Paragraph><Quote><Paragraph>I like robots. I like them considerably better than I do human beings. If a robot can be created capable of being a civil executive [such as Mayor], I think he&#x2019;d make the best one possible. By the laws of Robotics, he&#x2019;d be incapable of harming humans, incapable of tyranny, of corruption, of stupidity, of prejudice. And after he had served a decent term, he would leave, even though he were immortal, because it would be impossible for him to hurt humans by letting them know that a robot had ruled them. It would be most ideal.</Paragraph></Quote><Paragraph>Thus the suggestion is that robots could not only take over human functions, but if they obeyed Asimov&#x2019;s laws, they could make a better job of them than humans.</Paragraph><Paragraph>How would a robot mayor cope with the conflicting demands of the electorate? Ethical arguments often make use of the term &#x2018;the greater good&#x2019; to justify particular actions. Later in the lesson we will examine to what extent a robot operating under the constraints of Asimov&#x2019;s laws could appeal to this idea of the &#x2018;greater good&#x2019; when making decisions in which there are winners and losers.</Paragraph><Section><Title>Robot bosses</Title><Paragraph>Human societies are structured in ways that give some people authority over others. In organisations such as the military this authority can be absolute. And in industry, bosses have the authority to tell other people what to do. Usually the authority of a boss is underpinned by sanctions that can be applied for non-compliance. In the military, punishments can be very severe. In industry and civil occupations, punishments can include fines and, ultimately, dismissal.</Paragraph><Paragraph>But the application of sanctions is usually the last resort. Most people do what they are told because it makes sense to do so. If you want your company to survive and protect your job, it makes sense to cooperate with your boss &#x2013; and it makes sense for them to cooperate with their boss. And it makes sense for the bosses at every level to cooperate with the people they manage. In today&#x2019;s world &#x2018;people skills&#x2019; are very important in getting things done.</Paragraph><Paragraph>Suppose a robot like Stephen Byerley in Asimov&#x2019;s book were elected as mayor. What would be the implications of this? In the United Kingdom, most mayors are council leaders. This means that they have risen through the ranks to their current position. Sometimes this happens because people are &#x2018;charismatic&#x2019;, i.e. they have something about them that makes people want to follow them. Charisma can reflect personal charm and the ability to make people feel comfortable, or it can reflect ruthless authority that will not be faced down. Either way, in politics it must be accompanied by a conviction in one&#x2019;s policies and an unstoppable desire to prevail.</Paragraph><Figure><Image src="\\dog\PrintLive\Courses\t184\web\e1i1\published\images\lesson_9\t184_lesson9_f15.gif" height="" width="100%" alt="" id="" webthumbnail="" x_imagesrc="t184_lesson9_f15.gif" x_imagewidth="96" x_imageheight="121"/><Caption/></Figure><Paragraph>So a robot mayor must have the conviction that the policies it proposes are the right ones, and the plans it has to put those polices into practice will succeed. What about its political opponents, and even its political allies? As the robot struggles to get power, others may be left disappointed. Members of its own political group must give way to its more charismatic personality. Members of opposition groups must suffer the humiliation of losing elections to the robot, and the frustration of seeing the implementation of policies that they oppose. All of this contradicts the first law. Surely a robot could not become a politician without repeatedly breaking the first law.</Paragraph><Paragraph>A robot boss that obeyed the second law could be a contradiction in terms. How could a robot manager take orders from those it managed? For example, a human employee might be given the instruction to go and fetch something, but it is not unknown that that employee might respond by telling its human boss to go and fetch it themself. How would a robot react to such insubordination? Would it obey the command, in which case who would be the boss?</Paragraph><Paragraph>The possibility of having robots in authority does not sit easily with either the first or second law. Asimov himself realised this when he introduced the zeroth law, discussed in Session 3 of Lesson 6. The zeroth law allows the robot to harm individual humans when the greater good of humanity is at stake.</Paragraph><Paragraph>This law raises the question as to whether &#x2018;the greater good of humanity&#x2019; is meaningful and whether this idea could be implemented in a positronic brain in a practical way. This idea suggests that &#x2018;the good&#x2019; of humanity is being optimised, and even that there is a global optimum &#x2013; some absolutely best way to do things which optimises everything. Perhaps one starting point would be to embed the UN&#x2019;s Universal Declaration of Human Rights in the robot in some way and ensure that the robot upheld it. However, as you saw in Lesson 7, life is characterised by many competing criteria and there often have to be trade-offs. Furthermore, life is complex and there are few problems that have a single global optimum, leaving the pragmatic necessity of accepting relatively good local optima.</Paragraph><Paragraph>In a world where there may be several levels of management, or government, how would robots cope with being at the top of a hierarchical management tree with human and robot underlings spread across the various management levels? Would the robot chief command robots to do jobs that would be dangerous for humans, and give the humans other safer jobs to do? Would a robot feel comfortable giving other robots jobs that humans could not do?</Paragraph></Section><Section><Title>Robot teachers</Title><Paragraph>Could robots be used in schools &#x2013; as learning aids, teaching assistants or fully qualified teachers? You might think that they&#x2019;d be perfect for subjects such as physics and maths! But how might a robot maintain discipline in the classroom?</Paragraph><Paragraph>Perhaps the presence of a robot would make lessons so interesting and inspiring that children would not want to misbehave. Perhaps the individual tuition that large numbers of trained robot teachers would permit would have a similar effect. But even the best human teachers sometimes have to cope with disruptive children. No doubt a robot would have to impose discipline too. Below is one child&#x2019;s view of a robot teacher &#x2013; with eyes in the back of her head! No child is going to put one over on her!</Paragraph><Figure><Image src="\\dog\PrintLive\Courses\t184\web\e1i1\published\images\lesson_9\t184_lesson9_f16.jpg" height="" width="100%" alt="" id="" webthumbnail="" x_imagesrc="t184_lesson9_f16.jpg" x_imagewidth="367" x_imageheight="328"/><Caption/></Figure><Paragraph>Let us suppose that robot development leads in some way towards the development of robots that somehow embody the major characteristics of the three laws. How could such a robot teacher impose discipline without breaking the three laws? Since education is considered to be in children&#x2019;s own best interests, the robot teacher would not let a child come to harm by not being educated to their full potential (first law). This has higher potential than the child possibly telling the robot teacher to go away (second law). But how would a robot teacher cope with teaching people to play a potentially painful contact sport, such as rugby? And would robot trainers be able to teach soldiers to fire a gun?</Paragraph><Paragraph>Despite their ability to access and process huge databases of information, robots are unlikely to be as good as human teachers in the foreseeable future. This is because they, unlike humans, are unable to search these databases and make connections between different bits of information. Robots and intelligent systems may be able to perform well in some knowledge domains, but their performance can degrade completely when the domain shifts. There are, however, many computerised intelligent tutors that operate in particular domains, as well as expert systems that provide decision support in many settings, such as law and medicine.</Paragraph><Paragraph>Children in need of additional learning support in specific areas might benefit from being taught by robots. For example, playing educational games with robots might help to improve children&#x2019;s numeracy skills. Unlike human teachers, robots do not get tired (battery packs allowing!), no matter how many times they have to repeat things.</Paragraph><Figure><Image src="\\dog\PrintLive\Courses\t184\web\e1i1\published\images\lesson_9\t184_lesson9_f17.jpg" height="" width="100%" alt="" id="" webthumbnail="" x_imagesrc="t184_lesson9_f17.jpg" x_imagewidth="372" x_imageheight="264"/><Caption>Million dollar machine</Caption><SourceReference><ItemRights><OwnerRef/><ItemRef/><ItemAcknowledgement><font val="Verdana"><language val="">RoboMedia, Inc., Hainesport, NJ. 08036 LifeSkills4Kids&#x2122;.</language></font></ItemAcknowledgement></ItemRights><font val="Verdana"><language val="">RoboMedia, 2002</language></font></SourceReference></Figure><Paragraph>In fact, robot teachers are commercially available already. The American company <a href="http://www.lifeskills4kids.com/assembly-program.html">LifeSkills4Kids</a> makes a robot, the Million Dollar Machine (MDM), that delivers educational packages. The MDM is not an autonomous robot in the way we have defined it on this module, since it is teleoperated and is given a voice by a hidden human. But it does suggest that robots could be an attractive teaching medium for children. The studies of the RoboFesta Robotics Outreach Group at the Open University suggest that children are highly motivated to learn when they engage in robotics-related activities. However, this is different from being taught by a robot teacher, and very different from a robot being in charge and in authority.</Paragraph></Section><Section><Title>Robot medics</Title><Paragraph>Doctors and nurses are authority figures in human societies since they have specialist knowledge about the human body. When doctors tell people that they need operations, it is normal for them to explain the reasons in layman&#x2019;s terms. The patient may be given a choice, but if they decide to have treatment, they generally assume that the doctor will take full control of the situation. What if the doctor or nurse were a robot? Would people submit so readily to their authority?</Paragraph><Figure><Image src="\\dog\PrintLive\Courses\t184\web\e1i1\published\images\lesson_9\t184_lesson9_f18.gif" height="" width="100%" alt="" id="" webthumbnail="" x_imagesrc="t184_lesson9_f18.gif" x_imagewidth="136" x_imageheight="208"/><Caption/></Figure><Paragraph>It is speculated that swarms of microscopic nanorobots may be used in medicine. For example, in an article called <a href="http://www.irfi.org/articles/articles_101_150/nanotechnology.htm">Nanotechnology</a>, Professor Ibrahim B. Syed of the University of Louisville School of Medicine writes:</Paragraph><Quote><Paragraph>Nanomedicine deals with (1) the comprehensive monitoring, control, construction, repair, defense, and improvement of all human biological systems, working from the molecular level, using engineered nanodevices and nanostructures; (2) the science and technology of diagnosing, treating, and preventing disease and traumatic injury, of relieving pain, and of preserving and improving human health, using molecular tools and molecular knowledge of the human body; (3) the employment of molecular machine systems to address medical problems, using molecular knowledge to maintain and improve human health at the molecular scale. Cosmetic nanosurgery done with simple nanomachines (no on-board computers, for example) could change hair color, cause hair to grow or not to grow in specific locations, keep teeth clean and skin smooth, etc., all far more effectively than with current day treatments.</Paragraph></Quote><Quote><Paragraph/></Quote><Paragraph>To what extent is a swarm of nanorobots autonomous and in control? Would you allow your body to be invaded by thousands of tiny robots? Would you subject yourself to their authority? What if a human doctor prescribed such a treatment? Is there any difference between this and a doctor prescribing other medicines?</Paragraph><Paragraph>Intelligent computer systems have been developed widely for use by doctors in a decision support role. The doctor can enter a list of presented symptoms and will receive a list of possible conditions in return. In the UK, the NHS Direct telephone helpline provides a link to a qualified nurse to provide people at home with a first point of call if they are unable to go to a casualty department, or if they are unsure as to whether an ailment is severe enough to merit a visit to the doctor. Advice like this could come from a system like Emily, the intelligent telephone call handler from Lesson 4, which used a tree structure to order lists of possible questions based on previous answers.</Paragraph><Paragraph>But how comfortable would you be if you knew the diagnosis of the illness or prescription of the medicine were based on an initial recommendation or suggestion from a computer program? There are two issues here:</Paragraph><BulletedList><ListItem>Who is ultimately responsible for the diagnosis?</ListItem><ListItem>How is the message delivered to you &#x2013; e.g. by a nurse, a doctor, a robot or a virtual reality avatar?</ListItem></BulletedList><Paragraph>If a doctor and a nurse both ask you a series of questions as determined by an intelligent decision support system, for minor ailments you would probably accept the nurse&#x2019;s diagnosis. However, for anything more serious, you would probably want an expert doctor&#x2019;s opinion. We ultimately want people to be arbiters of decisions because machines can malfunction. For the bigger decisions in life, we tend to trust the human professionals whose lives are spent making similar decisions.</Paragraph></Section><Section><Title>Robot policemen</Title><Paragraph>The police have different roles in different countries. In Britain the police fight social crimes such as burglary, assault and disorder. Alongside this, the police fight serious crime such as racketeering, drug trafficking, bank robbery and so on. The work of the police can be seen in terms of crime prevention, criminal detection and prosecution. A large part of police work involves collecting information and piecing it together to recognise patterns of illegal or antisocial activity. Increasingly, data mining of databases can be used to identify such patterns.</Paragraph><Paragraph>In the context of gathering and interpreting forensic evidence, intelligent computer systems might make excellent police aids. For example, fingerprint identification would be virtually impossible were it not for computers automating the task. In this context, robots might make excellent policemen. Equipped with cameras, sensitive microphones, and other sensors, a robot could be a very efficient way of collecting information. This could be particularly so for swarms of robot policemen on reconnaissance missions, for example, collecting evidence about people behaving suspiciously. This could provide raw information, but on its own this would not be particularly useful. The effectiveness of police work comes from correlating a wide variety of information. To what extent would robots be able to obtain information from conversations? Could there be a &#x2018;chatty robot&#x2019;, capable of extracting information verbally from potential witnesses? Would people accept robots collecting information surreptitiously, or would it be considered an intolerable invasion of privacy?</Paragraph><Figure><Image src="\\dog\PrintLive\Courses\t184\web\e1i1\published\images\lesson_9\t184_lesson9_18a.jpg" height="" width="100%" alt="" id="" webthumbnail="" x_imagesrc="t184_lesson9_18a.jpg" x_imagewidth="77" x_imageheight="140"/><SourceReference><font val="Verdana"><language val="">&#xA9; Orion Pictures/MGM</language></font></SourceReference></Figure><Paragraph>There is a sinister aspect to robot policemen. Would they be allowed to use &#x2018;justifiable&#x2019; force when arresting people? Would a robot be subject to police complaints procedures? What if they were to be used for illegal purposes or to suppress the population for political ends? Could there be a robot police state? At present few people would accept autonomous robots having the power of the police. I find the idea that a machine could physically detain or arrest me or anyone else intolerable. See the <a href="http://robocoparchive.com/">Robocop archive website</a>, an unofficial website for the Robocop movies of the late 1980s and early 90s.</Paragraph></Section><Section><Title>Robot judges and juries</Title><Paragraph>Suppose that after being arrested by a robot policeman, you are brought before a robot judge and a robot jury. The judge&#x2019;s job is to hear all the evidence for and against you, guide the jury on points of law as they relate to your case, and sentence you if you are found guilty. Would you accept any of this authority?</Paragraph><Paragraph>It is likely that the robot judge would know more law, and know it better, than a human judge. Computerised decision support is well established in legal circles to identify precedents and find other information.</Paragraph><Paragraph>Magistrates have procedures which they have to follow in various situations, such as when sentencing an offender. A machine could just as easily do this, and probably do it more consistently too, since magistrates&#x2019; sentences on some offences are quite variable across the UK, notwithstanding guidance provided from the Lord Chief Justice.</Paragraph><Paragraph>Also a robot judge could be completely without prejudice. Would you prefer a robot judge with no gender and no social background, to the middle-class white males that dominate the judiciary in the UK? Perhaps a miscarriage of justice would be less likely with a robot judge?</Paragraph><Paragraph>What about that robot jury? Would you trust &#x2018;twelve good robots and true&#x2019; to judge you? Human juries have twelve members in order to get a variety of people, to give a representative view of the &#x2018;average person&#x2019;. Of course, the average person does not exist, and human juries reflect a mixture of values and viewpoints. In some sense this is the least worst option. If humans must be judged by others, then this is probably the best and most practical way that can be devised.</Paragraph><Figure><Image src="\\dog\PrintLive\Courses\t184\web\e1i1\published\images\lesson_9\t184_lesson9_f19.gif" height="" width="100%" alt="" id="" webthumbnail="" x_imagesrc="t184_lesson9_f19.gif" x_imagewidth="200" x_imageheight="218"/><Caption/></Figure><Paragraph>In the case of a jury, a kind of &#x2018;social intelligence&#x2019; is at work. We make extensive use of social intelligence when we form teams to perform particular tasks. Sometimes we need teams of people because there is too much work for one person to do. But sometimes we form teams of people to benefit from the variety of ideas team members produce. For example, what good would a focus group be if it only contained one person?</Paragraph><Paragraph>A robot jury suggests that each of the robots is capable of taking a personal view from which a collective decision will emerge. Is this possible? Even if two robots were identical at the time of manufacture, if they lived different lives their experiences could lead them to have different personalities. A similar nature-versus-nurture argument applies to human beings &#x2013; some part of us is carried in our genes while another part of us is conditioned by our experiences. What sort of variation in robot capabilities would we expect in the future? Could there be distinctions of social class, competency, and physical and mental health, etc? Could a robot jury thus have the same variety as a human jury?</Paragraph></Section><Section><Title>Robot parents and childminders</Title><Paragraph>Could robots make parents, and would children respond to a parent&#x2019;s normal discipline? Most of us would find this a strange idea, but many children have to manage without natural parents. Could the loving care of a robot mum and dad be better than living in local authority care? Would children respond well to robot parents? Would they do what they were told? Again this is a situation that reverses the second law, with the human obeying the commands of the robot.</Paragraph><Paragraph>Legislation in the UK prevents parents from harming their children, although parents can still smack a child. But could robots be brought into line? It seems unthinkable that a robot should inflict physical pain on a child. But should a robot parent be allowed to make the same sort of decisions that human parents make?</Paragraph><Paragraph>It seems unlikely that society will accept robot parents, but as robots get more able, they may become childcare assistants. There is an argument that if robots are mass produced and inexpensive, then every child could have their own dedicated carer, rather than sharing a single adult human with many other children. But would we want to go this far?</Paragraph><Paragraph>Children seem to think that they will be the boss of &#x2018;Robo-Mom&#x2019;. The drawing below by an eight-year old girl firmly establishes the robot as a domestic servant, whose job it is to do all the cleaning, dusting, polishing and other housework. She does have a button so you can talk to her through the speaker, but that&#x2019;s just to tell her what to do.</Paragraph><Figure><Image src="\\dog\PrintLive\Courses\t184\web\e1i1\published\images\lesson_9\t184_lesson9_f20.jpg" height="" width="100%" alt="" id="" webthumbnail="" x_imagesrc="t184_lesson9_f20.jpg" x_imagewidth="467" x_imageheight="346"/><Caption/></Figure><Paragraph>Of course, mums and dads do much more than put up shelves and cook the lunch. They provide the moral and emotional infrastructure that is essential when children are growing up. Could robots provide this subtle combination of authority, moral guidance and parental love? In the foreseeable future this seems very unlikely.</Paragraph><Paragraph>If you have a young child, you might like to read them the book <i>Robomum</i> by Emily Smith.</Paragraph></Section><Section><Title>Could robots take positions of responsibility?</Title><Paragraph>Do you agree with the suggestion that robots could make better politicians, teachers, judges and parents than humans?</Paragraph><Paragraph>My answer to this question is that, currently, it is based on a false assumption. We don&#x2019;t have robots with positronic brains that obey Asimov&#x2019;s laws, and some of the robots we have seem to have all the worst features of humans built into them. We deliberately make robots that kill. I am not impressed by Asimov&#x2019;s zeroth law, because it assumes that it is possible to judge what is in the interests of &#x2018;humanity&#x2019;.</Paragraph><Paragraph>For the foreseeable future, it is likely that robots will be the assistants of humans, rather than taking on roles of authority with complete autonomy. Most people want to see a &#x2018;human in the loop&#x2019;, who can take responsibility if anything goes wrong.</Paragraph><Paragraph>Many of the systems that we have in place today &#x2013; such as modern telephone networks and car engines &#x2013; would not operate were it not for computer control. In many senses, we have by necessity handed over control of these systems to computers. In the world of design and manufacture, in the absence of computers it would be impossible for humans to produce many modern everyday items. Without powerful computers there would be no powerful computers! This suggests that we are in some form of symbiosis with modern machines, at least in terms of design and manufacture.</Paragraph><Paragraph>Is it humans who still set the goals? Well, maybe. Many large organisations with large numbers of field engineers use automated computer systems to schedule the work of their employees (a real application of the Travelling Salesman problem). Jobs are automatically logged and the engineers provided with optimised, sequenced, itemised lists of jobs for them to complete each day. In government, economic policy is significantly influenced by complex mathematical models that are used to play out possible futures, such as the effect of a change in the base interest rate. So, are the computers running the show?</Paragraph><Paragraph>Our conclusion in this session is that at present, few people would knowingly subject themselves to the authority of robots or machines. However, we think most people would be comfortable with the idea of a robot aiding a human professional in a position of authority.</Paragraph></Section></Session><Session><Title>9.5 RobotLab9</Title><Paragraph>In this session you will be doing lab activities using RobotLab9.</Paragraph><Activity><Heading>RobotLab</Heading><Question><Paragraph><InlineFigure><Image src="\\dog\PrintLive\nonCourse\design_templates\ICONS\Web\png's\42_pixels\robotlab_42.png" height="" width="100%" alt="" id="" webthumbnail="" x_imagesrc="robotlab_42.png" x_imagewidth="42" x_imageheight="35"/></InlineFigure>Download the lab guide for <olink targetdoc="RobotLab9">RobotLab9</olink>. Work through the guide carefully and do the activities.</Paragraph></Question></Activity><Paragraph>Grateful acknowledgement is made to LEGO for use of components from the LEGO MindStorms RIS kit (<a href="http://www.legomindstorms.com/">www.legomindstorms.com</a>).</Paragraph></Session><Session><Title>9.6 Summary </Title><Paragraph>In this lesson you have considered to what extent our lives are already dominated by machines, and how we may interact with machines in the future.  Certainly the robots of the future will become much better and have a wider range of abilities than today&#x2019;s robots.  If and when we will see human-like humanoid robots is a matter of speculation.  The RoboCup organisation suggests a time horizon of 2050, and this may be reasonable, give or take a few decades.  However, there may be unforeseen obstacles that could put the project back for much longer.  Whether or not true humanoid robots ever appear, it is certain that we interact with robots now, that we will interact with more sophisticated robots in the future, and that robots will have an increasing impact on our lives.</Paragraph><Paragraph>I have suggested that most of us are deeply embedded in a complex socio-technical system that includes all the infrastructure of modern life: buildings, road, railways, and particularly telecommunications.  In some way this can be seen as a massive autonomous organism that is adapted to life on Earth. We are all parts of that organism, which in many respects seems to have a life of its own.</Paragraph><Paragraph>In some ways we might even be able to consider ourselves to be part of this organism, acting as its sensors and actuators.   We provide inputs to the organism, and it nurtures us by providing the things we need to survive. More contentiously, perhaps, I have suggested that this organism has its own behaviour, which processes information in ways not designed or controlled by human beings, and that it can be considered to be a robot.  Most people unconsciously, or consciously but unquestioningly, accept this symbiotic relationship with the parent organism, neither feeling threatened by it nor feeling any loss of individuality.</Paragraph><Paragraph>Less contentiously, we have introduced the idea of cyborgs, humans and other living things whose bodies are physically altered by technology, and the wide spectrum between human beings with no artificial parts and robots with no human parts. Some people argue that the advantages to be gained from implanted chips and other devices will be so great that everyone will want to be a cyborg in the future. Non-invasive aids to our senses such as eye glasses are common, while many people have aids such as pacemakers embedded in their bodies.  So, to some extent, many people are already cyborgs.</Paragraph><Paragraph>Having looked at humans living as part of a robotic super-culture, and being part-robot, we considered the possibility of giving robots control over all or part of our lives.  This is not the doomsday scenario that we considered in Lesson 4, but the pragmatic use of robots for things they can do better than us.  Subject to democratic controls, why shouldn&#x2019;t we have a robot mayor or robot Members of Parliament, if they do the job better than human politicians? However, this assumes that robots would obey the three laws, and currently there is no way to ensure that this would be the case.</Paragraph><Paragraph>So, in this lesson we have seen a number of different futures for robotics and society.  The first is an extension of what we have already: the socio-technical system that we are part of will get ever more intelligent and ever more complex.  At present we don&#x2019;t find it threatening most of the time, and we don&#x2019;t find its future threatening. Another possible future is that we will all become much more like machines, with significant parts of our sensing and cognition systems augmented by artificial robot parts.  The implicit assumption is that no matter how much hardware we interface with our bodies we will remain human beings, with our personalities and human values intact.  Finally, we have considered a future in which society is composed of robots and humans, with some robots having authority over some humans in a new and better run social order.</Paragraph><Paragraph>Of these three visions, the first is certain, the second is likely, and the third is unlikely in the foreseeable future. This raises a number of questions about our future relationship with robots and intelligent machines.  To what extent can we let our socio-technical world develop its own autonomous intelligence, and to what extent can we ignore the way it evolves and what it evolves into?  Another question concerns the extent to which it is natural to augment our bodies to enhance their performance, and whether this may induce some psychological change, which alters our humanity. Finally we can ask to what extent there will be interaction: As cyborgs will we better adapted to evolve with our increasingly complex socio-technical environment?</Paragraph><StudyNote><Heading>Where next:</Heading><Paragraph>This is the end of Lesson 9. When you are ready go on to <olink targetdoc="Lesson 10">Lesson 10.</olink></Paragraph></StudyNote></Session></Unit><BackMatter><References><Reference><i>Robomum</i> by Emily Smith, Corgie Books (London), 2003. See also <a href="http://www.kidsatrandomhouse.co.uk/">http://www.kidsatrandomhouse.co.uk</a> </Reference><Reference>&#x2018;21st Century Lives: Kevin Warwick&#x2019;, ABC News Internet Ventures, 2000, [no longer available online]. </Reference></References></BackMatter><settings><numbering><Session autonumber="false"/><Section autonumber="false"/><SubSection autonumber="false"/><SubSubSection autonumber="false"/><Activity autonumber="false"/><Exercise autonumber="false"/><Box autonumber="false"/><CaseStudy autonumber="false"/><Quote autonumber="false"/><Extract autonumber="false"/><Dialogue autonumber="false"/><KeyPoints autonumber="false"/><Reading autonumber="false"/><StudyNote autonumber="false"/><Example autonumber="false"/><Verse autonumber="false"/><SAQ autonumber="false"/><ComputerDisplay autonumber="false"/><Summary autonumber="false"/><ProgramListing autonumber="false"/><ITQ autonumber="false"/><Tables autonumber="false"/><Figures autonumber="false"/><MediaContent autonumber="false"/><Chemistry autonumber="false"/></numbering><discussion_alias>Discussion</discussion_alias><session_prefix/></settings></Item>
