<?xml version="1.0"?>
<Item TextType="CompleteItem" SchemaVersion="1.2" id="WEB012111" ACSPageNumber="1" ACSTemplate="generic_unnumbered" ACSCourseItem="T184" LastRendering="VLE Preview" DiscussionAlias="Discussion" SessionAlias="" SecondColour="None" ThirdColour="None" FourthColour="None" Logo="colour"><CourseCode>T184</CourseCode><CourseTitle>Robotics and the meaning of life: a practical guide to things that think</CourseTitle><ItemID>T184</ItemID><ItemTitle>Lesson 8 </ItemTitle><Unit><UnitID>Lesson 8 Introduction</UnitID><UnitTitle>Lesson 8 Introduction</UnitTitle><ByLine>Prepared for the module team by Tony Hirst</ByLine><Session><Title>Lesson 8: Exploring space with robots</Title><Paragraph><i>Prepared for the module team by Tony Hirst, updated by Jon Rosewell</i></Paragraph><Paragraph>Welcome to Lesson 8. Throughout this module, you have seen how building robots can help us to understand ourselves better.</Paragraph><Paragraph>In this lesson you will see how a wide variety of robots can be used to help us explore and work in space. Robot telescopes allow us to explore the heavens from the Earth itself, as well as from space. Space probes and planetary explorers have visited the moon and the planets many times over in the past 30 years, gathering important scientific information and some spectacular holiday snaps! And robots are also playing an important role as construction workers in the assembly of the International Space Station (ISS). A major issue in space robotics that you will consider on this module is the relationship between humans and robots, and how we can best use robots to go where no one has gone before, or is likely to go in the future.</Paragraph><Paragraph>Lesson 8 contains a number of study sessions, listed to the left.</Paragraph><Section><Title>Learning outcomes</Title><Paragraph>At the end of Lesson 8 you should be able to:</Paragraph><BulletedList><ListItem>understand the basic operations of a robot telescope;</ListItem><ListItem>appreciate the particular challenges associated with space robotics;</ListItem><ListItem>be able to categorise different types of space robot;</ListItem><ListItem>understand the various ways of controlling a space robot;</ListItem><ListItem>understand how teleoperation and telepresence allows us to virtually explore a real environment.</ListItem></BulletedList></Section></Session><Session><Title>8.1 Exploring space</Title><Paragraph>Humans have been explorers for time immemorial. At the dawn of a new century, our desire to explore is as strong as ever. But what drives people to seek the unknown, often at great personal risk and expense?</Paragraph><InternalSection><Heading>Motivation for exploration</Heading><Paragraph>There are three main drivers for large-scale, often state-sponsored, exploration:</Paragraph><BulletedList><ListItem>economics</ListItem><ListItem>politics</ListItem><ListItem>science.</ListItem></BulletedList><Paragraph><b>Economics:</b>  The great trading nations of the late Middle Ages opened up trading routes that linked the world, importing and exporting goods from one continent to another. In space, there are several long-term opportunities for commercial and scientific exploitation &#x2013; for example, extraterrestrial mining of minerals or hydrocarbons from the Moon, near-Earth asteroids or comets, or energy generation using solar power. To date, none of these schemes has ever got beyond a feasibility study. This is because of the huge costs involved with launching satellites from Earth, and the large amount of machinery that would need to be launched to build a commercial mining operation, for example. However, there may come a point in our future when scarcity of resources on Earth requires us to look for them elsewhere.</Paragraph><Paragraph>Closer to home, space-based laboratories can be used to manufacture drugs and specialised electronics equipment. One of NASA&#x2019;s main objectives for the International Space Station is to use it for &#x2018;industrial exploitation&#x2019; (<a href="http://www.csp.co.jp/iss.pdf">http://www.csp.co.jp/iss.pdf</a>).</Paragraph><Paragraph>Satellites are also important economically, and play an essential part in many telecommunications and broadcasting systems. In addition, they provide the infrastructure for satellite navigation and global positioning systems (GPS) and remote sensing, e.g. weather prediction, remote imaging of the Earth&#x2019;s surface and acquiring military intelligence about large-scale troop movements on the ground.   There are even much-touted opportunities for space tourism!</Paragraph><Paragraph>Finally, there are many spin-off applications of space science research, from the &#x2018;space blankets&#x2019; used to keep accident victims warm to the Teflon coating on frying pans. These materials and processes, developed as part of the space program, have been widely used and have generated multimillion pound industries.</Paragraph><Paragraph><b>Political pressures:</b> Political (and military) pressures also play a part in driving space exploration &#x2013; nation states used to build empires, thereby guaranteeing access to natural resources unavailable domestically. The space race &#x2013; the race for technological supremacy between the USA and former USSR set against the backdrop of the Cold War &#x2013; was triggered by the launch of the first satellite. It was the space race that subsequently put men into space and on the Moon. The value of remote sensing and GPS to the military has already been mentioned.</Paragraph><Paragraph><b>Scientific discovery:</b> The driving force of scientific discovery has been particularly evident over the past 200 years. One notable example was Darwin&#x2019;s trip on the <i>Beagle</i> around South America in the 1830s, which led to the theory of evolution.  This was recalled by the ill-fated Beagle 2 mission to Mars in 2003, intended to search for evidence of extraterrestrial life &#x2013; one of the major scientific and theological issues of our time. For scientists today, the quest is to understand better the origins of our solar system and &#x2013; the ultimate goal of all &#x2013; to continue the search for life on other planets.</Paragraph><Figure><Image src="\\dog\PrintLive\Courses\t184\web\e1i1\published\images\lesson_8\t184_lesson8_f01.gif" height="" width="100%" alt="" id="" webthumbnail="" x_imagesrc="t184_lesson8_f01.gif" x_imagewidth="308" x_imageheight="175"/><Caption>HMS Beagle in the Strait of Magellan</Caption><SourceReference><font val="Verdana"><language val="">www.geo.cornell.edu</language></font></SourceReference></Figure><Paragraph>Many deep space probes are seen as potentially playing the role of ambassadors of the human race in the event that they be discovered by other civilisations. However, probes that travel across space for thousands of years would eventually cease to function. In these cases, they become not so much ambassadors as inert objects in space.</Paragraph><Paragraph>The plaque depicted below was designed as an intergalactic calling card for the Pioneer 10 mission to the outer solar system. How much better it would be if our robot explorer could actually attempt, and learn, to communicate directly with any aliens it happened to meet!</Paragraph><Figure><Image src="\\dog\PrintLive\Courses\t184\web\e1i1\published\images\lesson_8\t184_lesson8_f02.gif" height="" width="100%" alt="" id="" webthumbnail="" x_imagesrc="t184_lesson8_f02.gif" x_imagewidth="512" x_imageheight="439"/><Caption>The intergalactic calling card for the Pioneer 10 mission </Caption><SourceReference><font val="Verdana"><language val="">Pioneer Project, NASA.</language></font></SourceReference></Figure><Paragraph>The latest lander, Phoenix, carried a DVD with the optimistic label on it:</Paragraph><Quote><Paragraph>This archive, provided to the NASA Phoenix mission by The Planetary Society, contains literature and art (Visions of Mars), greetings from Mars visionaries of our day, and names of 21st century Earthlings who wanted to send their names to Mars. This DVD-ROM is designed to be read on personal computers in 2007. [&#x2026;] For more information refer to the standards document ECMA-268 &#x2026;</Paragraph><SourceReference><a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Phoenix_spacecraft">http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Phoenix_spacecraft</a></SourceReference></Quote><Paragraph>For space exploration, all three driving forces for exploration &#x2013; economic, political and scientific &#x2013; have their role to play. However, getting humans into space, and keeping them there for any considerable time, is both expensive and dangerous. By using robots, we can contemplate long-term &#x2013; and long-distance &#x2013; missions without having to leave the Earth. Or can we?</Paragraph></InternalSection><Section><Title>Space viewed from Earth</Title><Paragraph>Before departing into space with our robot explorers, consider how robots can help us explore space from Earth. People have been looking up at the night sky and recording the motion of the stars and planets, for thousands of years, and it has proved possible to learn a lot about our universe in this way.</Paragraph><Paragraph>However, there is a limit to how much we can see from Earth using just our eyes. Magnifying glasses have been around since the 1300s and lenses first became mounted in reading glasses a hundred or so years later. However, it wasn&#x2019;t until the first decade of the 17th century (1608, in fact) that an instrument &#x2018;for seeing faraway things as though nearby&#x2019; was invented &#x2013; by placing a particular combination of different lenses together in a long tube, called a telescope.</Paragraph><Paragraph>A year later, in 1609, Galileo pointed one of the newly designed telescopes at the Moon, where he discovered detailed craters, and at Jupiter, where he discovered several of the planet&#x2019;s moons.</Paragraph><Paragraph>In the following decades, ever more powerful telescopes were built, and ever more detail observed in the night sky.  Today, very large optical telescopes are used to collect as much light as possible from the distant bodies that can be seen at night.</Paragraph><Figure><Image src="\\dog\PrintLive\Courses\t184\web\e1i1\published\images\lesson_8\t184_lesson8_f03.jpg" height="" width="100%" alt="" id="" webthumbnail="" x_imagesrc="t184_lesson8_f03.jpg" x_imagewidth="256" x_imageheight="255"/><Caption>Large optical telescope</Caption><SourceReference><font val="Verdana"><language val="">&#xA9; Eckhard Slawik/Science Photo Library</language></font></SourceReference></Figure><Paragraph>One of the most important discoveries for astronomy was made in 1666, when Isaac Newton noticed that when white light is passed through a glass prism, a visible coloured spectrum &#x2013; or rainbow &#x2013; results. This visible spectrum forms part of the electromagnetic spectrum that we looked at briefly in Session 2.3.</Paragraph><Paragraph>When different chemical elements are heated, they each emit a different spectrum.   This is of significance to astronomers because the spectra of light from distant hot bodies, such as the Sun or another star, can be collected using large, optical astronomical telescopes. By analysing the light, using a technique known as spectroscopy, it is possible to determine the chemical composition of these bodies.</Paragraph><Paragraph>The electromagnetic spectrum ranges far beyond visible light &#x2013; so spectra can be taken anywhere in the electromagnetic spectrum. To look at signals with very long wavelengths requires a  large radio telescope, such as the one at Jodrell Bank in the UK. At the other end of the scale, the detectors of short wavelength signals are also used to detect gamma rays and X-rays.</Paragraph><Figure><Image src="\\dog\PrintLive\Courses\t184\web\e1i1\published\images\lesson_8\t184_lesson8_f04.jpg" height="" width="100%" alt="" id="" webthumbnail="" x_imagesrc="t184_lesson8_f04.jpg" x_imagewidth="300" x_imageheight="345"/><Caption>Radio telescope at Jodrell Bank in the UK</Caption><SourceReference><font val="Verdana"><language val="">&#xA9; Martin Bond/ Science Photo Library</language></font></SourceReference></Figure><Paragraph>An important part of all professional telescopes today is the image processing that removes noise from the captured images and automates spectrum analysis.</Paragraph><Paragraph>There are a few major difficulties associated with making observations from Earth, of course. Have you ever gone out on a dark evening to look at the Moon or one of the planets, perhaps, only to find that the sky is overcast? Or perhaps the observation you wanted to make could only be made between 4 and 5 o&#x2019;clock on a cold February morning, or from the southern hemisphere?</Paragraph></Section><Section><Title>Robot telescopes</Title><Paragraph>The observation of the night sky is today an automated process, which uses large, computer-controlled telescopes at selected locations all around the world. It has not always been so. You used to have to work at an observatory. However, there are now several robot telescopes that astronomers and members of the general public can use from the comfort of their own Internet-enabled computers.</Paragraph><Paragraph>When I was introduced to the idea of a robot telescope, I was quite taken aback. How could a telescope be a robot? If you think of an observatory, there are several things that immediately come to mind:</Paragraph><BulletedList><ListItem>a domed roof, that may be able to rotate, with a sliding door that allows the telescope inside to peer out at the night sky;</ListItem><ListItem>the telescope itself, with a motorised mount that allows it to point to different parts of the night sky;</ListItem><ListItem>a camera attached to the telescope, so that a permanent record can be made of the observation.</ListItem></BulletedList><Paragraph>In a robot telescope, we can see how the motorised roof and telescope mount provide the actuators of the robot. But what are its sensors?</Paragraph><Paragraph>The instruments attached to the telescope form part of its sensory apparatus, but that is not all. Consider the situation of a robot telescope based in the UK, such as the original Bradford telescope at Oxenhope (pictured below). It is more than likely that the sky will be overcast on any particular day, in which case there is no point in trying to make an observation (at least, not with an optical telescope!). Robot telescopes therefore tend to be equipped with weather stations (temperature sensors, wind speed detectors, light meters and rain gauges, for example) that allow it to sense its environment and work out the likelihood of the sky being clear, and hence suitable for making an observation.</Paragraph><Figure><Image src="\\dog\PrintLive\Courses\t184\web\e1i1\published\images\lesson_8\t184_lesson8_f05.gif" height="" width="100%" alt="" id="" webthumbnail="" x_imagesrc="t184_lesson8_f05.gif" x_imagewidth="391" x_imageheight="294"/><Caption>The first Bradford robotic telescope, which is equipped with a small weather station</Caption><SourceReference><font val="Verdana"><language val="">www.telescope.org, Bradford University</language></font></SourceReference></Figure><Paragraph>Users of robot telescopes usually book into a computer database the observation they wish to make, and the time they would like it to be made. It is part of the robot telescope&#x2019;s intelligent planning system to satisfy as many of these requests as accurately as possible. The robot telescope&#x2019;s control system must also take care of all necessary operational procedures, such as opening the roof and pointing the telescope at the correct bit of sky. However, if the sky is cloudy at the required time then there is no point in the telescope trying to make that observation. Similarly, if a gale is blowing or it is raining, the observatory or the telescope may be damaged if the observatory roof is opened. Therefore, the robot telescope takes steps to protect itself from making observations that might place it at risk, in accordance with Asimov&#x2019;s third law.</Paragraph><Paragraph>Another important feature of some robot telescopes is their ability to track moving objects, thus keeping the objects fully in the field of view at all times. The telescope mount can be programmed to handle this automatically for objects that move as a consequence of the Earth turning on its axis. The situation is different if the telescope is used to track objects that move or appear unexpectedly and whose paths are therefore unknown, such as meteor showers. In these cases, the telescope really does act like a robot, using the information from its sensors to identify objects and keep them in its sights.</Paragraph><SAQ><Heading>SAQ 1</Heading><Question><Paragraph>Using the criteria introduced in Lesson 1, Session 1.2, to what extent do you think a robot telescope really can be described as a mobile, autonomous, intelligent robot?</Paragraph></Question><Answer><Paragraph>Robot telescopes must be capable of sensing their environment using weather sensors, for example, so that they can decide whether or not it is appropriate to even attempt to make an observation. To this extent, a robot telescope is a robot. Although not mobile in the sense that the whole station can move, the robot telescope system can move parts of itself. As robots plan and initiate their own movements based on the observations that have been booked for a particular night, they are autonomous. Given that the robot telescope may have to reorder its observations depending on changing weather circumstances, for example, I think that the robot telescope can act under uncertainty and is therefore intelligent.</Paragraph></Answer></SAQ><Paragraph>If you have time, you might like to visit a robot telescope website and perhaps book an observation. Many robot telescopes are being developed for use by schools, amateur astronomers and other members of the public. On any given night, it is likely that many people will request similar observations. If this happens the telescope&#x2019;s control system often makes a single observation and posts the results to all those who requested it, rather than making several observations of the same thing. Because of the fact that these telescopes are continually being developed, they are not always available when required.</Paragraph><BulletedList><ListItem><Paragraph><a href="http://www.telescope.org/">Bradford Robotic Telescope</a></Paragraph></ListItem><ListItem><Paragraph><a href="http://faulkes-telescope.com/"><font val="Arial">Faulkes Telescope</font></a></Paragraph></ListItem><ListItem><Paragraph><a href="http://www.schoolsobservatory.org.uk/">National Schools Observatory</a></Paragraph></ListItem><ListItem><Paragraph><a href="http://telescope.livjm.ac.uk/"><font val="Arial">The Liverpool Telescope</font></a></Paragraph></ListItem><ListItem><Paragraph><a href="http://pirate.open.ac.uk/"><font val="Arial">PIRATE</font></a><font val="Arial"> (for OU students of S382 </font><font val="Arial"><i>Astrophysics</i></font><font val="Arial">)</font></Paragraph></ListItem><ListItem><Paragraph><a href="http://www.slooh.com/"><font val="Arial">SLOOH</font></a></Paragraph></ListItem></BulletedList></Section></Session><Session><Title>8.2 Robots in space</Title><Paragraph>Space robots come in many forms, and it is natural to think of them as &#x2018;in-space&#x2019; robots or &#x2018;planetary surface&#x2019; explorers.</Paragraph><InternalSection><Heading>In-space robots</Heading><Paragraph>In-space robots are categorised in terms of the tasks they may be expected to perform:</Paragraph><BulletedList><ListItem>observation, such as the Hubble space telescope;</ListItem><ListItem>assembly, such as helping to construct the International Space Station; for example, the space shuttle and space station remote manipulator systems (that is, robot arms);</ListItem><ListItem>inspection of the exterior of a spacecraft as part of a regular maintenance program or in the case of an accident;</ListItem><ListItem>maintenance of structures that have already been assembled and are in need of repair or replacement;</ListItem><ListItem>assisting astronauts on space walks (also called extra-vehicular activities or EVAs), for example by looking after tools and passing them to the astronauts when they are required, or acting as a secure anchor point for the astronauts to attach to;</ListItem><ListItem>in-orbit servicing of other satellites, such as refuelling, replacing or upgrading parts, collecting experiment packages or installing new ones, or retrieving old satellites (for example, the space shuttle).</ListItem></BulletedList><Paragraph> These types of in-space robot might almost be thought of as &#x2018;robot mechanics&#x2019; or robot helpers given they are largely developed to assist humans working on satellites or the International Space Station.</Paragraph><Paragraph>Satellites and space probes are sometimes also considered to be in-space robots. Satellites are generally small spacecraft that are placed in orbit around the earth and which perform some useful function, such as routing telecommunications signals, acting as part of the global positioning system, or imaging the surface of the Earth.</Paragraph><Paragraph>&#x2018;Space probes&#x2019; are the spacecraft that are used for exploring the inner and outer reaches of our solar system. Probes may fly past one or more planetary bodies, collecting information and beaming it back to Earth, before continuing on their journeys out of the solar system.  Alternatively, they may enter into orbit around a particular planet or moon.</Paragraph><Paragraph>Satellites and deep space probes are often not viewed as robots because they tend to operate largely under the control of a human controller, performing a fixed repertoire of actions in response to a limited number of commands. One reason for this approach is safety &#x2013; space probes are expensive to build and launch, and the behaviour of their software systems is usually strictly formally specified, a constraint that does not fit well with autonomous decision-making.</Paragraph><Paragraph>To what extent do you think a space probe is a robot?</Paragraph></InternalSection><InternalSection><Heading>Planetary surface explorers</Heading><Paragraph>Planetary surface explorers are also categorised by activity. For example, some existing and potential activities are:</Paragraph><BulletedList><ListItem>surface exploration (that is, surface mobility), where the robot may be expected to explore the planetary surface in the immediate vicinity of the lander, or move away from its immediate landing site (e.g. the Mars Exploration Rovers (MER) that landed on Mars at the beginning of 2004, or the Pathfinder Sojourner rover that went to Mars in 1997);</ListItem><ListItem>instrument deployment and sample manipulation (e.g. the Beagle 2 lander, which had a robot arm and a burrowing &#x2018;mole&#x2019;, and the 2008 NASA Phoenix lander, which had a robotic arm);</ListItem><ListItem>the robot scientist &#x2013; identifying sites of scientific interest, and planning activities related to these;</ListItem><ListItem>assisting astronauts during an EVA.</ListItem></BulletedList><Figure><Image src="\\dog\PrintLive\Courses\t184\web\e1i1\published\images\lesson_8\t184_lesson8_f06.jpg" height="" width="100%" alt="" id="" webthumbnail="" x_imagesrc="t184_lesson8_f06.jpg" x_imagewidth="400" x_imageheight="274"/><Caption>The&#xA0;robotic arm on the <i>Phoenix</i> Mars lander</Caption><SourceReference>NASA/JPL-Caltech/University of Arizona/Texas A&amp;M University</SourceReference></Figure></InternalSection><Section><Title>Challenges for space robots</Title><Paragraph>Robots that operate in space must be able to endure a very hostile environment. In the first place, they must survive the stresses of the launch and potentially the landing on another world such as a planet, moon or asteroid.  The robot must also be able to cope with extremes of temperature, light (and darkness), and exposure to high levels of radiation which can badly affect unshielded electronic systems. In addition to this, typical operating conditions for a space robot include working in a vacuum and little or no gravity. And all  this, remember, is likely to be at a distance from the Earth so large that human control interventions may take minutes, or even hours, to reach the robot.</Paragraph><Paragraph>On purely practical and economic grounds, space robots are also severely constrained in terms of their weight (mass) and size (volume), as payloads dictate whether or not a robot can even get a ride on a spacecraft. There are also restrictions on the electrical power available to robots, which limits the number of electronic systems that can be supported. The limited power available also limits the potential for transmitting data back from the robot.</Paragraph><InternalSection><Heading>Operating in a vacuum</Heading><Paragraph>Operating in a vacuum raises several issues. For example, on Earth many robots use ultrasound sensors to detect obstacles. However, ultrasound does not work in the vacuum of space or on planets with very thin atmospheres.  You may recall from Lesson 2 that sound travels through air as a series of longitudinal or compression waves, which bounce the air molecules backwards and forwards. If you place your hand in front of a speaker, you can feel the vibration of the air as the speaker moves backwards and forwards several hundred times a second. It is this vibration of air that allows sound &#x2013; and ultrasound &#x2013; to travel. So if there is no atmosphere, there can be no sound.</Paragraph><Paragraph>A bigger problem for robots that operate in a vacuum concerns their heat management. In fact, thermal control is a very important aspect of any space system. It is significant because of the extremes of temperature experienced in space.</Paragraph><Paragraph>On the surface of the Earth, when an object is warmer than the surrounding air, it loses heat and the air heats up by a process of convection. This is not the case in space.</Paragraph><Paragraph>A spacecraft may get hot for a variety of reasons: from firing its engines, doing mechanical work or running electronic systems, and this heat must be dissipated in some way. The vacuum that surrounds a spacecraft, unlike air, acts as an insulator. The heat therefore has to be dissipated via a different process &#x2013; either through infrared radiation, which is very inefficient, or through more active, energy-consuming measures.</Paragraph><Paragraph>At the other extreme is the potentially bitter cold of space. There is no point in using grease, for example, to keep the moving parts of a mechanism working, since grease will freeze in the low temperatures of space. As with vehicles designed for use in Arctic and Antarctic conditions on Earth, some subsystems in space need heating in order for them to work properly.</Paragraph><Paragraph>Thermal control is thus a major problem, but can be tackled in several ways. &#x2018;Passive&#x2019; regulation involves taking measures such as using reflective materials or insulation. &#x2018;Active&#x2019; measures, which themselves expend energy, include the use of radiators (to keep cool) or heaters (to keep warm). A third approach, and one that is becoming increasingly viable with the availability of new materials, is &#x2018;avoidance&#x2019;: using equipment that is unaffected by extreme ranges of temperature.</Paragraph><Paragraph>As well as extremes of temperature there are extremes of pressure. In the vacuum of space, the pressure is effectively zero. However, on some of the planets in our solar system the pressure far exceeds that of the atmospheric pressure on Earth, another factor which must be addressed if we are to send robot explorers to such destinations.</Paragraph></InternalSection><SAQ><Heading>SAQ 2</Heading><Question><Paragraph>What makes space inhospitable for humans and robots?</Paragraph></Question><Answer><Paragraph>Space is a hostile environment that goes from extreme to extreme in terms of temperature, pressure and light levels (for example, the dark side of the moon is very dark!). Low or zero gravity conditions, as well as high G-forces as the rocket launcher accelerates, must also be accommodated. The lack of a breathable atmosphere means an astronaut must have access to an air supply at all times. Radiation is also a problem in space, where there is no Earth atmosphere to filter out some of the harmful rays.</Paragraph></Answer></SAQ></Section><Section><Title>Robots or astronauts?</Title><Paragraph>For humans to be able to work in space outside their spacecraft they need to carry a number of life-support systems around with them. This life support includes protection from radiation, extremes of temperature and the external vacuum, for which a supply of clean air is required. A communication system is also needed. A robot, on the other hand &#x2013; such as the Robonaut humanoid robot being developed by NASA &#x2013; doesn&#x2019;t need any additional &#x2018;life-support systems&#x2019; to operate in space and needs little modification.</Paragraph><Figure><Image src="\\dog\PrintLive\Courses\t184\web\e1i1\published\images\lesson_8\t184_lesson8_f07.jpg" height="" width="100%" alt="" id="" webthumbnail="" x_imagesrc="t184_lesson8_f07.jpg" x_imagewidth="300" x_imageheight="431"/><Caption>NASA&#x2019;s Robonaut</Caption><SourceReference><font val="Verdana"><language val="">&#xA9; Peter Menzel/Science Photo Library.</language></font></SourceReference></Figure><Paragraph>The dexterity of astronauts is limited by the physical constraints &#x2013; size, inflexibility, etc. &#x2013; of their spacesuits. You can get an impression of just how limited this is by trying to tie a pair of shoe laces, do up a button or pick up a pin while wearing a thick pair of gloves. With gloves on, you effectively lose your sense of touch. This sense provides important feedback when performing manipulation tasks requiring a fine degree of control.</Paragraph><Figure><Image src="\\dog\PrintLive\Courses\t184\web\e1i1\published\images\lesson_8\t184_lesson8_f08.jpg" height="" width="100%" alt="" id="" webthumbnail="" x_imagesrc="t184_lesson8_f08.jpg" x_imagewidth="310" x_imageheight="250"/><Caption>Spacesuits significantly restrict physical dexterity</Caption><SourceReference><font val="Verdana"><language val="">SPACE.com, Inc.</language></font></SourceReference></Figure><Paragraph>If you would like to know more about the constraints that are imposed by a spacesuit you might find this web page of interest: <a href="http://www.technologyreview.com/computing/24404/?a=f">NASA's Next Space Suit</a>.</Paragraph><Paragraph>Robots and astronauts can only spend a limited amount of time outside a spacecraft. For robots the limiting factor is battery life, and for astronauts it is the quantity of air and other life-support systems that they can carry.</Paragraph></Section><Section><Title>Robot arms in space</Title><Paragraph>Robot arms have been used in space environments for some time for a variety of tasks. The space shuttle remote manipulator system (SRMS, also known as Canadarm) has been in use since 1981 for manoeuvring payloads in and out of the shuttle cargo bay. There is also a second generation arm, SSRMS (or Canadarm 2) in use on the International Space Station. This was used to help manoeuvre the various parts used in the construction of the space station and to provide a secure footrest for astronauts to stand on while space-walking.</Paragraph><Figure><Image src="\\dog\PrintLive\Courses\t184\web\e1i1\published\images\lesson_8\t184_lesson8_f09.jpg" height="" width="100%" alt="" id="" webthumbnail="" x_imagesrc="t184_lesson8_f09.jpg" x_imagewidth="512" x_imageheight="297"/><Caption>The Canadarm shuttle remote manipulator system (SRMS)</Caption><SourceReference><font val="Verdana"><language val="">MD Robotics</language></font></SourceReference></Figure><Paragraph>The SRMS arm has six degrees of freedom. You will see that it has six joints (shoulder yaw, shoulder pitch, elbow pitch, wrist roll, wrist yaw and wrist pitch) each of which provides one degree of freedom. Pitch, roll and yaw describe how the joint can move. The SSRMS has an additional degree of freedom, which makes it easier to avoid obstacles while moving the end of the arm.</Paragraph><Figure><Image src="\\dog\PrintLive\Courses\t184\web\e1i1\published\images\lesson_8\t184_lesson8_f10.jpg" height="" width="100%" alt="" id="" webthumbnail="" x_imagesrc="t184_lesson8_f10.jpg" x_imagewidth="512" x_imageheight="512"/><Caption>The Canadarm 2 being used on the International Space Station</Caption><SourceReference>NASA</SourceReference></Figure><Paragraph>Astronauts can control the robot arm using two joysticks in several ways. For example, they can control one arm joint at a time, or they can guide a reference point (such as a point on the end actuator) from one place to another. The latter approach requires the control software of the arm to plan which joints should move, when and by how much.</Paragraph><Activity><Heading>Do</Heading><Question><Paragraph><InlineFigure><Image src="\\dog\PrintLive\nonCourse\design_templates\ICONS\Web\png's\42_pixels\off_act_42.png" height="" width="100%" alt="" id="" webthumbnail="" x_imagesrc="off_act_42.png" x_imagewidth="42" x_imageheight="42"/></InlineFigure>If you have Adobe Shockwave Player open this link in a new window: <a href="http://robofesta.open.ac.uk/t184playground/robotArm">T184robot arm</a>.  You will then be able to see how difficult it is to position the end of the robot arm by controlling each joint independently.</Paragraph></Question></Activity><Paragraph>The SRMS and SSRMS can be used to move payloads into or out of the shuttle cargo bay, or to act as flexible, fixed anchor points (or footrests) for astronauts on a space walk. It is even possible for the arm on the shuttle and the arm on the International Space Station (ISS) to work together and pass objects between them. </Paragraph><Activity><Heading>Watch</Heading><Question><Paragraph><InlineFigure><Image src="\\dog\PrintLive\nonCourse\design_templates\ICONS\Web\png's\42_pixels\video_42.png" height="" width="100%" alt="" id="" webthumbnail="" x_imagesrc="video_42.png" x_imagewidth="42" x_imageheight="42"/></InlineFigure> Watch this <a href="http://spaceflight.nasa.gov/gallery/video/shuttle/sts-100/mpg/sts100ani11.mpg">animation</a> that shows the space station robot arm passing an object to the shuttle robot arm.</Paragraph><Quote><Paragraph/><SourceReference>Courtesy NASA</SourceReference></Quote></Question></Activity><Paragraph>On a structure the size of the ISS, which is far larger than the reach of the SSRMS, it is necessary to provide a means for the robot arm to move around the space station. There are several potential solutions to this problem, including &#x2018;free-floating&#x2019; robot arms that can fly around the station to reach their worksite and &#x2018;trolleys&#x2019; that move the robot arm across a gantry system to wherever it needs to go. </Paragraph><Activity><Heading>Watch</Heading><Question><Paragraph><InlineFigure><Image src="\\dog\PrintLive\nonCourse\design_templates\ICONS\Web\png's\42_pixels\video_42.png" height="" width="100%" alt="" id="" webthumbnail="" x_imagesrc="video_42.png" x_imagewidth="42" x_imageheight="42"/></InlineFigure> Watch this <a href="http://spaceflight.nasa.gov/gallery/video/shuttle/sts-113/mpg/sts113ani16.mpg">animation</a> that shows a trolley moving along the length of the space station. </Paragraph><Quote><Paragraph/><SourceReference>Courtesy NASA</SourceReference></Quote></Question></Activity><Paragraph>As well as using the trolley approach, the symmetric design of the SSRMS allows it to &#x2018;walk&#x2019; across the space station, end-over-end. </Paragraph><Activity><Heading>Watch</Heading><Question><Paragraph><InlineFigure><Image src="\\dog\PrintLive\nonCourse\design_templates\ICONS\Web\png's\42_pixels\video_42.png" height="" width="100%" alt="" id="" webthumbnail="" x_imagesrc="video_42.png" x_imagewidth="42" x_imageheight="42"/></InlineFigure> Watch this <a href="http://spaceflight.nasa.gov/gallery/video/shuttle/sts-111/mpg/sts111ani7a.mpg">video clip</a> showing how the SSRMS moves end-over-end from one part of the space station to another. </Paragraph><Quote><Paragraph/><SourceReference>Courtesy NASA</SourceReference></Quote></Question></Activity><Paragraph>The mobility system does not just provide a place to anchor the arm onto. As well as a mechanical coupling, there also needs to be an interface for the power and control subsystems.</Paragraph></Section></Session><Session><Title>8.3 Interplanetary robots</Title><Paragraph>As well as working in space, robots are used to explore space, and in particular to visit the Moon and the other planets and their moons. These missions provide an opportunity to perform geological and meteorological studies. The robots provide a platform for mounting scientific experiments, can retrieve samples for analysis and are sometimes capable of travelling around on the planetary surface in search of new testing sites. As well  as the general problems associated with working in space (the extremes of temperature, pressure and radiation on the one hand, the constraints of mass, volume and power on the other), planetary robots have additional problems.</Paragraph><Paragraph>For example, the robot must be able to land on the planetary surface safely, and in the correct orientation (e.g. not upside down!). Ideally, it should be able to locate itself in the environment. In many missions, the robot will have been designed to rove the planet. In this case, an appropriate mobility system will have been designed. There is also the significant issue of how the robot will be controlled.</Paragraph><Section><Title>Roving other worlds</Title><Paragraph>In Lesson 2 we considered how robots might move in a variety of environments. In this session we&#x2019;ll focus on robots moving in hostile environments on other planets, their moons and asteroids.  For robots exploring the surfaces of other worlds, the mobility subsystem must be capable of operating reliably under normal conditions. The topography and geology of the area around the landing site are two important considerations. Not only must the nature of the terrain be taken into account at a high level (for example, are there steep slopes to be navigated, or wide flat plains?), but also the nature of the surface (fine dust, sand or ice, for example).</Paragraph><Paragraph>The effect of gravity on other worlds is a major issue for the choice of mobility system. Gravity is one factor that affects the amount of traction (frictional grip) that any given mobility system is likely to generate. The mass constraint on the spacecraft and the effect of low gravity make the weight of the rover robot very small. This can make it hard for the rover to gain sufficient grip. This is one reason why some rovers have large, squashy tyres.</Paragraph><Paragraph>Tracks are often proposed for the mobility system because they have a large surface area and can provide plenty of traction. However, many space rovers make use of steerable wheels mounted on rocker bogies, which keeps the wheels in contact with the ground in the most rugged terrain.</Paragraph><Figure><Image src="\\dog\PrintLive\Courses\t184\web\e1i1\published\images\lesson_8\t184_lesson8_f11.jpg" height="" width="100%" alt="" id="" webthumbnail="" x_imagesrc="t184_lesson8_f11.jpg" x_imagewidth="432" x_imageheight="329"/><Caption>A rocker bogie keeps the wheels on the ground in even the roughest terrain</Caption><SourceReference><font val="Verdana"><language val="">JPL, California Institute of Technology/NASA</language></font></SourceReference></Figure><Figure><Image src="\\dog\PrintLive\Courses\t184\web\e1i1\published\images\lesson_8\t184_lesson8_f12.jpg" height="" width="100%" alt="" id="" webthumbnail="" x_imagesrc="t184_lesson8_f12.jpg" x_imagewidth="340" x_imageheight="256"/><Caption>A rocker bogie built from Lego MindStorms</Caption></Figure><Paragraph>One thing that comes as a surprise to many people is the size of the robots that are now being sent to Mars. The economics of space flight means that there is an increasing interest in the use of very small, lightweight rovers for planetary exploration. The Mars Pathfinder Sojourner robot had a mass of 10.6 kg and was about the size of a microwave oven. According to NASA:</Paragraph><Quote><Paragraph>The micro rover is a 6-wheeled vehicle of a rocker bogie design which allows the traverse of obstacles a wheel diameter (13 cm) in size. Each wheel is independently actuated and geared (2000:1) providing superior climbing capability in soft sand. The front and rear wheels are independently steerable, providing the capability for the vehicle to turn in place. The vehicle has a top speed of 0.4 m/min.</Paragraph><SourceReference>California Institute of Technology, 1996</SourceReference></Quote><Figure><Image src="\\dog\PrintLive\Courses\t184\web\e1i1\published\images\lesson_8\t184_lesson8_f13.jpg" height="" width="100%" alt="" id="" webthumbnail="" x_imagesrc="t184_lesson8_f13.jpg" x_imagewidth="400" x_imageheight="261"/><Caption>A Mars Exploration Rover next to a copy of the Mars Sojourner rover</Caption><SourceReference><ItemRights><OwnerRef/><ItemRef/><ItemAcknowledgement><a href="http://mars.jpl.nasa.gov/mer/gallery/spacecraft/mer2002_1106_b231browse.html">http://mars.jpl.nasa.gov/mer/gallery/spacecraft/mer2002_1106_b231browse.html</a></ItemAcknowledgement></ItemRights>Nasa</SourceReference></Figure><Paragraph>Martian robots have not always been so light, however. The NASA Viking landers, which visited Mars in 1976, had a mass of 576 kg. The Soviet Lunokhod lunar rovers (launched in 1970 and 1973) weighed in at 756 kg and 840 kg respectively, and were the size of  a large desk. To launch such a massive lander today would be unthinkable on economic grounds.</Paragraph><InternalSection><Heading>Planetary base stations</Heading><Paragraph>Many designs for planetary rovers provide for a lander base station as well as a rover. For example, this approach was taken by the Pathfinder Sojourner mission to Mars.</Paragraph><Paragraph>A lander can be used to provide many support functions for a rover, including:</Paragraph><BulletedList><ListItem>providing a beacon to help the rover locate its position;</ListItem><ListItem>providing a communications link to an orbiter, or back to Earth;</ListItem><ListItem>providing power, either by recharging the rover&#x2019;s batteries, or via a tether (also referred to as an umbilical);</ListItem><ListItem>providing shelter from the temperature, or weather;</ListItem><ListItem>housing a large part of the scientific equipment, such  as a laboratory for analysing samples retrieved by the rover.</ListItem></BulletedList><Paragraph>The issue of power is critical to the success of a space exploration mission. Solar arrays can be used to provide electricity and to charge batteries during &#x2018;daylight&#x2019; hours. Chemical batteries can also be used, but they have a limited lifetime. Fuel cell technology is being investigated, but this technology is still in its infancy. Nuclear power supplies are perhaps the best engineering solution, but here political considerations regarding nuclear power and the proliferation of nuclear devices in space come into play. Deep-space probes, such as the Cassini-Huygens eleven year mission to Saturn, have used radioisotopes to power thermoelectric generators; at such extreme distances from the Sun, insufficient light is received to make solar cells viable.</Paragraph></InternalSection></Section><Section><Title>Alternatives to wheels and tracks</Title><Paragraph>Many alternative mobility systems have been proposed for robots in space, though none have been used to date. One obvious candidate is a robot with legs, which can either walk or hop. Such robots are adept at traversing landscapes covered with small rocks, for example. Hopper robots were included on two Soviet missions to the Martian moon Phobos in 1988. Hopping is well suited to low gravity situations because the hopper can propel itself quite a large distance with each hop: this was estimated to be 20 m on the Phobos missions. However, both missions failed before the hopper could be properly tested.</Paragraph><Figure><Image src="\\dog\PrintLive\Courses\t184\web\e1i1\published\images\lesson_8\t184_lesson8_f14.jpg" height="" width="100%" alt="" id="" webthumbnail="" x_imagesrc="t184_lesson8_f14.jpg" x_imagewidth="497" x_imageheight="314"/><Caption>The Russian Hopper carried by Phobos 2</Caption><SourceReference><font val="Verdana"><language val="">The Planetary Society</language></font></SourceReference></Figure><Paragraph>Although the Beagle 2 mission to Mars did not include a rover, it did include a &#x2018;mole&#x2019;. This little machine is capable of burrowing into the Martian surface to retrieve an underground soil sample.</Paragraph><Paragraph>Jupiter&#x2019;s moon, Europa, is believed to be covered by a sea, on top of which there is a crust of ice. For missions to environments such as these, cryobots (robots that penetrate ice by creating heat) could be used to melt their way through the ice to reach the oceans and rocks below. One problem with this is that the ice would refreeze above them. The idea of cryobots is not as strange as it may seem. They were used in the 1960s to explore the Arctic ice-cap.</Paragraph><SAQ><Heading>SAQ 3</Heading><Question><Paragraph>What problems might you expect to encounter if a rover were tethered to a lander?</Paragraph></Question><Answer><Paragraph>I can think of several potential problems. Firstly, the range of the rover is limited to the length of the tether. The rover must be capable of dragging the weight of the tether, and there should be some mechanism in place on the lander to reel the tether in and out. The tether may limit the manoeuvrability of the rover, and there is also the possibility that the tether could get caught on something in the environment, or the rover may even get itself tangled up in the tether.</Paragraph></Answer></SAQ></Section><Section><Title>Controlling space robots</Title><Paragraph>Ideally, it should be possible to program a planetary rover to perform a particular mission autonomously. For example, a mission controller on Earth could command the robot to go to a particular location or return to the base station. The robot would then be responsible for getting there. In a fully autonomous system, the robot would be responsible for choosing its destination, as well as making local navigation decisions. There are justifiable concerns about a totally autonomous robot or spacecraft. But as long as space missions are defined by human beings for human purposes there will always be human beings in the control loop.</Paragraph><Paragraph>A lesser evil is to use semi-autonomous control. In this approach, a user sends the robot occasional commands, and also allows it to perform some tasks under its own control when particular conditions are met. In some forms of semi-autonomous control, the robot would act autonomously, but subject to the user overriding its actions.</Paragraph><Paragraph>What the mission scientists really want, though, is to be able to control their robots remotely. This is achieved using the twin approaches known as telepresence and teleoperation (literally: presence/operation at a distance).</Paragraph><InternalSection><Heading>Telepresence and teleoperation</Heading><Paragraph>Telepresence means the acquisition of remote information, as if one were actually present. For example, remote television cameras allow security guards to have telepresence of a number of locations around the site they are guarding. Similarly, remote cameras give store detectives telepresence in shops.</Paragraph><Paragraph>Teleoperation goes one step further, allowing the human to control the motion of the vehicle or platform on which the sensors and other actuators are mounted.</Paragraph><Paragraph>Teleoperated robots are used increasingly to provide telepresence in situations that would be too dangerous or difficult for a human. For example, robots are used by the police and security services to get close to suspicious objects, allowing remote humans to see more closely what they are. Similarly, rescue robots allow rescuers to see inside cramped and dangerous parts of buildings, when searching for the survivors of accidents, etc. In these cases telepresence goes hand in hand with teleoperation.</Paragraph><Paragraph>Telepresence and teleoperation have many applications, particularly in cases where some element of human control is required but human presence may not be possible. For example, unmanned reconnaissance vehicles are now widely used on the modern battlefield, with the human operator in the safety of a control centre. There have been cases of surgeons operating on patients on different continents, using computer-controlled sensors and instruments.</Paragraph><Paragraph>Telepresence has two problems in space applications. The first is the quantity of information contained in video images. These can easily be communicated along cables and high-powered transmitters for the &#x2018;short&#x2019; distances on Earth. For spacecraft with limited electrical and computer power, low data transmission rates are the norm, which makes real-time video communication impractical. Sending a single image may take an appreciable time, many seconds, compared to the 20&#xA0;milliseconds it takes for a TV image on Earth to be transmitted.</Paragraph><Paragraph>The second problem with telepresence, and particularly teleoperation, is the time delays due to the finite speed of light and radio signals.</Paragraph></InternalSection></Section><Section><Title>Remote control and the problem of time</Title><Paragraph>Many of the robots that we have looked at during this module are controlled in real-time by a human who is relatively close by. If we want to control robots over greater distances, we need to address the problem of time. The following table, which is taken from <i>A Taxonomy for Human-Robot Interaction</i>, by Holly A. Yanco and Jill L. Drury, shows how remote robot control can be considered in the context of time and space.</Paragraph><Table><TableHead/><tbody><tr><td/><td><b>Same time</b></td><td><b>Different time</b></td></tr><tr><td>Same space</td><td>e.g. robot wheelchair</td><td>e.g. manufacturing robots</td></tr><tr><td>Different space</td><td>e.g. urban search and rescue</td><td>e.g. Mars robot</td></tr></tbody></Table><Paragraph>So for example, we can control a robot on Earth (same time, same space) using infrared remote control, or telepresence, and there are various techniques we can use. Robots can also be programmed to operate at particular times when we are not present (same place, different time). They can also be operated at a distance, using radio control (same time, different place). The problem with space robots is that they must be operated at a different place and a different time. Although radio control appears to work almost instantaneously over short distances, this is not true over interplanetary distances.</Paragraph><Paragraph>You will recall from Lesson 2 that radio waves, like visible light, are part of the electromagnetic spectrum. Although electromagnetic waves travel very fast (300 million metres per second), they still take a finite time to travel between two points. In fact, it will take just under  3 seconds for a radio signal to do the 769,000 km &#x2018;round trip&#x2019; from the Earth to the Moon and back, and between 8 and 25 minutes for a signal to travel  between the Earth and Mars, depending on the relative position of the planets.  Allowing for the round trip travel time, and ignoring delays at either end, hands-on (real-time) remote control is therefore just not practical.</Paragraph><SAQ><Heading>SAQ 4</Heading><Question><Paragraph>The speed of light is 0.3 million kilometres per second. What is the minimum time it would take a radio signal to travel to the Earth and back from the following planets?</Paragraph><NumberedList class="lower-alpha"><ListItem>Mercury &#x2013; minimum distance from Earth 124 million kilometres</ListItem><ListItem>Venus &#x2013; minimum distance from Earth 64 million kilometres</ListItem><ListItem>Mars &#x2013; minimum distance from Earth 56 million kilometres</ListItem><ListItem>Jupiter &#x2013; minimum distance from Earth 941 million kilometres</ListItem></NumberedList></Question><Answer><NumberedList class="lower-alpha"><ListItem>Mercury &#x2013; 826 seconds</ListItem><ListItem>Venus &#x2013; 426 seconds</ListItem><ListItem>Mars &#x2013; 373 seconds</ListItem><ListItem>Jupiter &#x2013; 6273 seconds</ListItem></NumberedList><Paragraph>From this example, the shortest radio communication from Mars to Earth and back (with control information) is over six minutes, making telecontrol impractical.</Paragraph></Answer></SAQ></Section><Section><Title>Controlling a planetary rover</Title><Paragraph>The following link takes you to <a href="http://www.thetech.org/">The Tech Museum of Innovation</a> website, from where you can access an interactive animation in which you can control a lunar rover using your keyboard. An interesting feature is that you can remotely control the rover subject to a time-delay between when you issue the command and when the rover executes it.</Paragraph><InternalSection><Heading>Red Rover goes to Mars</Heading><Paragraph>If you do not have the MindStorms kit, it may still be possible for you to control a MindStorms robot using the Internet. The Planetary Society Red Rover Goes to Mars project established several authentic Martian landing sites that could be explored with a MindStorms robot using teleoperation and telepresence via a web browser. If you have time, log on to the <a href="http://www.planetary.org/rrgtm/drive.html">Red Rover Goes to Mars website</a> and visit one of their landing sites.</Paragraph></InternalSection><SAQ><Heading>SAQ 5</Heading><Question><Paragraph>What problems might there be with teleoperation and telepresence? For example, what happens if the feedback from the device being remotely controlled is not instantaneous? Under what sorts of circumstance might you imagine such a scenario occurring?</Paragraph></Question><Answer><Paragraph>Teleoperation and telepresence will both be affected by delays between sending a control signal or video image and receiving it if the distance between the transmitter and the receiver is very large. Radio waves which carry this information travel at the speed of light &#x2013; about 0.3 million kilometres per second. For interplanetary distances, this can represent a delay of several minutes.</Paragraph><Paragraph>Another potential problem is the amount of data required to transmit video images. Where transmission rates are low, it may take several minutes to transmit several seconds of video data, even without the delays incurred by the finite speed of light over large distances. This would make real time control, even of a robot a few metres away, hard to achieve.</Paragraph></Answer></SAQ><InternalSection><Heading>The Mars Exploration Rover mission</Heading><Paragraph>The NASA Mars exploration rovers <i>Spirit</i> and <i>Opportunity</i> have been very successful missions. Originally planned for a mission of 90 days, by early 2009 these rovers had been operating for five years. Between them they had explored over 20 km of the surface of Mars, investigating the geology of surface rocks. </Paragraph><Figure><Image src="\\dog\PrintLive\Courses\t184\web\e1i1\published\images\lesson_8\t184_lesson8_f15.jpg" height="" width="100%" alt="" id="" webthumbnail="" x_imagesrc="t184_lesson8_f15.jpg" x_imagewidth="489" x_imageheight="192"/><Caption><i>Spirit</i> on Mars, Martian day 1809</Caption><SourceReference><ItemRights><OwnerRef/><ItemRef/><ItemAcknowledgement><a href="http://marsrovers.nasa.gov/gallery/press/spirit/20090213a.html">http://marsrovers.nasa.gov/gallery/press/spirit/20090213a.html</a></ItemAcknowledgement></ItemRights>Courtesy NASA/JPL-Caltech</SourceReference></Figure><Figure><Image src="\\dog\PrintLive\Courses\t184\web\e1i1\published\images\lesson_8\t184_lesson8_f16.jpg" height="" width="100%" alt="" id="" webthumbnail="" x_imagesrc="t184_lesson8_f16.jpg" x_imagewidth="490" x_imageheight="307"><i/></Image><Caption><i>Opportunity</i> at the edge of Victoria crater, photographed from space by the Mars Reconnaissance Orbiter </Caption><SourceReference><ItemRights><OwnerRef/><ItemRef/><ItemAcknowledgement><a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/File:Oppland01.jpg">http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/File:Oppland01.jpg</a></ItemAcknowledgement></ItemRights>NASA/JPL/University of Arizona</SourceReference></Figure><Paragraph>As you can see from the above images, traversing the surface of Mars presents considerable challenges. Can the rover avoid the boulders and not get bogged in loose sand? Can it avoid driving over the edge of a cliff? Will it tip over on a steep slope? What happens if it drives into shadow &#x2013; would it lose solar power?</Paragraph><Activity><Heading>Read</Heading><Question><Paragraph><InlineFigure><Image src="\\dog\PrintLive\nonCourse\design_templates\ICONS\Web\png's\42_pixels\book_42.png" height="" width="100%" alt="" id="" webthumbnail="" x_imagesrc="book_42.png" x_imagewidth="42" x_imageheight="42"/></InlineFigure>Read the description of the <a href="http://marsrovers.nasa.gov/technology/is_autonomous_mobility.html">mobility system</a> of the Mars Explorations Rovers at the <a href="http://marsrovers.nasa.gov/home/index.html">MER mission website</a>. You may also like to watch the animation provided on this page.</Paragraph><Paragraph>Which of the following best characterises the method of control of these rovers?</Paragraph><BulletedList><ListItem>teleoperation</ListItem><ListItem>semi-autonomous</ListItem><ListItem>autonomous</ListItem></BulletedList></Question><Discussion><Figure><Image src="\\dog\PrintLive\Courses\t184\web\e1i1\published\images\lesson_8\t184_lesson8_f17.jpg" height="" width="100%" alt="" id="" webthumbnail="" x_imagesrc="t184_lesson8_f17.jpg" x_imagewidth="500" x_imageheight="375"/><Caption>An illustration of a Mars rover planning a path </Caption><SourceReference><ItemRights><OwnerRef/><ItemRef/><ItemAcknowledgement><a href="http://marsrovers.nasa.gov/technology/is_autonomous_mobility-02.html">http://marsrovers.nasa.gov/technology/is_autonomous_mobility-02.html</a></ItemAcknowledgement></ItemRights>Courtesy NASA/JPL-Caltech</SourceReference></Figure><Paragraph>The rovers can operate semi-autonomously. The rover is given a target position and then left to plan its own route. It does this by using two cameras to take stereo images from which a 3D map is created. Then areas are evaluated, looking for roughness and slopes, to determine which areas are safe for the rover and which are not. Different paths to the target are evaluated, looking for the shortest and safest. Finally, the rover drives a short distance and then stops and repeats the process. So for short distances, the rover is operating autonomously. But human controllers decide on objectives and closely monitor the rover&#x2019;s progress; in areas of difficult terrain, closely spaced targets are given. Ground controllers can also override normal operation: <i>Spirit&#x2019;s </i>front right wheel seized after two years and since then has had to drive backwards, dragging the dead wheel behind.</Paragraph></Discussion></Activity><Paragraph>If you are interested, you can find out more about the Mars Exploration Rover missions at the <a href="http://marsrovers.nasa.gov/home/index.html">NASA MER website</a>.</Paragraph><Activity><Heading>Watch (optional)</Heading><Question><Paragraph><InlineFigure><Image src="\\dog\PrintLive\nonCourse\design_templates\ICONS\Web\png's\42_pixels\video_42.png" height="" width="100%" alt="" id="" webthumbnail="" x_imagesrc="video_42.png" x_imagewidth="42" x_imageheight="42"/></InlineFigure>In November 2006, Professor Steve Squyres, principal investigator for the MER mission, gave a lecture at the Open University on the geological results so far of the mission. You may be interested to <a href="http://stadium.open.ac.uk/stadia/preview.php?s=1&amp;whichevent=914">watch this lecture</a>. <b>Note</b>: This lecture lasts about 1 hr 30 mins and mainly covers technical geology with only occasional mentions of robotics; it is not essential for your study of this module.</Paragraph></Question></Activity></InternalSection></Section></Session><Session><Title>8.4 Robot and human synergy</Title><Paragraph>Space systems are nearly always designed as a &#x2018;whole system&#x2019;. This means that robots are designed with the relationships they will have with human and other system components very much in mind.</Paragraph><Activity><Heading>Read</Heading><Question><Paragraph><InlineFigure><Image src="\\dog\PrintLive\nonCourse\design_templates\ICONS\Web\png's\42_pixels\book_42.png" height="" width="100%" alt="" id="" webthumbnail="" x_imagesrc="book_42.png" x_imagewidth="42" x_imageheight="42"/></InlineFigure> Read Chapter 7: &#x2018;Escape!&#x2019; in <i>I, Robot</i>, then answer the SAQ   below.</Paragraph><Figure><Image src="\\dog\PrintLive\Courses\t184\web\t184lesson7\i-robot.gif" height="60" width="col_100" alt="" id="" webthumbnail="" x_imagesrc="i-robot.gif" x_imagewidth="107" x_imageheight="170"/><Caption/><SourceReference><font val="Verdana"><language val="">&#xA9; Harper Collins Publishers</language></font></SourceReference></Figure></Question></Activity><SAQ><Heading>SAQ 6</Heading><Question><NumberedList class="lower-alpha"><ListItem>Do you think The Brain acts in accordance with the first law?</ListItem><ListItem>Do you think AI controlled spacecraft will be used in manned space exploration?</ListItem></NumberedList></Question><Answer><NumberedList class="lower-alpha"><ListItem>As far as the first law goes, I think that The Brain is on the verge of breaking it. I would say that the worry caused to the two field men when they thought they were dying, and the potential of long term psychological damage to them both would constitute causing them harm, even if it was as the result of a practical joke by The Brain. (How many times do jokes go wrong, for example, and have dire consequences if taken wrongly?)</ListItem><ListItem>Many science fiction films and stories that do not make use of warp drives rely on astronauts hibernating during the long journey time required for an intergalactic expedition. If ever this were to become a reality, then I would expect the spacecraft to operate autonomously, and be able to take executive action in the event of having to avoid an encroaching meteor shower, for example. More realistically, providing space probes with the intelligence to look after themselves during their voyages is being worked on today.</ListItem></NumberedList></Answer></SAQ><Activity><Heading>Watch</Heading><Question><Paragraph><InlineFigure><Image src="\\dog\PrintLive\nonCourse\design_templates\ICONS\Web\png's\42_pixels\video_42.png" height="" width="100%" alt="" id="" webthumbnail="" x_imagesrc="video_42.png" x_imagewidth="42" x_imageheight="42"/></InlineFigure>Watch this <a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=mpdfg_nLTdM">YouTube video clip</a> that illustrates how robots might be used to   support large-scale manned missions to Mars.</Paragraph></Question></Activity><Paragraph>The video shows how teams of robots might be deployed on the planet Mars. Deploying robots in advance of a human mission means that colonies can be prepared in advance of the human visitors arriving. Just like humans have different capabilities, there will be a need for a range of different types and sizes of robots to perform different tasks.</Paragraph><Activity><Heading>Read</Heading><Question><Paragraph><InlineFigure><Image src="\\dog\PrintLive\nonCourse\design_templates\ICONS\Web\png's\42_pixels\book_42.png" height="" width="100%" alt="" id="" webthumbnail="" x_imagesrc="book_42.png" x_imagewidth="42" x_imageheight="42"/></InlineFigure>Now read the paper <a href="http://openurl.open.ac.uk.libezproxy.open.ac.uk/sfxlcl3?id=doi:10.1016/j.actaastro.2004.05.072">Robots and humans: synergy in planetary exploration</a> by Geoffrey A. Landis and as you do so, reflect on the following questions. It might help you to jot   down a few key points. (Please note that it may take some time to download this paper.)</Paragraph></Question></Activity><Paragraph>What assumptions does the author make about the main ways in which robots are used to support human space explorers? How might robots be used to support human extra-vehicular activity? What requirements and constraints are there on teleoperated robots, and how does Landis address these?</Paragraph><SAQ><Heading>SAQ 7</Heading><Question><Paragraph>Summarise Landis&#x2019; paper. What is his main conclusion?</Paragraph></Question><Answer><Paragraph>Landis&#x2019; paper asks how humans and robots will cooperate in future planetary exploration. It looks at Martian exploration, and considers astronauts being given assistance by a solar-powered &#x2018;scout airplane&#x2019; giving environmental information, and robotic &#x2018;mules&#x2019; carrying tools and burdens. The paper questions if robots can replace humans for &#x2018;EVA&#x2019; (extra-vehicular activity), and suggests they can.</Paragraph><Paragraph>According to Landis, space robots have been used mainly as precursors for future possible human exploration missions. Mars has been the focus of many missions (completed, current and planned) as it is likely to be the next target of a major manned mission. Landis suggests that robots can act as assistants to human explorers, for example by providing aerial reconnaissance or acting as a &#x2018;mule&#x2019;. Teleoperated rovers could also be used to replace human explorers on the planetary surface, and allow exploration of terrain too dangerous for space-suited human explorers. Landis&#x2019; &#x2018;radical concept&#x2019; is to support human exploration of Mars without landing people on the Martian surface. Instead, human explorers would be &#x2018;parked&#x2019; in Mars&#x2019; orbit and use teleoperated robots to explore the Martian surface. Indeed, from Landis&#x2019; use of the phrase &#x2018;Tele-exploration from Mars orbit also allows human (virtual) presence at a wide variety of locations&#x2019; on page 6, I think he is implying that human operators actually make use of telepresence technologies. By not landing humans on Mars in this way you minimise the risks of contaminating either planet (Mars or Earth) with alien life forms.</Paragraph></Answer></SAQ></Session><Session><Title>8.5 RobotLab8</Title><Paragraph>In this session you will be doing lab activities using RobotLab8.</Paragraph><Activity><Heading>RobotLab</Heading><Question><Paragraph><InlineFigure><Image src="\\dog\PrintLive\nonCourse\design_templates\ICONS\Web\png's\42_pixels\robotlab_42.png" height="" width="100%" alt="" id="" webthumbnail="" x_imagesrc="robotlab_42.png" x_imagewidth="42" x_imageheight="35"/></InlineFigure>Download the lab guide for <olink targetdoc="RobotLab8">RobotLab8</olink>. Work through the guide carefully and do the activities.</Paragraph></Question></Activity></Session><Session><Title>8.6 Summary</Title><Paragraph>In this lesson, you have seen how robots and robotic technologies have been used in robot telescopes to help explore space from Earth.</Paragraph><Paragraph>Designing robots for use in space requires the many extreme conditions of space to be addressed, particularly temperatures, pressures and gravitational conditions. There are also severe constraints on the mass and volume of a space robot, as dictated by the economies of the launch. Power consumption is also a major issue, perhaps more so than on Earth where there is often the opportunity to make use of a battery recharger connected to a mains electricity supply.</Paragraph><Paragraph>In spite of these constraints, robots, such as the robot arm Canadarm2, are widely used in space, particularly in the construction of the International Space Station. The use of robots for rescuing and refuelling stranded satellites in Earth orbit is one of many challenges of the next 10-20 years.</Paragraph><Paragraph>Robots have also been used for interplanetary exploration. The problems of controlling these robots, particularly mobile rovers, is compounded by the distances involved &#x2013; distances so great that it can take several minutes for a radio signal to travel to and from even our closest neighbours in the solar system. A combination of semi-autonomous robots with teleoperation backed up by telepresence helps Earth-based scientists get the most from the exploratory capabilities of these robots.</Paragraph><Paragraph>In the future it may be possible for astronauts to control planetary rovers from manned control stations in space using telepresence (so-called hybrid manned-robot missions).</Paragraph><StudyNote><Heading>Where next:</Heading><Paragraph>This is the end of Lesson 8. When you are ready go on to <olink targetdoc="Lesson 9">Lesson 9</olink>.</Paragraph></StudyNote></Session></Unit><BackMatter><References><Reference>Yanco, H.A. and Drury, J.L. (2002)<i> &#x2018;</i>A taxonomy for human-robot interaction,<i> AAAI Symposium on Human-Robot Interaction, AAAI Technical Report FS-02-03, November 2002,pp. 111-119.</i> </Reference><Reference>Anon (1996) &#x2018;A description of the rover Sojourner&#x2019;, <a href="http://marsrovers.jpl.nasa.gov/home/index.html">Jet Propulsion Laboratory</a>, California Institute of Technology and the National Aeronautics and Space Administration, 1996 [Online at: http://mars.jpl.nasa.gov/MPF/rover/descrip.html]</Reference><Reference>Landis, G.A. (2004) Robots and humans: synergy in planetary exploration, Acta Astronautica, Vol. 55, Issue 12, pp. 985-990.</Reference></References></BackMatter><settings><numbering><Session autonumber="false"/><Section autonumber="false"/><SubSection autonumber="false"/><SubSubSection autonumber="false"/><Activity autonumber="false"/><Exercise autonumber="false"/><Box autonumber="false"/><CaseStudy autonumber="false"/><Quote autonumber="false"/><Extract autonumber="false"/><Dialogue autonumber="false"/><KeyPoints autonumber="false"/><Reading autonumber="false"/><StudyNote autonumber="false"/><Example autonumber="false"/><Verse autonumber="false"/><SAQ autonumber="false"/><ComputerDisplay autonumber="false"/><Summary autonumber="false"/><ProgramListing autonumber="false"/><ITQ autonumber="false"/><Tables autonumber="false"/><Figures autonumber="false"/><MediaContent autonumber="false"/><Chemistry autonumber="false"/></numbering><discussion_alias>Discussion</discussion_alias><session_prefix/></settings></Item>
