<?xml version="1.0"?>
<Item TextType="CompleteItem" SchemaVersion="1.2" id="WEB012104" ACSPageNumber="1" ACSTemplate="Generic_A4_Unnumbered" ACSCourseItem="T184-11E" LastRendering="VLE Preview" DiscussionAlias="Comment" SessionAlias="" SecondColour="None" ThirdColour="None" FourthColour="None" Logo="colour"><CourseCode>T184-11E</CourseCode><CourseTitle>Robotics and the meaning of life: a practical guide to things that think</CourseTitle><ItemID>T184</ItemID><ItemTitle>Lesson 1</ItemTitle><FrontMatter><Imprint><Standard><GeneralInfo><Paragraph/></GeneralInfo><Address><AddressLine/></Address><FirstPublished><Paragraph/></FirstPublished><Copyright><Paragraph/></Copyright><Rights><Paragraph/></Rights><Edited><Paragraph/></Edited><Printed><Paragraph/></Printed><ISBN><font val="Courier New">WEB026201</font></ISBN><Edition>2.1</Edition></Standard></Imprint></FrontMatter><Unit><UnitID>Lesson 1 Introduction</UnitID><UnitTitle>Lesson 1 Introduction</UnitTitle><ByLine>Prepared by the module team</ByLine><Session><Title>Introduction</Title><Paragraph><i>Prepared for the module team by Jeffrey Johnson and Tony Hirst, updated by Jon Rosewell</i></Paragraph><Paragraph>Hello. We&#x2019;d like to welcome you to the first lesson of T184. </Paragraph><Paragraph>Lesson 1, in common with the other lessons, is split into a number of study sessions that are listed to the left of this page.</Paragraph> <Paragraph>We start Lesson 1 with an overview of the whole module, explaining how it is organised and how to approach your studies.</Paragraph> <Paragraph>We then turn to a fundamental question: just what is a robot? We&#x2019;ll look both at some current examples of robotics and some historical examples of artificial beings.</Paragraph> <Paragraph>One of the features that might distinguish a robot from other machines is that of intelligence, so we will need to explore what we mean by intelligence and artificial intelligence.</Paragraph> <Paragraph>The final study session will introduce you to the practical aspects of the module.</Paragraph></Session><Session><Title>1.1 About the module</Title><Figure><Image src="\\dog\PrintLive\Courses\t184\web\e1i1\published\images\lesson_1\t184_lesson1_f01.jpg" height="" width="100%" alt="" id="" webthumbnail="" x_imagesrc="t184_lesson1_f01.jpg" x_imagewidth="400" x_imageheight="220"/></Figure><Paragraph>Robotics and the meaning of life! What can tin-men and bug-eyed monsters tell us about the meaning of life? This module is designed to show that robotics can teach us a great deal about what it means to be human. Robots will increasingly become part of our lives. They will be found not just in factories, but also in shops and offices, in hospitals and especially in our homes. Here are just a few of the many kinds of robots that already exist or are being developed:</Paragraph><BulletedList><ListItem>robot vacuum cleaners, lawnmowers and window cleaners;</ListItem><ListItem>robot surgeons, therapists, helpers for disabled people;</ListItem><ListItem>robots that fly aeroplanes and drive cars;</ListItem><ListItem>robots that unblock pipes and weld undersea structures;</ListItem><ListItem>robot bartenders, waiters and butlers;</ListItem><ListItem>robot football players, dancers and performing artists;</ListItem><ListItem>robots that rescue people from collapsed buildings;</ListItem><ListItem>robot pets, insects and animals.</ListItem></BulletedList><Paragraph>On this module we&#x2019;ll explain how robots work, and give you a chance to program and control real or simulated robots. But we&#x2019;ll go far beyond this &#x2013; by examining the relationship between humans and robots and the enormous impact they are having on our lives and on society. In doing this we will often have to reflect on what it means to be a human being, interacting with other human beings.</Paragraph><Section><Title>Aims</Title><Paragraph>T184 is intended to be studied by a variety of students with a variety of backgrounds. These will range from people who know nothing about robots to those who know quite a lot, and from people who are new to studying to those with a lot more experience. Whichever group you fall in, we hope that you will find T184 interesting and rewarding.</Paragraph><Paragraph>The aims of T184 are:</Paragraph><BulletedList><ListItem><b>to enable you to understand robots:</b> learning about the various technologies involved in robotics and how to program or train robots;</ListItem><ListItem><b>to enable you to understand how robots are affecting our lives:</b> how robots will help us and our families at home, their role in health and social care, and their contribution to industry, transportation, science and philosophy;</ListItem><ListItem><b>to alert you to the many ethical issues concerning robots:</b> to help you reflect on and find your own answers to questions such as: should we use a robot babysitter? is it murder to switch off a robot? are robot soldiers acceptable? should there be a charter of robot rights? will robots take over the world? should we be allowed to marry a robot?</ListItem><ListItem><b>to share with you a sense of excitement and fun:</b> robots can make you laugh, making robots do things can be very satisfying, robots can be fascinating and can motivate us to learn.</ListItem></BulletedList><Paragraph>The last of these aims is particularly important to the module team. The message we want to get across is that robots, and the study of robotics, can be fun!</Paragraph><Paragraph>For example, each year, at the international RoboCupJunior international finals, groups of children from all over the world show their robot creations off in robot dance, rescue and football competitions. One of the most successful teams over the past few years has been a team from Amberfield School in the UK. The following video shows their 2006 prizewinning robot dance performance &#x2018;The Flight of the Phantom Phoenixes&#x2019;.</Paragraph><Activity><Heading>Watch</Heading><Question><Paragraph><InlineFigure><Image src="\\dog\PrintLive\nonCourse\design_templates\ICONS\Web\png's\42_pixels\video_42.png" height="" width="100%" alt="" id="" webthumbnail="" x_imagesrc="video_42.png" x_imagewidth="42" x_imageheight="42"/></InlineFigure>  <a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ks3Y6SwdraM">&#x2018;The Flight of the Phantom Phoenixes&#x2019;</a> &#x2013; this YouTube video shows the Amberfield School team&#x2019;s prizewinning robot dance performance.</Paragraph><Paragraph>A large, bird-like robot, reminiscent of a feathered star in a Las Vegas show is seen in the centre of the stage, with a smaller feathered robot pirouetting on either side. Several small robots act as a chorus line at the front of the stage. In the background, team members dance to a musical sound track along with the robot.</Paragraph></Question></Activity><Paragraph>The robot performers were built and programmed by the team members. Did you notice how the robots&#x2019; movements were coordinated with the music? As you will learn, this coordination requires some sophisticated computer programming. The robots also made use of some clever mechanical engineering. For example, how do you think the wings moved up and down?</Paragraph><Paragraph>The fun element also plays a part in the other competitions and challenges that we describe in Section 1.3.</Paragraph><Paragraph>In addition to making dancing robots, people are doing many other surprising things with robots. For example, in Japan scientists are investigating the possibility of robots being used as companions during therapy. Paro is a lifesize, white robot seal pup that responds as it is stroked and petted. It was designed by Dr Taknori Shibata of Japan's National Institute of Advanced Industrial Science and Technology.</Paragraph><Activity><Heading>Watch</Heading><Question><Paragraph><InlineFigure><Image src="\\dog\PrintLive\nonCourse\design_templates\ICONS\Web\png's\42_pixels\video_42.png" height="" width="100%" alt="" id="" webthumbnail="" x_imagesrc="video_42.png" x_imagewidth="42" x_imageheight="42"/></InlineFigure>  <a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Vx8mv87e6wE">Paro</a> &#x2013; this YouTube video shows Paro, a robot in the form of a white, furry baby seal. When Paro is called, it opens its large, dark eyes. When Paro is stroked and petted, it responds by moving its body and flippers. If stroked too vigorously, it calls plaintively. Paro can be recharged through a baby&#x2019;s dummy that plugs into its mouth; it goes to sleep while charging and is woken by calling and being tickled under the chin.</Paragraph></Question></Activity><Paragraph>As you may be able to tell from the video, a new relationship is developing between robots and humans. Investigating this relationship is one of the main purposes of T184. During the module you will see many other applications of robots, learn the principles behind them and learn how to create simple robotic systems.</Paragraph></Section><Section><Title>Structure of the module</Title><Paragraph>The module you have embarked upon lasts 10 weeks. You will be working at the rate of one lesson a week, with each lesson &#x2013; hence a week&#x2019;s work &#x2013; representing about 10 hours of study time. This will be split approximately equally between reading and practical activities. There are 10 lessons in total including assessment at the middle and end of the module &#x2013; more on these later.</Paragraph><Paragraph>The study planner on your module home page will suggest a study plan for the module. We recommend that you follow the suggested pacing if you can because that will allow you to participate in the forums with other students at the appropriate time. However, if you can&#x2019;t follow the study plan, you can get ahead a little or drop behind a little on the lessons, but you <b>must</b> submit the assignments on time.</Paragraph><Paragraph>The first part of each lesson will involve reading web pages like this, watching parts of the DVD or reading chapters of a book, and answering some self-assessment questions (SAQs) to test your understanding. The duration will vary but typically will take you about five hours a week. In the second part of each lesson you will be doing some related lab work. This will involve working through some practical activities with simulated or real robots. Each lesson concludes with a summary of what you have learnt during that week.</Paragraph><Paragraph>The module uses several resources besides these web pages. The first is a DVD containing an OU/BBC programme <i>James May&#x2019;s Big Ideas: Man&#x2013;Machine</i>, which you are asked to watch in Lessons 1 to 4. Later, in Lessons 6 to 9, you will read extracts from Isaac Asimov's <i>I, Robot</i>. You won&#x2019;t be expected to remember all the details; these web pages will summarise and develop what you have seen and read.</Paragraph><Paragraph>You will also explore the module wiki, which is kept up to date with examples of interesting robots, and there is an online forum where you can exchange information with fellow students.</Paragraph><Paragraph>So in any one week you might expect to do most of the following:</Paragraph><BulletedList><ListItem>read that week&#x2019;s material on the module website;</ListItem><ListItem>watch some video clips;</ListItem><ListItem>explore some of the links to other sites on the web;</ListItem><ListItem>do the activities;</ListItem><ListItem>answer the SAQs;</ListItem><ListItem>work through the lab activities with simulated or real robots;</ListItem><ListItem>perform experiments and record results;</ListItem><ListItem>look ahead to questions in the assignments.</ListItem></BulletedList><InternalSection><Heading>James May&#x2019;s Big Ideas: Man&#x2013;Machine</Heading><Figure><Image src="\\dog\PrintLive\Courses\t184\web\e1i1\published\images\lesson_1\t184_lesson1_f02.jpg" height="" width="100%" alt="" id="" webthumbnail="" x_imagesrc="t184_lesson1_f02.jpg" x_imagewidth="219" x_imageheight="134"/><Caption>James May and a robot</Caption><SourceReference><a href="http://www.open2.net/jamesmay/man_machine.html">Open2.net</a></SourceReference></Figure><Paragraph>As part of the module materials, you should have received a DVD of a programme from the series <i>James May&#x2019;s Big Ideas</i>. This contains film of some interesting current developments in robotics.</Paragraph><Paragraph>You will initially be asked to watch the programme in its entirety to get a flavour of the field of robotics. While you watch it, you will be asked to think about what defines a &#x2018;robot&#x2019;. This is, perhaps surprisingly, not an altogether easy question to answer, so we will spend some time in this lesson coming up with a definition.</Paragraph><Paragraph>Later on, you will watch specific sequences from this programme again to see particular examples of robots in action.</Paragraph></InternalSection><InternalSection><Heading>I, Robot</Heading><Figure><Image src="\\dog\PrintLive\Courses\t184\web\e1i1\published\images\lesson_1\t184_lesson1_f03.jpg" height="" width="100%" alt="" id="" webthumbnail="" x_imagesrc="t184_lesson1_f03.jpg" x_imagewidth="200" x_imageheight="320"/><SourceReference>&#xA9; Harper Collins Publishers</SourceReference></Figure><Paragraph>In Lessons 6 to 9 you will read some of the short fictional stories in Asimov&#x2019;s book<i> I, Robot</i>. Asimov wrote these stories in the 1940s and 50s, but the issues they raise about the way human beings and robots coexist are increasingly relevant today. Thus, having seen examples of real robot technology in the first four lessons, you will be well placed to understand the significance of Asimov&#x2019;s ideas later in the module.</Paragraph></InternalSection><InternalSection><Heading>The T184 wiki</Heading><Paragraph>Robotics is a fast-moving field. To keep the module up-to-date, we will be using a wiki to build a collection of examples of current robotics. At several points in the module, you will be asked to explore this wiki. And if at any time you come across interesting examples of robots in the news or in your reading, we encourage you to add information about them to the wiki.</Paragraph><Paragraph>You may not know much about wikis, but you will probably have come across <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page">Wikipedia</a>, a huge on-line encyclopaedia built by volunteer contributors. Our wiki will only be a fraction of the size but, like Wikipedia, it is a shared endeavour &#x2013; your contributions are welcome and will be most valuable to your fellow students. To contribute to the wiki is very easy &#x2013; simply click on &#x2018;Edit&#x2019; and start typing!</Paragraph><Paragraph>By the way, if you are curious to know why a wiki is called a wiki, why not use <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page">Wikipedia</a> to find out?</Paragraph></InternalSection><InternalSection><Heading>The T184 forum</Heading><Paragraph>The T184 forum is a meeting-place where you can ask questions, give answers and exchange information with other students. It is also a place in which you can ask for help on technical and study-related issues from experienced moderators and fellow students. We have divided the forum into several areas for different topics; each contains a welcoming message that will tell you what that forum is intended to be used for.</Paragraph><Paragraph>We do encourage you to use the forums. If you have questions or need help, you will probably get an answer from fellow students very quickly. The forums can save you a lot of time and make studying more enjoyable. They are also a place for interesting discussions around issues raised by the module. There is a Caf&#xE9; forum where you can chat with other students &#x2013; why not say hello there soon? </Paragraph></InternalSection><InternalSection><Heading>RobotLab</Heading><Figure><Image src="\\dog\PrintLive\Courses\t184\web\e1i1\published\images\lesson_1\t184_lesson1_f04.small.gif" height="" width="100%" alt="" id="" webthumbnail="" x_imagesrc="t184_lesson1_f04.small.gif" x_imagewidth="512" x_imageheight="359"/></Figure><Paragraph>The laboratory work uses RobotLab, the OU Robotics Laboratory that runs on your computer. We will provide you with full instructions on how to get started with RobotLab in Session 5 of Lesson 1. There will be further lab work sessions in the subsequent lessons, and these will be clearly signposted.</Paragraph><Paragraph>Hands-on experimentation is an important part of this module. We hope you will find the activities interesting and fun. Lab work can be very time-consuming, so we have tried not to overload this part of the module. If you want to go further, we include some additional optional activities. These are intended to enrich the module, but are not compulsory.</Paragraph><Paragraph>Although the amount of lab work may vary from week to week, you should find that it takes you on average about five hours to complete.</Paragraph></InternalSection><InternalSection><Heading>Lessons 5 and 10</Heading></InternalSection><InternalSection><Paragraph>Lessons 5 and 10 are different from the other lessons. Neither of these lessons has any compulsory coursework or laboratory work &#x2013; they are intended to give you time to do the assessed components of the module. </Paragraph><Paragraph>Lesson 5 contains an online quiz (in OU jargon, this is the computer-marked assignment iCMA41) which covers the first half of the module. Lesson 10 contains the final assessment, covering the whole module. This has two components: one is a quiz (the computer-marked exam iCME81), and the other written questions (the end-of-module assessment or EMA). <font val="Arial">You </font><font val="Arial"><b>must submit both</b></font><font val="Arial"> iCME81 and the EMA to complete the course. </font>Your final mark for the module will combine your marks for all three components, weighted as follows: iCMA41 10%, iCME81 30%, EMA 60%. If you choose not to do the optional activities you can still score full marks in the assessments.</Paragraph></InternalSection></Section><Section><Title>Learning outcomes</Title><Paragraph>At the end of Lesson 1 you should:</Paragraph><BulletedList><ListItem>know what the module is about;</ListItem><ListItem>understand how to use the teaching materials provided;</ListItem><ListItem>be able to define what an intelligent, autonomous, mobile robot is;</ListItem><ListItem>know some robot history;</ListItem><ListItem>know something about the uses of robots, current and future;</ListItem><ListItem>understand some of the ethical issues in human-robot interaction;</ListItem><ListItem>have practised some basic study skills, including making summary notes, conducting experiments and recording the results.</ListItem></BulletedList><InternalSection><Heading>Module learning outcomes</Heading><Paragraph>The learning outcomes for the module as a whole are grouped under four headings as follows.</Paragraph><UnNumberedList><ListItem><b>Knowledge and understanding</b><Paragraph>By the end of the module you should be able to:</Paragraph><BulletedSubsidiaryList><SubListItem>demonstrate your knowledge of the theory and principles underlying robot design, assembly and programming;</SubListItem><SubListItem>organise information for effective communication;</SubListItem><SubListItem>apply basic programming metaphors to robots;</SubListItem><SubListItem>apply simple control strategies for robot control;</SubListItem><SubListItem>demonstrate your appreciation of the ways in which robots are impacting on human beings and human society.</SubListItem></BulletedSubsidiaryList></ListItem><ListItem><b>Cognitive skills</b><Paragraph>By the end of the module you should be able to:</Paragraph><BulletedSubsidiaryList><SubListItem>identify the key features for a robot to undertake a task in a given environment;</SubListItem><SubListItem>create a sequence of instructions to control a robot;</SubListItem><SubListItem>be able to explain the interactions between humans and robots;</SubListItem><SubListItem>reflect on your learning and evaluate your achievements.</SubListItem></BulletedSubsidiaryList></ListItem><ListItem><b>Key skills</b><Paragraph>By the end of the module you should be able to:</Paragraph><BulletedSubsidiaryList><SubListItem>develop your abilities to communicate information to an intended audience;</SubListItem><SubListItem> make use of different sources of information;</SubListItem><SubListItem>search for relevant information on the Web.</SubListItem></BulletedSubsidiaryList></ListItem><ListItem><b>Practical skills</b><Paragraph>You will experiment with various ways of interacting with simulated or real robots, and learn the skills to:</Paragraph><BulletedSubsidiaryList><SubListItem>write simple programs to control a simulated or real robot;</SubListItem><SubListItem>train a simulated or real robot to perform a given task;</SubListItem><SubListItem>find relevant information on the Web;</SubListItem><SubListItem>organise and document information from different sources.</SubListItem></BulletedSubsidiaryList></ListItem></UnNumberedList></InternalSection></Section></Session><Session><Title>1.2 What is a robot?</Title><Paragraph>The term &#x2018;robot&#x2019; is attributed to the Czech Karel &#x10C;apek, who wrote a play in 1920 called <i>RUR</i>. The initials stand for Rossum&#x2019;s Universal Robots, and the word robot comes from the word <i>robota</i>, which means forced labour. So, right from the start, robots were seen as artificial beings acting as slaves to humans.</Paragraph><Paragraph>&#x10C;apek&#x2019;s robots were actually made from biological parts, although now we tend to think of robots as being made from mechanical parts. With advances in biotechnologies (e.g. growing spare parts), we may yet turn full circle and return to the idea of a biological race of manufactured <i>robota</i>.</Paragraph><Figure><Image src="\\dog\PrintLive\Courses\t184\web\e1i1\published\images\lesson_1\t184_lesson1_f05.jpg" height="" width="100%" alt="" id="" webthumbnail="" x_imagesrc="t184_lesson1_f05.jpg" x_imagewidth="151" x_imageheight="289"/><Caption>The RUR robot that appeared in an adaptation of Karel &#x10C;apek&#x2019;s Rossum&#x2019;s Universal Robots, circa 1930s</Caption><SourceReference>www.thetech.org</SourceReference></Figure><Paragraph>The term &#x2018;robot&#x2019; soon gained widespread use through the work of science fiction authors. One of these, Isaac Asimov, wrote a number of stories in the early 1940s, and these were collected in the book <i>I, Robot</i> published in 1950. All of Asimov&#x2019;s robot stories appear in the book <i>The Complete Robot</i>.</Paragraph><Paragraph>Science fiction has been surprisingly important in developing the field of robotics. According to the Oxford English Dictionary, even the word &#x2018;robotics&#x2019; first appeared in one of Isaac Asimov&#x2019;s short stories rather than in a scholarly journal.</Paragraph><Section><Title>Asimov&#x2019;s three laws of robotics</Title><Paragraph>Asimov&#x2019;s three laws may have appeared in his fiction, but they state with brilliant simplicity some of the most basic characteristics of robots:</Paragraph><NumberedList><ListItem>A robot may not injure a human being, or through inaction allow a human being to come to harm.</ListItem><ListItem>A robot must obey the orders given to it by human beings except where such orders would conflict with the first law.</ListItem><ListItem>A robot must protect its own existence as long as such protection does not conflict with the first or second law.</ListItem></NumberedList><Paragraph>Of course, machines should not wilfully hurt human beings, and should obey orders &#x2013; unless someone orders a robot to hurt someone else. Clearly, it is also undesirable to have machines that damage themselves and then need to be repaired.</Paragraph><Paragraph>The laws also say something about how robots might be expected to work. For example, it is a fundamental requirement that robots do not harm people, as required by the first law. In order for this law to work, the robot must be aware of what is going on in its surroundings. For example, the robot should be able to perceive threats to humans and act to minimise any threat. The second law suggests that a robot can be commanded to do things. Finally, the third law implies that a robot can modify its behaviour and the way it operates in order to perform a task safely.</Paragraph><Paragraph>The brains of Asimov&#x2019;s robots had the three laws of robotics deeply embedded in them. The idea is that the way the robot brain is constructed (that is, its <i>architecture</i>) constrains robots, making it impossible for them to break the three laws. In the second half of the module you will read some of the chapters from the book <i>I, Robot</i>, which explore the consequences when the three laws interact and give many practical insights into the problems we are likely to face in trying to ensure the safe behaviour of robots in the 21st century.</Paragraph><Paragraph>Whilst the three laws and the positronic brains that embed them are purely fictional devices, you will see how they do reveal several important ideas about how we should regulate real robotic systems, especially in situations where they come into contact with humans.</Paragraph><InternalSection><Heading>Humanoid robots</Heading><Paragraph>Asimov&#x2019;s robots were typically humanoid, i.e. human-like. An advanced humanoid robot today is Honda&#x2019;s <a href="http://world.honda.com/ASIMO/">ASIMO</a>. This robot can move around freely, and can climb stairways and walk up and down slopes. It can be made to respond to voice inputs. This means that ASIMO can be customized and used in a variety of applications.</Paragraph><Figure><Image src="\\dog\PrintLive\Courses\t184\web\e1i1\published\images\lesson_1\t184_lesson1_f06.jpg" height="" width="100%" alt="" id="" webthumbnail="" x_imagesrc="t184_lesson1_f06.jpg" x_imagewidth="203" x_imageheight="300"><b/></Image><Caption><b>ASIMO</b></Caption><SourceReference><b>&#xA9; </b>2003 Honda Motor Co., Ltd. </SourceReference></Figure><Paragraph>A more affordable humanoid robot is the <a href="http://www.wowwee.com/">WowWee</a> Robosapien. This may be sold as a toy, but like its bigger cousin it can walk and will detect and avoid obstacles.</Paragraph><Figure><Image src="\\dog\PrintLive\Courses\t184\web\e1i1\published\images\lesson_1\t184_lesson1_f07.jpg" height="" width="100%" alt="" id="" webthumbnail="" x_imagesrc="t184_lesson1_f07.jpg" x_imagewidth="250" x_imageheight="288"/><Caption>Robosapien</Caption><SourceReference><a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/File:Robospaienv2.jpg">Wikipedia</a></SourceReference></Figure></InternalSection><InternalSection><Heading>Non-humanoid robots</Heading><Paragraph>Many robots are not humanoid, for example robot vacuum cleaners and robot lawnmowers, like those illustrated below.</Paragraph><Figure><Image src="\\dog\PrintLive\Courses\t184\web\e1i1\published\images\lesson_1\t184_lesson1_f08.jpg" height="" width="100%" alt="" id="" webthumbnail="" x_imagesrc="t184_lesson1_f08.jpg" x_imagewidth="363" x_imageheight="152"/><Caption><b>Vacuum cleaner robot (left) and robot lawnmower (right)</b></Caption><SourceReference>Vacuum cleaner: www.thetech.org; lawnmower: &#xA9; Petsafe Florida </SourceReference></Figure></InternalSection></Section><Section><Title>Definitions of robots</Title><Paragraph>The following definitions make it possible to classify most types of robot:</Paragraph><NumberedList><ListItem>A machine that can sense its environment, process information from its sensors and other internal information, decide what to do next and execute that decision will be called a robot.</ListItem><ListItem>A robot that can move using wheels, legs or other means with onboard power supply will be called a mobile robot.</ListItem><ListItem>A robot that can operate without the assistance of a human is said to be autonomous. Like many technical terms, the word autonomy is rooted in two Greek words &#x2013; <i>auto</i>, meaning &#x2018;self&#x2019;, and <i>nomos</i>, meaning &#x2018;law&#x2019;. Consequently, autonomy literally means &#x2018;self law&#x2019; and so the degree of autonomy refers to the extent to which the robot&#x2019;s behaviour is subject to its own law, or one might even say, its own free will.</ListItem><ListItem>A robot that can perform its functions in the presence of uncertainty is intelligent.</ListItem></NumberedList><Paragraph>For example, a mower that cuts grass without any intervention is autonomous. It needs sensors to know where the lawn is, and where the grass has already been cut. It needs to use that sensor information to stay on the grass and not cut down the flower beds. There&#x2019;s a lot of uncertainty in a garden, especially when there are cats, dogs and children around, and I&#x2019;d say some intelligence is necessary. So, this grass-cutting machine is an example of an intelligent, autonomous, mobile robot.</Paragraph><Paragraph>One interesting consequence is that according to our definitions most of the gladiatorial robots seen on the <i>Robot Wars</i> TV programme are not autonomous robots! Most of these machines are radio-controlled by humans, and they are not autonomous. Most rely on human vision, and they do not have sensors to know what is happening in their environment. They also rely on human information processing to decide what to do next. At best they are mobile machines using human intelligence. In this respect they are no more robots than motorcycles are.</Paragraph><Paragraph>Honda&#x2019;s ASIMO is without doubt more impressive than many <i>Robot Wars</i> &#x2018;robots&#x2019;. ASIMO is capable of walking very smoothly and even going up and down stairs. However, if you knew ASIMO was remotely controlled, would you still consider it to be an autonomous robot? Would it make ASIMO any less impressive to know that it is controlled by a person using a remote control? Do you think you are more likely to call something a robot if it looks human-like, or resembles some other living creature such as a six-legged insect?</Paragraph><Activity><Heading>Watch</Heading><Question><Paragraph><InlineFigure><Image src="\\dog\PrintLive\nonCourse\design_templates\ICONS\Web\png's\42_pixels\video_42.png" height="" width="100%" alt="" id="" webthumbnail="" x_imagesrc="video_42.png" x_imagewidth="42" x_imageheight="42"/></InlineFigure>Hans Moravec of Carnegie-Mellon University in the USA is one of the world&#x2019;s great experts on robotics. Watch the video to learn more.</Paragraph><MediaContent src="\\dog\PrintLive\Courses\t184\web\t184 lesson 1\univ-whatisrobot.flv" type="videolow"><Transcript><Paragraph>Many different organisations have different definitions for robots.  The key to their interests are the particular applications that their class of machines have already found.  </Paragraph><Paragraph>But for many of us, what a robot really is, is a machine that acts like an animal or human being. That can sense its world, can physically act in it and can understand what is going on.  </Paragraph><Paragraph>So, you might well find components of that in all kinds of different machinery and, in fact, the robot will be built by putting together a whole lot of different kinds of machinery that already exist.  </Paragraph><Paragraph>Computers represent probably the biggest missing piece of that puzzle &#x2013; the last big piece basically. Industrialisation has produced most of the other things. We have had machines that take in energy and move on their own, and since the beginning of the 1900s we have had electronic machines that can sense their environment. </Paragraph><Paragraph>But taking the data and really producing some understanding out of it and using that to control action, is the job of computers, and to date &#x2013; even though inexpensive computers are now at least a thousand times as powerful as very expensive computers were a few decades ago &#x2013; the processing power is still quite small on the scale of brain sizes and perhaps comparable to that of a very small fish or insect.  And for that reason we don&#x2019;t yet have what many of us would really like to see, robots doing neat things &#x2013; namely machines with the intelligence of larger vertebrates.</Paragraph></Transcript></MediaContent></Question></Activity><Paragraph>Throughout this module you will be asked to reflect on various issues and questions. Usually the questions relate to material that has recently been studied, but sometimes you are just expected to form your own opinion on things.</Paragraph><Paragraph>One of the objectives of T184 is to encourage you to think about issues, and construct reasoned arguments. So, spend a few minutes answering the following self-assessment questions (SAQs).</Paragraph></Section><Section><Title>Some questions</Title><SAQ><Heading>SAQ 1</Heading><Question><Paragraph>A cruise missile, illustrated below, is a pilotless rocket designed to carry an explosive warhead. It can have a long range and determines its own path using onboard cameras and position data supplied by satellite. Once it has been given a target, it guides itself towards it at high speed and explodes on reaching it. Over the past 20 years cruise missiles have been used in many conflicts, killing and injuring many soldiers and civilians.</Paragraph><Figure><Image src="\\dog\PrintLive\Courses\t184\web\e1i1\published\images\lesson_1\t184_lesson1_f09.jpg" height="" width="100%" alt="" id="" webthumbnail="" x_imagesrc="t184_lesson1_f09.jpg" x_imagewidth="350" x_imageheight="207"/><Caption>Cruise missile</Caption><SourceReference>&#xA9; US Government Material</SourceReference></Figure><NumberedList class="lower-alpha"><ListItem>To what extent can a cruise missile be described as a robot? (Hint: see my definitions of robot characteristics and think about Asimov&#x2019;s three laws.)</ListItem><ListItem>To what extent can a vacuum cleaner that cleans rooms by itself be described as a robot?</ListItem></NumberedList><Paragraph>Make a note of your answers, before looking at mine. </Paragraph></Question><Answer><Paragraph><font val="Verdana">I answered the questions by going through the definitions of intelligence, autonomous, mobile and robot provided, and seeing which applied. </font></Paragraph><NumberedList class="lower-alpha"><ListItem><font val="Verdana">To what extent is a cruise missile a robot?</font><NumberedSubsidiaryList><SubListItem><font val="Verdana">A cruise missile has sophisticated tracking equipment, including various sensors such as cameras and satellite data receivers that allow it to know where it is. Thus it can sense its environment, it can process that information, decide what to do next, and execute that decision. (Therefore, it&#x2019;s a robot.)</font></SubListItem><SubListItem><font val="Verdana">A cruise missile has an engine and its own fuel supply allowing it to fly under its own control, like a rocket. (It&#x2019;s mobile.)</font></SubListItem><SubListItem><font val="Verdana">Cruise missiles fly very fast and on &#x2018;autopilot&#x2019;, not requiring a human pilot. (They are autonomous.)</font></SubListItem><SubListItem><font val="Verdana">They operate in conditions of great uncertainty, including changing weather conditions, changes to the terrain they fly over, and possibly being fired at by counter-missile missiles. (They are intelligent.)</font></SubListItem></NumberedSubsidiaryList><font val="Verdana">Given all this, I would say that a cruise missile is an example of an intelligent autonomous mobile robot.</font></ListItem><ListItem><font val="Verdana">To what extent is a vacuum cleaner that cleans rooms by itself a robot?</font><NumberedSubsidiaryList><SubListItem><font val="Verdana">A machine that vacuum cleans rooms must have sensors to detect walls, furniture and the kind of material the floor is made of. It must process this sensor data, decide what to do next and execute it. (Therefore, it&#x2019;s a robot.)</font></SubListItem><SubListItem><font val="Verdana">The vacuum cleaner must be able to move, and since power cords could get tangled it should have its own onboard power supply. (It&#x2019;s mobile.)</font></SubListItem><SubListItem><font val="Verdana">Once switched on, the vacuum cleaner has to operate without human assistance. (It&#x2019;s autonomous.)</font></SubListItem><SubListItem><font val="Verdana">A robot vacuum cleaner has to work in circumstances of uncertainty, such as detecting the edge of the room, and detecting the presence of furniture, pets or children, and avoiding them. (It&#x2019;s intelligent.)</font></SubListItem></NumberedSubsidiaryList><Paragraph><font val="Verdana">So a vacuum cleaner that cleans rooms by itself is an intelligent, autonomous, mobile robot.</font></Paragraph></ListItem></NumberedList></Answer></SAQ><StudyNote><Paragraph><font val="Verdana"><b>Note: </b></font><font val="Verdana">My answer to SAQ 1 demonstrates an important method of analysing and classifying things. Even if you don&#x2019;t like my four definitions, you can probably apply them without too much trouble. So you can say, &#x2018;According to the T184 definitions, a cruise missile is an intelligent autonomous mobile robot. However, I don&#x2019;t like their definition of intelligence. For me, for a machine to be intelligent it must be able to speak. So as far as I am concerned, a cruise missile is just an autonomous mobile robot.&#x2019; The point here is that the classification is based on the definitions used. If you use a different definition, you may get a different classification. Often the most important thing is not which particular classification definitions are used, but that the classification definitions are explicit, they are agreed by everyone, and they are applied consistently by everyone. </font></Paragraph></StudyNote><SAQ><Heading>SAQ 2</Heading><Question><NumberedList class="lower-alpha"><ListItem>To what extent is a remote-controlled car a robot?</ListItem><ListItem>To what extent is a notebook computer a robot?</ListItem></NumberedList></Question><Answer><NumberedList class="lower-alpha"><ListItem><Paragraph>To what extent is a remote-controlled car a robot?</Paragraph><NumberedSubsidiaryList><SubListItem>A remote-controlled car does not usually have any sensors, so it&#x2019;s not really a robot.</SubListItem><SubListItem>It can move with its own onboard power supply, so it&#x2019;s mobile.</SubListItem><SubListItem>The remote-controlled car only moves about under human control, so it&#x2019;s not autonomous</SubListItem><SubListItem>A remote-controlled car operates in an uncertain environment, such as the presence of children or other remote controlled vehicles or pets. However, the intelligence required to avoid collisions, for example, comes from the human operator, so the vehicle itself is not intelligent.</SubListItem></NumberedSubsidiaryList><Paragraph>So a remote-controlled car is a mobile vehicle, but we could not call it intelligent, autonomous or a robot.</Paragraph></ListItem><ListItem><Paragraph>To what extent is a notebook computer a robot?</Paragraph><NumberedSubsidiaryList><SubListItem>A notebook computer has a keyboard and mouse that enable it to sense the external environment. Given this input data, its programs enable it to decide what to do next, and execute it. This could include writing data to disk, or displaying an image on the screen. If the computer is connected to the Internet, the intermediate circuitry could be considered as a kind of sensor from which the computer gets data. It processes these data to make decisions on what to do next, and then executes these decisions. So, by our definition, a notebook computer is indeed a robot!</SubListItem><SubListItem>By itself, a notebook computer cannot move, so it is not a mobile robot, even though it may have its own power supply.</SubListItem><SubListItem>Notebook computers are built to interact with humans. Most of the time they are totally under our control, and in this respect they are not autonomous. However, as they interact with us, our computers do a tremendous number of things by themselves. For example, once you&#x2019;ve given it a URL, you don&#x2019;t have to tell the machine how to find and display a web page. It&#x2019;s possible that a notebook computer could be left by itself for many hours doing some task like data logging. Then it would be autonomous. So, I suppose, it depends on the program that is running and how the machine is being used. I&#x2019;d say that a notebook computer is a &#x2018;sometimes-autonomous&#x2019; machine.</SubListItem><SubListItem>Notebook computers have to work in a wide variety of circumstances. There is great uncertainty about what the user will type in, and where and when the mouse is clicked. Some notebook computers have speech recognition capabilities. I&#x2019;d say that a notebook computer has quite a lot of built-in intelligence.</SubListItem></NumberedSubsidiaryList><Paragraph>So for me, a notebook computer is an intelligent, sometimes-autonomous, static robot.</Paragraph><Paragraph>This example shows a common problem in science: sometimes it&#x2019;s hard to classify things.  I found the definition of autonomous hardest to apply. On reflection, I wonder how autonomous anything can be. As we interact with other people, our freedom of action is necessarily restricted. We can&#x2019;t just do whatever we like, whenever we like.</Paragraph></ListItem></NumberedList></Answer></SAQ><SAQ><Heading>SAQ 3</Heading><Question><NumberedList class="lower-alpha"><ListItem>Do cruise missiles violate any of the laws of robotics? (Hint: think about the three laws.)</ListItem><ListItem>Do robot vacuum cleaners violate any of the laws of robotics?</ListItem></NumberedList></Question><Answer><NumberedList class="lower-alpha"><ListItem><Paragraph>Do cruise missiles violate any of the laws of robotics?</Paragraph><NumberedSubsidiaryList><SubListItem>Cruise missiles violate the first law of robotics in that they kill people. However, if the missile is aimed at a gun battery that is firing indiscriminately, then it might be argued that inaction causes harm. Generally, however, I think that violation of the first law is most likely.</SubListItem><SubListItem>Cruise missiles obey the second law, since they are instructed to carry out their missions by humans.</SubListItem><SubListItem>Cruise missiles violate the third law since they destroy themselves, but this is allowed because the second law has higher precedence.</SubListItem></NumberedSubsidiaryList></ListItem><ListItem><Paragraph>Do robot vacuum cleaners violate any of the laws of robotics?</Paragraph><NumberedSubsidiaryList><SubListItem>Robot vacuum cleaners are designed not to hurt people.</SubListItem><SubListItem>Robot vacuum cleaners do what they are instructed to do, within their own limited domain.</SubListItem><SubListItem>Robot vacuum cleaners have self-protection mechanisms.</SubListItem></NumberedSubsidiaryList><Paragraph>So, robot vacuum cleaners obey all three of the laws of robotics.</Paragraph></ListItem></NumberedList></Answer></SAQ></Section></Session><Session><Title>1.3 Artificial beings</Title><Paragraph>In this and the next session we will focus on robots as intelligent artificial beings. We&#x2019;ll start off by watching a 2008 OU/BBC TV programme <i>Man</i>&#x2013;<i>machine</i> presented by James May. He introduces the programme by saying:</Paragraph><Quote><Paragraph>When I was a small boy it was generally accepted that by the 21st century we&#x2019;d have intelligent, talking computers in every office, and domestic humanoid robots that would do the washing up for us.  Scientists would have overseen and perfected the merger between man and machine. </Paragraph><Paragraph>What a load of tosh that was!</Paragraph></Quote><Paragraph>While you watch this programme, you might like to think about some general issues it raises. Is there a real future for robotics, or will the hype always outrun the reality? Will the future hold robot housemaids, or something very different?</Paragraph><Paragraph>The programme is also a good opportunity to reflect on what defines a robot. James May encounters a wide range of different examples &#x2013; how many of them would you consider to be a &#x2018;robot&#x2019;?</Paragraph><Activity><Heading>Watch</Heading><Timing><Hours>1</Hours></Timing><Question><Paragraph><InlineFigure><Image src="\\dog\PrintLive\nonCourse\design_templates\ICONS\Web\png's\42_pixels\video_dvd_42.png" height="" width="100%" alt="" id="" webthumbnail="" x_imagesrc="video_dvd_42.png" x_imagewidth="42" x_imageheight="42"/></InlineFigure> <i>James May&#x2019;s Big Ideas: Man</i>&#x2013;<i>Machine</i>. Watch the program through. When you do so, note down for each example whether it is:</Paragraph><BulletedList><ListItem>a robot</ListItem><ListItem>autonomous</ListItem><ListItem>mobile</ListItem><ListItem>intelligent</ListItem></BulletedList><Paragraph>A full <olink targetdoc="James May DVD transcript">transcript for the DVD</olink> is available. You can also open it from the <olink targetdoc="More resources">More resources</olink> section of the website.</Paragraph></Question></Activity><SAQ><Heading>SAQ 4</Heading><Question><Paragraph>Do you think the following are: Robots? Autonomous? Mobile? Intelligent?</Paragraph><NumberedList class="lower-alpha"><ListItem>Kanagawa human exoskeleton</ListItem><ListItem>CBi humanoid</ListItem><ListItem>ASIMO</ListItem><ListItem>Geminoid</ListItem><ListItem>Mind Enhanced Roving Chair</ListItem></NumberedList></Question><Answer><Paragraph>My thoughts were:</Paragraph><NumberedList class="lower-alpha"><ListItem>Kanagawa human exoskeleton &#x2013; not a robot (although using robotic mechanisms), mobile, not autonomous, not intelligent;</ListItem><ListItem>CBi humanoid &#x2013; robot, not mobile, autonomous, intelligent</ListItem><ListItem>ASIMO &#x2013; robot, mobile, autonomous, intelligent</ListItem><ListItem>Geminoid &#x2013; not a robot (although using robotic mechanisms), not mobile, not autonomous, not intelligent</ListItem><ListItem>Mind Enhanced Roving Chair &#x2013; not a robot, mobile, not autonomous, not intelligent</ListItem></NumberedList><Paragraph>You may not entirely agree with me &#x2013; if so, why not post your thoughts on the T184 Discussion forum and see what your fellow students think?</Paragraph></Answer></SAQ><Paragraph>One message that emerges from James May&#x2019;s program is that human abilities we take for granted &#x2013; such as walking or seeing &#x2013; are extremely difficult to replicate in robots. This means that our expectations of robots (such as James&#x2019; dream of being able &#x2018;to send [a robot] downstairs to get me another beer&#x2019;) often fall well short of reality. We will see more of the challenges and solutions to these problems later in the module.</Paragraph><Paragraph>Another theme of James May&#x2019;s program is that the 1950&#x2019;s vision of mechanical men does not represent the real future of robotics. Perhaps what is emerging is a &#x2018;man-machine&#x2019; future where humans are augmented with technology and human intelligence is still required. We will look at robot futures at the end of the module.</Paragraph><Section><Title>Automatons</Title><Paragraph>There are stories of artificial beings in legend and literature. By the 18<sup>th</sup> century, artificial life must have seemed closer to reality as skilled engineers produced remarkably lifelike mechanisms. For example, Pierre and Henri-Louis Jacquet-Droz created a young woman who played the piano and a boy who could write.</Paragraph><Figure><Image src="\\dog\PrintLive\Courses\t184\web\e1i1\published\images\lesson_1\t184_lesson1_f10.jpg" height="" width="100%" alt="" id="" webthumbnail="" x_imagesrc="t184_lesson1_f10.jpg" x_imagewidth="470" x_imageheight="308"/><Caption>The Pierre and Henri-Louis Jacquet-Droz automatons</Caption><SourceReference><a href="http://www.miralab.unige.ch/automata/eightennth/jaquetdroz_uk.htm">MIRALab</a></SourceReference></Figure><Paragraph>Although the elaborate clockwork mechanisms of Pierre and Henri-Louis Jacquet-Droz are not robots in our terms, they are human-like machines doing human-like things. They are examples of automatons, defined in the dictionary as mechanisms with &#x2018;concealed motive power&#x2019;. On this module we will use the term automaton to mean a machine that operates automatically, but does not make its own decisions in a changing environment. Automatons play an important part in understanding the history of robotics because they demonstrate the high level of engineering necessary to build robots. They also demonstrate the extent to which mechanisms can be used to recreate human-like behaviour.</Paragraph><Paragraph>Although the automatons do interesting things, they lack intelligence to do new things in the face of changing circumstances. The sort of control that an automaton is subject to is sometimes referred to as automatism. An automaton is ruled by automatic behaviours that deny any sort of free will at all, unlike the behaviour of an autonomous robot. Automatic behaviours are fixed, built-in behaviours that are constructed so they cannot help but work that way, such as a particular wash program in a standard automatic washing machine.</Paragraph><Paragraph>Historically, the means of achieving artificial life reflected the technology of the day. In the mid-18th century it was the technology of metalworking and clockwork, like the automata shown above. Later, Luigi Galvani&#x2019;s discovery that electricity could make a dissected frog&#x2019;s legs twitch led to the idea that electricity could supply the life force.</Paragraph><Paragraph>As the automaton builders discovered, there was a limit to which they could make their creations perform new tasks. The automatons also lacked sensory inputs that would allow them to respond to things happening in the world around them. However, there were a few notable hoaxes. One such hoax was the Turk, a chess-playing automaton constructed by Wolfgang von Kempelen in the 18th century. Inside the &#x2018;automaton&#x2019; box was a small human chess player! If you have time you can read more about the Turk in an article in <a href="http://www.wired.com/wired/archive/10.03/turk.html">Wired magazine.</a></Paragraph><Paragraph>Having reached the limits of mechanical ingenuity, it was not until the coming of computers that further advances could be made towards artificial beings.</Paragraph><Paragraph/><Activity><Heading>Optional &#x2013; Watch and read</Heading><Question><Paragraph><InlineFigure><Image src="\\dog\PrintLive\nonCourse\design_templates\ICONS\Web\png's\42_pixels\video_42.png" height="" width="100%" alt="" id="" webthumbnail="" x_imagesrc="video_42.png" x_imagewidth="42" x_imageheight="42"/></InlineFigure> If you have time, you can read more about the construction of the Jaquet Droz automatons on the Automates Anciens website: <a href="http://www.automates-anciens.com/english_version/main_pages/androids_jaquet_droz.php">The three Jaquet-Droz androids</a>.</Paragraph><Paragraph><font val="Arial">You may also be able to find video of automatons in action by searching on video sharing sites such as YouTube.</font> </Paragraph></Question></Activity></Section><Section><Title>From automatism to autonomy</Title><Paragraph>The 19th century saw the first computing machines. This led to a more modern view of robotics, in which information processing and intelligence became important.</Paragraph><Paragraph>In 1834 Charles Babbage designed an Analytical Engine, which if built would have been the first programmable computing machine. It could be &#x2018;programmed&#x2019; by the user to execute its repertoire of instructions in any required order. The earlier Jacquard loom developed the idea of punched cards to store the information necessary for weaving different types of cloth. Babbage took up this idea, using punched cards to store programs and data that could be fed into the machine.</Paragraph><Paragraph>The Analytical Engine had a store and a mill, corresponding to the memory and processor of a modern computer. Like modern computers, the Analytical Engine could repeat the same sequence of operations many times, or loop. Also, it could perform conditional branching using &#x2018;if-then&#x2019; statements, allowing its flow of calculations to be determined by the results of its calculations. You will see examples of if-then statements in RobotLab1, and they are explained in RobotLab2.</Paragraph><Paragraph>Babbage never succeeded in building his Analytical Engine, due to the accuracy required, and funding difficulties. Nonetheless, it is now seen as a major step in the history of computing machines. If you have time and want to know more about Babbage&#x2019;s work, click on the <a href="http://www.sciencemuseum.org.uk/onlinestuff/stories/babbage.aspx">Science Museum</a> website.</Paragraph><Paragraph>Herman Hollerith invented an electromechanical machine for the 1890 census in the USA which stored population data on punched cards. Hollerith&#x2019;s Tabulating Machine Company of 1911 was later to become IBM (the International Business Machines Corporation).</Paragraph><Figure><Image src="\\dog\PrintLive\Courses\t184\web\e1i1\published\images\lesson_1\t184_lesson1_f11.jpg" height="" width="100%" alt="" id="" webthumbnail="" x_imagesrc="t184_lesson1_f11.jpg" x_imagewidth="260" x_imageheight="172"/><Caption>The Colossus computer developed at Bletchley Park in the 1940s</Caption><SourceReference>&#xA9; The National Archives</SourceReference></Figure><Paragraph>One of the first electronic computers, Colossus, was developed by Alan Turing and others at Bletchley Park (code name Station X) in Buckinghamshire to decipher German signals intelligence during the Second World War.</Paragraph><Paragraph>Even though computers were developed for &#x2018;number crunching&#x2019; applications, many scientists, including Turing, saw them as logical devices and were interested in programming them to perform intelligent tasks like playing chess. The amazing progress in the development of digital computers over the past half century has led to them being used as the major platform for investigating machine intelligence up to the present day.</Paragraph></Section><Section><Title>Competitions and challenges</Title><Paragraph>One way in which research in robotics has been stimulated in recent years has been by the introduction of competitions and challenges.</Paragraph><InternalSection><Heading>RoboCup</Heading><Paragraph>In 1997 Prof Kitano established <a href="http://www.robocup.org/">RoboCup</a> with the challenge of developing, by 2050, a team of fully autonomous humanoid robots that can take on the human world soccer champions &#x2013; and beat them!</Paragraph><Paragraph>Of course that is an ambitious goal, but international RoboCup tournaments are held every year in which teams of robots compete against each other. Different leagues allow different types of robots to compete. For example, in one league small wheeled robots compete in teams of five on a table-tennis sized table. There has also been a league specifically for football-playing Sony Aibo robot dogs. Besides soccer, there is a competition for search and rescue robots that might be used after an earthquake.</Paragraph><Paragraph>As well as being great fun for the researchers, these competitions have a serious purpose. The challenge itself, of playing football in teams of robots, requires solving many real problems in robotics that will have much wider application. Competition pits different approaches and technologies against each other and will stimulate further research and development.</Paragraph></InternalSection><InternalSection><Heading>DARPA</Heading><Paragraph>The progress that can be stimulated by challenges and competitions is vividly illustrated by the <a href="http://www.darpa.mil/grandchallenge">DARPA Grand Challenge</a>, a competition for robotic cars sponsored by the US Government&#x2019;s Defense Advanced Research Projects Agency (DARPA).</Paragraph><Paragraph>The challenge here is to produce driverless vehicles that can travel long distances on standard roads. The first competition was held in 2004: no vehicle managed the 150-mile route and the best performer only travelled 7 miles. A year later all but one of the entrants travelled further than this; five vehicles completed the 130-mile course, the winner averaging nearly 20 mph. In 2007 the competition was an urban challenge where robotic cars had to obey the rules of the road while driving over 60 miles in traffic with other robotic and human-driven cars.</Paragraph><Activity><Heading>Watch</Heading><Question><Paragraph><InlineFigure><Image src="\\dog\PrintLive\nonCourse\design_templates\ICONS\Web\png's\42_pixels\video_42.png" height="" width="100%" alt="" id="" webthumbnail="" x_imagesrc="video_42.png" x_imagewidth="42" x_imageheight="42"/></InlineFigure> <i>James May&#x2019;s Big Ideas: Come fly with me</i>. </Paragraph><MediaContent src="\\dog\PrintLive\Courses\t184\web\e1i1\published\images\lesson_1\Sequence 1.flv" type="video"><Transcript><Paragraph>This is a 1990s Mercedes S class. Not a particularly unusual car, but in October of 1994, two of them &#x2013; just like this &#x2013; did something rather incredible. They drove for 1000 kilometres around the autoroutes near Paris without crashing into anything. </Paragraph><Paragraph>And if you&#x2019;ve ever been there, you will know that that is something of a feat in itself. But what made it particularly impressive on this occasion was that no one was driving.</Paragraph><Paragraph>This was the culmination of the Prometheus project, a European venture to develop a driverless car. </Paragraph><Paragraph>Now there was a good reason that they chose the auto-routes; they are relatively hazard-free, there&#x2019;s no oncoming traffic, no roundabouts, no T-junctions and no pedestrians. Easy.</Paragraph><Paragraph>So while I&#x2019;m in California, I&#x2019;m going to meet the latest generation of driverless car. Not one that&#x2019;s just learned to go around a motorway on its own, but one that can deal with the unexpected. </Paragraph><Paragraph>That is Stamford University&#x2019;s experimental car, which they have named Junior. Gathered around it is the team of engineering boffins who&#x2019;ve made it work. And this is the challenging environment in which we shall be testing it. It&#x2019;s some cones in a car park. But it is a car park for a very good reason, you see. If we took that out on the public road, and it ran amok and caused an accident, well, it&#x2019;s a robot, so they wouldn&#x2019;t know who to sue. Americans don&#x2019;t like that. </Paragraph><Paragraph>Right. Gear stick in, panic button set, steering, throttle, brakes, gear change, park brake, turn signal &#x2013; go! </Paragraph><Paragraph>Go on then &#x2013; ooh! And we&#x2019;re off!</Paragraph><Paragraph>Not touching anything, I haven&#x2019;t got my foot on the pedals, look, hands, no hands. I have to say this is quite disconcerting because the urge to get hold of the steering wheel, especially as that big lamppost is approaching, is overwhelming. Here&#x2019;s a junction, slowing down. It&#x2019;s turning! [laughs]</Paragraph><Paragraph>Very good. </Paragraph><Paragraph>Well, that&#x2019;s all very good fun. But how will this help the flying car? </Paragraph><Paragraph>Proponents of the flying car talk about this thing called &#x2018;the highway in the sky&#x2019;.</Paragraph><Paragraph>It&#x2019;s like a motorway, everything is going the same direction, they keep a constant distance from each other, they go at a constant speed.</Paragraph><Paragraph>Controlling a flying car in that environment is actually relatively simple. </Paragraph><Paragraph>The driverless cars in the nineties could handle that sort of thing.</Paragraph><Paragraph>The difficult bit is the transitional phase, taking off and joining the stream or dropping out of the stream and coming in to land. </Paragraph><Paragraph>That&#x2019;s when most accidents are likely to happen, and that&#x2019;s when you&#x2019;d need a more sophisticated system like this. Junior uses GPS to tell the car where it is, but also lasers and radar to detect hazards around it. </Paragraph><Paragraph>So I&#x2019;m driving along on my way to the shops and there is a car parked by the side of the road in front, but there is also another car coming the other way. Junior can see all that happening, so it waits, the car&#x2019;s gone past, and there you go &#x2013; piece of cake. </Paragraph><Paragraph>So, having detected objects, it has made an assessment of the situation and taken action, entirely autonomously. </Paragraph><Paragraph>It can even handle a junction that baffles most Europeans &#x2013; and a few Americans &#x2013; the notorious four-way stop.</Paragraph><Paragraph>We come to the four-way stop, stop and have a look, there is another car coming, which Junior has seen. He was there first, we&#x2019;ve come to a stop. He drives on &#x2013; that&#x2019;s the rule on American unmarked crossroads. He&#x2019;s gone, we can go! I think I&#x2019;ll have one of these. </Paragraph><Paragraph>So something like Junior here, with a few modifications, should be able to handle a 3D world full of dangers like tall buildings, other flying cars, and joining streams of flying traffic. </Paragraph><Paragraph>Ah, we&#x2019;re here. Marvellous! I&#x2019;m off to the shops &#x2013; you wait in the car, car.</Paragraph><Paragraph>There&#x2019;s no doubt that entrusting your safety to a machine does require an enormous leap of faith, but it is inevitable if flying cars are to become a reality, if only to avoid aerial carnage</Paragraph></Transcript></MediaContent><Paragraph>Watch this video clip, in which James May gets first-hand experience of Stamford University&#x2019;s robotic car, Junior, which took part in the 2007 DARPA urban challenge. He also speculates on what this might mean for a future flying car. However, as James says:</Paragraph><Quote><Paragraph>&#x2018;Most car accidents are due to human error, or &#x2018;the nut behind the wheel&#x2019; as someone once famously put it. So if we all took to the air and flying cars crowded the skies, the &#x2018;nut&#x2019; would have to be removed from the equation. And to work out how, for the moment, it is best to stick to the ground.&#x2019;</Paragraph><SourceReference>May, 2008</SourceReference></Quote></Question></Activity></InternalSection><InternalSection><Heading>Kids in robotics</Heading><Paragraph>There are robotics challenges and competitions open to school-age students, too. RoboCup has its counterpart in RoboCupJunior which, besides soccer and rescue, has a robot dance competition; you may have seen a video of this earlier in this Lesson. First LEGO League is another international competition, this time based around the LEGO Mindstorms robotics kit. </Paragraph><Paragraph>Besides being great fun, these events provide real educational opportunities for school-age students who must work as a team to design and build their robots. After all, if a team of humanoid robots is to beat the world soccer champions by 2050, it will be the school kids of today that must build them!</Paragraph></InternalSection></Section></Session><Session><Title>1.4 Robot brains and computers</Title><Paragraph>Many explanations have been offered of how the brain works. A large proportion of these use metaphors that reflect the latest technologies of the time. These include Ren&#xE9; Descartes&#x2019; hydraulic analogy of a tank and pumping system, clockwork mechanisms (e.g. automatons), mechanical calculating machines, telephone switchboards routing messages, and most recently computers and supercomputers.</Paragraph><Paragraph>Many modern robots use digital computers and programs, and use computer power to solve problems. In principle, the more powerful the computer, the more computations it can perform and the more difficult the problems it can solve.</Paragraph><Paragraph>Underlying the power of a computer is the amount of computation that can be performed on a computer chip. This, in turn, is related to the number of individual transistors or switches that can be manufactured on each chip. According to Moore&#x2019;s law, computer power doubles about every 18 months, or by a factor of four every three years. This gives the breath-taking prediction that in 20 years, computers will be thousands of times more powerful than they are now!</Paragraph><Figure><Image src="\\dog\PrintLive\Courses\t184\web\e1i1\published\images\lesson_1\t184_lesson1_f12.gif" height="" width="100%" alt="" id="" webthumbnail="" x_imagesrc="t184_lesson1_f12.gif" x_imagewidth="511" x_imageheight="292"/><Caption>Increasing computer power from 1970 to 2000</Caption></Figure><Paragraph>Commonsense suggests that there are limits to this increase. Moore&#x2019;s law is actually related to the number of microscopic components that can be laid down in a given area of silicon. It is recognised that ultimately the laws of physics will limit this, possibly in the next 10 to 20 years. In the meantime, the increase in computer power &#x2013; and the &#x2018;bang-for-your-buck&#x2019; &#x2013; marches relentlessly on.</Paragraph><InternalSection><Heading>Are brains computers?</Heading></InternalSection><Paragraph>If intelligence depended on raw computer power, and the ability to process more and more computer instructions faster and faster, then we could expect to see the intelligence of machines increase rapidly. We don&#x2019;t, so &#x2018;intelligence&#x2019; appears to involve more than the ability simply to compute. Clearly, the digital computer is completely different from the benchmark of intelligence, the human brain.</Paragraph><Paragraph>Our brains are made up of nerve cells called neurons, billions of them all connected together. As shown below, a neuron has many inputs (called dendrites), a cell body, and a long thread-like output called an axon. The dendrites of each individual neuron receive electrochemical signals from many other neurons. When these inputs collectively exceed a threshold, the nerve cell &#x2018;fires&#x2019;, and a signal passes to the axon. This is, in turn, conveyed to other nerve cells.</Paragraph><Figure><Image src="\\dog\PrintLive\Courses\t184\web\e1i1\published\images\lesson_1\t184_lesson1_f13.gif" height="" width="100%" alt="" id="" webthumbnail="" x_imagesrc="t184_lesson1_f13.gif" x_imagewidth="512" x_imageheight="199"/></Figure><Paragraph>Neurons are much slower than digital computers. They work on a timescale of milliseconds (1/1000 seconds) while computers work on a timescale of nanoseconds (1/1000,000,000 seconds). That is, computers work about a million times faster than the neurons in our brains.</Paragraph><Paragraph>You can get a feel for the rate at which the brain processes information at a conscious level from the following example. Early films were displayed at 12 frames per second, about 1 every 85 milliseconds. Our brains can detect the flicker at this rate. A television displays 50 images per second, or one every 20 milliseconds. This suggests that your eyes and brain process visual information in a time frame of somewhere between 20 and 85 milliseconds.</Paragraph><Paragraph>Even though computers work millions of times faster than our eyes and brains, computers have very limited vision abilities at the present time. This suggests that the way we are programming computers to understand visual scenes differs from the way in which our eyes and brains process similar information. One difference is that current computers only execute one or maybe a few instructions at a time, whereas in the brain very many neurons may be firing at the same time, perhaps processing different features of an image in parallel. </Paragraph><InternalSection><Heading>Artificial neural networks</Heading></InternalSection><Paragraph>Although digital computers have been the dominant technology in robotics research, artificial neural networks have been the subject of intense research only over the past 20 years.</Paragraph><Paragraph>However, in 1943 Warren S. McCulloch, a neuroscientist, and Walter Pitts, a logician, developed a simplified model of a neuron. These could perform simple logical calculations, and it was thought that with millions of such neurons the brain could be modelled by a computer. However, McCulloch and Pitts&#x2019; mathematically defined neurons lacked the ability to learn. Modifications were made to the model, but even so, there followed a period of about 20 years after this in which research in neural networks virtually stopped. In the 1980s, new methods for training these networks were discovered, allowing the networks to learn to perform various tasks. These techniques in &#x2018;parallel distributed processing&#x2019; brought about an explosion of research interest in artificial neural networks that continues to this day.</Paragraph><Paragraph>Roboticists often use combinations of traditional computer programs and neural processing. Generally it is agreed that the information processing and pattern recognition capabilities of the current generation of robots are very low indeed, at least compared with a human brain.</Paragraph><Section><Title>Artificial intelligence</Title><Paragraph><b>What is intelligence?</b></Paragraph><Paragraph>It is difficult to give a good definition of intelligence for both humans and robots. One definition of artificial intelligence (AI) is that it is behaviour that if carried out by humans would be considered intelligent &#x2013; but that leaves us needing to define human intelligence.</Paragraph><Paragraph>A measure of human intelligence widely used in the past was that of IQ (intelligence quotient) tests that were based on a mixture of general knowledge and puzzles. The AI community of the 1950s and 60s made good progress in writing programs that could solve similar logical puzzles. But the appealing idea that IQ tests are an objective measure of human intelligence, let alone artificial intelligence, is highly problematic in practice, because of the inevitable cultural context of some of the questions in IQ tests, and because some people can improve their performance by practising the tests. </Paragraph><Paragraph>Human intelligence is now frequently seen as having many dimensions, including the ability to carry out spatial reasoning, write and speak fluently, use imagination, and deploy emotional intelligence in social relationships. Intelligence is too complex to be represented by a number. An AI system may be able to solve simple puzzles, but it completely lacks the subtlety and complexity of human intelligence.</Paragraph><Paragraph>Another early test bed for artificial intelligence was playing chess. No other animal plays chess &#x2013; surely this is an ability that requires human levels of intelligence? The AI community also made impressive progress in chess playing computers: in 1997 the IBM supercomputer Deep Blue won a match against the world chess champion, Gary Kasparov.</Paragraph><Paragraph>Like the much simpler game of noughts-and-crosses, chess is an example of a closed problem: it has a fixed number of pieces and a small number of rules. A program that played noughts-and-crosses would not be very impressive and a chess playing computer might be no more &#x2018;intelligent&#x2019; but simply rely on the speed of the computer to consider large numbers of possible moves looking for the best. However, the complexity of living in the real world is so much larger than the complexity of a board game that maybe chess playing is not a good indication of intelligence.</Paragraph><Paragraph>Perhaps the best we can say is that machines that are able to deal with uncertainty in their environment should be classified as intelligent.</Paragraph></Section><Section><Title>Animal analogies in robotics</Title><Paragraph>Roboticists are increasingly finding biological systems a rich vein of inspiration: animals move, sense their environment and behave in so many different ways. And while we may not consider a cockroach very intelligent, its combination of sensing, moving and behaviour patterns is sufficient for the cockroach to function autonomously in the world. Creating a robotic cockroach may be a more achievable goal than building a humanoid robot.</Paragraph><Paragraph>Biomimetics is the name given to this approach to robotics which is inspired by biological systems. </Paragraph><Paragraph>For example, the physical characteristics of insects have a part to play in the design of robots. Having six legs makes walking easier because it enables an insect to keep three legs on the ground at all times. Legs are also well-adapted to coping with rugged terrain. The study of such creatures suggests that multi-legged robots could be better than wheeled robots for many purposes.</Paragraph><Paragraph>One of the great problems in robotics is making them self-sustaining and autonomous. Homeostasis, the process by which living things keep themselves in a functional state in a changing environment, is a challenge in robotics. For example, just as keeping your body temperature constant is a very important homeostatic process in humans, it may also be a requirement of robots, which contain sensitive electronic equipment.</Paragraph><Paragraph>Respiration, excretion and reproduction are other essential features of natural life, which may be useful to a greater or lesser extent in robots.</Paragraph><Paragraph>Biomimetics may also give us a different slant on &#x2018;intelligence&#x2019;. In contrast to early attempts at building robots, which tried to build artificial brains with human-like intelligence, it is now known that animals such as insects, with much simpler brains, can achieve feats of great complexity by working together. The success of insects suggests that they may have something to teach us about robotics.</Paragraph><Figure><Image src="\\dog\PrintLive\Courses\t184\web\e1i1\published\images\lesson_1\t184_lesson1_f14.jpg" height="" width="100%" alt="" id="" webthumbnail="" x_imagesrc="t184_lesson1_f14.jpg" x_imagewidth="200" x_imageheight="264"/><Caption>A termite mound in Kakadu National Park, Australia</Caption><SourceReference>&#xA9; Gopal Venkat, www.travel-library.com</SourceReference></Figure><Paragraph>Termite hills are complex, resulting from many termites acting together, in the absence of a &#x2018;termite in charge&#x2019;. Thus, complex behaviour can emerge from the interaction of many relatively simple animals. It is possible that complex robotic behaviour will emerge from the interaction of many relatively simple robots.</Paragraph><Paragraph/></Section><Section><Title>Will robots take over the world?</Title><Paragraph>The desire to create artificial beings often has the associated fear that our creations might behave undesirably or that they might take over.</Paragraph><Paragraph>The story of Frankenstein in Mary Shelley&#x2019;s book about the creation of a being from the parts of many human bodies and then brought to life with electricity, turns out badly. Initially disposed to be gentle and kind, the robot is mistreated by people, and becomes a violent monster. Similarly, Rossum&#x2019;s Universal Robots were used to serve the human race in factories and the military. Badly treated by their human masters, they revolted and killed nearly everyone.</Paragraph><Paragraph>Some people have a concern that irresponsible scientists or technologists may create robots that will take over the world. For example, scientists created the atomic bomb, which has the power to destroy humanity. Today there are fears about genetic modification of plants and animals, and that scientists may take irreversible steps towards our destruction.</Paragraph><Paragraph>There are many reasons to believe that robots will not take over the world in our lifetimes, or ever. Certain robots may become supremely adapted to artificial environments where uncertainty is kept to a minimum. However, their ability to cope with the natural world in all its glorious complexity is likely to be severely restricted for a long time to come. By the time you finish this module you will be able to make a considered judgement for yourself.</Paragraph></Section></Session><Session><Title>1.5 RobotLab1</Title><Paragraph>The practical work on this module makes use of the Open University&#x2019;s robotics software, RobotLab. There is one RobotLab session per week. The session this week (RobotLab1) gives you an overview of the practical work you will be doing in this and coming weeks. As you work through the activities in RobotLab1 you will begin to appreciate how RobotLab works, and explore some of its features. If you have the Lego Mindstorms kit you will be able to build and commission the Pedro robot. If you don&#x2019;t have the kit you will be able to experiment with Simon, a simulated robot, on your computer screen.</Paragraph><Paragraph>Download the pdf file, &#x2018;RobotLab1&#x2019;, from the link below. This tells you how to get started and gives you full instructions. You will need to read and follow the instructions carefully. You may find it easier to print the file out. The work should take you about 4 &#x2013; 5 hours. When you have completed RobotLab1 you may continue to the next session of Lesson 1.</Paragraph><Activity><Heading>RobotLab</Heading><Question><Paragraph><InlineFigure><Image src="\\dog\PrintLive\nonCourse\design_templates\ICONS\Web\png's\42_pixels\robotlab_42.png" height="" width="100%" alt="" id="" webthumbnail="" x_imagesrc="robotlab_42.png" x_imagewidth="42" x_imageheight="35"/></InlineFigure> Download the lab guide for <olink targetdoc="RobotLab1">RobotLab1</olink> and then carry out the activities.</Paragraph><Paragraph>If you are using the Lego Mindstorms kit you&#x2019;ll also need the robot Build Instructions for RobotLab1 &#x2013; these are on the T184 CD-ROM. However, please don&#x2019;t build Pedro until asked to do so.</Paragraph></Question></Activity><Paragraph>Grateful acknowledgement is made to LEGO for use of components from the LEGO MindStorms RIS kit (<a href="http://www.legomindstorms.com/">www.legomindstorms.com</a>).</Paragraph></Session><Session><Title>1.6 Summary</Title><Paragraph>In Lesson 1 you have been introduced to T184. The lesson has looked at the development of robotics since the early 18th century. In approximate chronological order, some of the most significant milestones you have met so far include:</Paragraph><BulletedList><ListItem>automata such as those of Pierre and Henri-Louis Jacquet-Droz;</ListItem><ListItem>Babbage&#x2019;s calculating machines;</ListItem><ListItem>Rossum&#x2019;s Universal Robots;</ListItem><ListItem>Asimov&#x2019;s three laws of robotics;</ListItem><ListItem>the invention of digital and neural computation;</ListItem><ListItem>developments in artificial intelligence;</ListItem><ListItem>Moore&#x2019;s law;</ListItem><ListItem>Deep Blue beating the world chess champion;</ListItem><ListItem>animal metaphors and intelligence emerging in robot swarms;</ListItem><ListItem>ASIMO, a bipedal robot that can run;</ListItem><ListItem>RoboCup: robots to beat the soccer world champions by 2050.</ListItem></BulletedList><Paragraph>You have also used RobotLab to investigate some elementary ideas in programming robots. In this context you have considered the questions:</Paragraph><BulletedList><ListItem>what is a robot, and how can robots be classified?</ListItem><ListItem>should all robots obey the three laws of robotics?</ListItem><ListItem>what is intelligence in machines?</ListItem><ListItem>is there danger of robots taking over from humans?</ListItem></BulletedList><Paragraph>We hope you enjoyed this first taste of robotics, and found the many questions it has raised stimulating.</Paragraph><StudyNote><Paragraph><b>Where next</b>:</Paragraph><Paragraph>This is the end of Lesson 1. Now go on to <olink targetdoc="Lesson 2"><font val="Verdana"><language val="">Lesson 2</language></font></olink></Paragraph></StudyNote></Session><BackMatter><References><Reference>Asimov, I. (1995),<i> The Complete Robot</i>, Voyager.</Reference><Reference> <i>James May&#x2019;s Big Ideas: Come Fly With Me</i>, BBC/OU television programme, 2008.</Reference></References></BackMatter></Unit><settings><numbering><Session autonumber="false"/><Section autonumber="false"/><SubSection autonumber="false"/><SubSubSection autonumber="false"/><Activity autonumber="false"/><Exercise autonumber="false"/><Box autonumber="false"/><CaseStudy autonumber="false"/><Quote autonumber="false"/><Extract autonumber="false"/><Dialogue autonumber="false"/><KeyPoints autonumber="false"/><Reading autonumber="false"/><StudyNote autonumber="false"/><Example autonumber="false"/><Verse autonumber="false"/><SAQ autonumber="false"/><ComputerDisplay autonumber="false"/><Summary autonumber="false"/><ProgramListing autonumber="false"/><ITQ autonumber="false"/><Tables autonumber="false"/><Figures autonumber="false"/><MediaContent autonumber="false"/><Chemistry autonumber="false"/></numbering><discussion_alias>Comment</discussion_alias><session_prefix/></settings></Item>
