<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<Item TextType="CompleteItem" SchemaVersion="1.2" id="Xweek1" ACSPageNumber="15" ACSTemplate="generic_unnumbered" ACSCourseItem="T151" LastRendering="VLE Preview" SessionStartNumber="1" Language="" DiscussionAlias="Discussion" SessionAlias="" SecondColour="None" ThirdColour="None" FourthColour="None" Logo="colour"><CourseCode>T151</CourseCode><CourseTitle><language val="">Digital worlds: designing games, creating alternative realities</language></CourseTitle><ItemID/><ItemTitle>Week 1</ItemTitle><FrontMatter><ByLine/><Imprint><Standard><GeneralInfo><Paragraph/></GeneralInfo><Address><AddressLine>The Open University</AddressLine><AddressLine>Walton Hall,</AddressLine><AddressLine>Milton Keynes</AddressLine><AddressLine>MK7 6AA</AddressLine></Address><FirstPublished><Paragraph>First published year 2008.</Paragraph></FirstPublished><Copyright><Paragraph>© 2008 The Open University</Paragraph></Copyright><Rights><Paragraph>All rights reserved. No part of this publication may be reproduced, stored in a retrieval system, or transmitted in any form or by any means, electronic, mechanical, photocopying, recording, or otherwise without either the prior written permission of the publishers or a licence permitting restricted copying issued by the Copyright Licensing Agency, 90 Tottenham Court Road, London W1P 0LP. This material may not be lent, resold, hired out or otherwise disposed of by way of trade in any form of binding or cover other than that in which it is published, without the prior consent of the Publishers.</Paragraph></Rights><Edited><Paragraph>Edited, designed and typeset by The Open University</Paragraph></Edited><Typeset><Paragraph/></Typeset><Printed><Paragraph>Printed in the United Kingdom by printer</Paragraph></Printed><ISBN/><Edition>1.1</Edition></Standard></Imprint></FrontMatter><Unit><UnitID/><UnitTitle/><ByLine/><Session><Title>Week 1</Title><Section><Title>Introduction </Title><Paragraph>Have you ever played a computer game, or watched someone playing a computer game, and wondered how the game works, either from a technical point of view, or at a more psychological level? Why is one game fun to play, for example, when another is not? </Paragraph><Paragraph>Perhaps you’ve noticed an increasing number of television adverts for computer games, many of them looking like big budget Hollywood movie trailers, and asked yourself just how big an industry computer gaming really is? </Paragraph><Paragraph>T151 aims to give you a greater understanding of the role interactive computer games play in today's society, as well as an understanding of how they actually work. From the technical basics, through the development process, to marketing and distribution; from the simplest two-dimensional computer arcade games like <i>Pac-Man</i> and <i>Space Invaders</i>, to immersive three-dimensional virtual worlds populated by thousands of other people, you’ll see how the media landscape is changing, and how game technology is helping to drive that change. </Paragraph><Paragraph>First of all, let’s have some ground rules: </Paragraph><NumberedList><ListItem><i>This ‘</i><i>module</i><i>’ is not a </i><i>module</i><i> about learning how to play computer games better.</i> That said, one of the best ways of learning about game design is to look at – and play – some of the games that are already out there. I’ll direct you to trailers and reviews of some of these games at appropriate points, as well as providing links to online games you can experience for yourself and opportunities to explore some virtual worlds; <i>but don’t spend too long playing with them!</i> If you already are a gameplayer, we’ll hopefully provide you with new ways of looking at, and thinking about, the games you play. </ListItem><ListItem><i>This </i><i>module</i><i> draws heavily on third party resources</i>. Many of the resources you will be asked to read will be found on the Digital Worlds blog as well as other, third party websites. The Digital Worlds blog records my own journey through the world of computer games and interactive media design and was written to help others learn about this world as I explored it. </ListItem><ListItem><i>You will need to know how to read blog posts and other 'web native' documents</i>. At times I will refer you to informed blog posts on a particular topic. Many blog authors embed their articles, or blog posts, in the context of other blog posts through the use of hyperlinks, so you may find many of the posts include links to other stories and resources. You do not have to follow all these links if you do not want to, but you may find that if you want to learn more about a particular topic, the linked references will provide additional information. One technique I use is to open links in a separate tab in my browser so that I can refer to them later. (In many browsers, you can open a link in a new tab by pressing the control key when you click on the link (CTRL+CLICK). Apple Mac users should use COMMAND+CLICK (aka APPLE+CLICK).)  </ListItem></NumberedList><Paragraph>An inevitable implication of the way this module has been designed is that you will have to spend a good deal of time online. I realise that not every one of you will be overjoyed at that prospect. However, I do hope you’ll gain some appreciation about how widely scattered resources that are available on the web can be gathered together in a structured way (much as a museum curator puts together an exhibition on a particular topic from a wide range of possible sources and artefacts) in order to provide a coherent learning journey. </Paragraph><Paragraph>The module was designed to be ‘social’. That is, throughout the module there are ‘calls to action’ that encourage you to participate in a variety of activities on the module forums. Whilst your participation in these forums is not assessed, you may find that you get more out of the module if you do engage in discussions with your fellow students.</Paragraph><Paragraph>The module is structured into nine sections, each of which should involve about 10 hours of study, or one week’s worth of work. I’ve tried to make each section self-contained, so that you will have a clear idea of what you need to have covered by the end of it. You can mark off your progress through the module by using the check boxes associated with each topic on the module calendar. Game Maker activities are locked until you have marked the previous Game Maker activity as complete. The final week of the module is dedicated to the EMA, although you will also be expected to work towards that EMA throughout the whole of the module. </Paragraph></Section><Section><Title>Topic exploration 1A – <b>So what is a game? </b></Title><Paragraph>For a module that is largely about deepening our appreciation of interactive computer games, we need to start by taking a step back and considering just what games, in general, are, and how <i>interactive</i> computer games might differ from other traditional sorts of game. In this topic, you will explore just what it is that we mean when we think of ‘games’, computer games and otherwise. </Paragraph><Activity><Question><Paragraph>To get things started, write down the names of three of your favourite games (of any kind), and then ask yourself: what do they have in common? Once you’ve done that, try to write down your own definition of what a game is. </Paragraph><Paragraph><font val="Verdana">Once you have come up with your own definition of a game, post it to the </font><font val="Verdana">module</font><font val="Verdana"> forum to see how it compares with everybody else's definition, and whether there appears to be any consensus about what a game actually is. </font></Paragraph><Paragraph><olink targetdoc="General Discussion Forum">Go to the forum now.</olink><InlineFigure><Image src="\\dog\PrintLive\nonCourse\design_templates\ICONS\Web\png's\32_pixels\forum_32.png" height="" width="100%" alt="" id="" webthumbnail="" x_imagesrc="forum_32.png" x_imagewidth="32" x_imageheight="32"/></InlineFigure></Paragraph></Question><Answer><Paragraph><font val="Verdana">Three of my favourite games are </font><font val="Verdana"><i>Carcassonne</i></font><font val="Verdana"> (a tile matching board game), </font><font val="Verdana"><i>Boom Blox</i></font><font val="Verdana"> (a Nintendo Wii game where the idea is to knock things down), and </font><font val="Verdana"><i>Denki Blocks</i></font><font val="Verdana"> (a puzzle game I have for an old Game Boy Color that lives in my car!). Part of the attraction for me of each of these games is the puzzle solving aspect – in </font><font val="Verdana"><i>Boom Blox</i></font><font val="Verdana">, this relates to finding the best angle from which to throw objects at the towers of blocks you are supposed to knock down; in </font><font val="Verdana"><i>Denki Blocks</i></font><font val="Verdana">, you are restricted as to how you can move the blocks around the screen to create specific collections of blocks. The visual design of each of the games is also ‘uplifting’ – each of the games are nicely designed using bright, primary colours. The two computer games can be played as solo games, or by taking turns with another player (although there the competition is to see who scores most, rather than playing directly against each other). They are also similar in that both games are made up of lots of separate puzzles, grouped together in levels by theme or difficulty. Each separate puzzle only takes a few minutes to complete. In </font><font val="Verdana"><i>Carcassonne</i></font><font val="Verdana">, players can choose to cooperate or compete aggressively with each other, and may use different strategies throughout the game. </font><font val="Verdana"><i>Carcassonne</i></font><font val="Verdana"> has different ‘phases’ across the game, too, which accommodate different strategies. Unlike the other games, </font><font val="Verdana"><i>Carcassonne</i></font><font val="Verdana"> is played through from start to finish in one sitting (about 45 minutes). Each game of </font><font val="Verdana"><i>Carcassonne</i></font><font val="Verdana"> tends to turn out differently, where the puzzles in the two computer games are ‘fixed’.</font></Paragraph><Paragraph><font val="Verdana">For me, and off the top of my head, a game is something that is </font><font val="Verdana"><i>fun</i></font><font val="Verdana">, provides a challenge (in the sense of requiring me as a player to </font><font val="Verdana"><i>do</i></font><font val="Verdana"> something, or meet some sort of </font><font val="Verdana"><i>goal</i></font><font val="Verdana">), and has a limited set of ‘moves’ or things that are allowed in the game (that is, a game has </font><font val="Verdana"><i>rules</i></font><font val="Verdana">). </font></Paragraph></Answer></Activity><SubSection><Title>Questions and suggested resources </Title><Paragraph>Try to answer the following questions based on your reading of the suggested resources below (that is, the Digital Worlds resources, the Readings and the recommended Links). Remember, the questions are there in part to provide you with different ‘lenses’ that you can use to help guide your reading of the resources in one of the two following ways – a critical way (‘what does this resource <i>actually</i> have to say about this topic?’); and a reflective way (‘does what the resources say about this topic make sense to me in terms of what I already believe and understand?’). </Paragraph><NumberedList><ListItem>What are the defining characteristics of games in general? </ListItem><ListItem>To what extent are there different ‘sorts’ of game and what makes them different? </ListItem><ListItem>How does the number of players influence what's possible in a game? </ListItem><ListItem>What is the ‘Magic Circle’ when that phrase is applied in terms of games studies? </ListItem><ListItem>To what extent do the rules of ‘traditional games’ and ‘computer games’ differ? Who enforces the rules in each case? </ListItem></NumberedList><Paragraph>As you work through the material, make notes on the questions as you go. If you find interesting or relevant sources that complement (or challenge) the resources I’ve suggested, post them to your Delicious, or RefWorks, account and tag them with ‘T151’ (plus any other tags that seem useful to you<i>). </i></Paragraph><Paragraph><b>Spend no more than 1.5 hours exploring this topic.</b> </Paragraph><Paragraph>Without looking at your previous definition of a game, how would you now define a game? Write your definition down. How does it compare to your original definition? </Paragraph><Paragraph>When you’ve finished, read My observations on Topic exploration 1A. </Paragraph><InternalSection><Heading>Digital Worlds resources </Heading><BulletedList><ListItem><a href="http://digitalworlds.wordpress.com/2008/03/05/so-what-is-a-game/">So What is a Game?</a> </ListItem><ListItem><a href="http://digitalworlds.wordpress.com/2008/03/07/thoughts-on-the-understanding-games-tutorial-episode-1/">Thoughts on the ‘Understanding Games Tutorial, Episode 1’</a> </ListItem><ListItem><a href="http://digitalworlds.wordpress.com/2008/03/10/whose-rules/">Whose Rules?</a> </ListItem><ListItem><a href="http://digitalworlds.wordpress.com/2008/03/11/getting-philosophical-about-games/">Getting Philosophical About Games</a> </ListItem></BulletedList></InternalSection><InternalSection><Heading>Readings </Heading><BulletedList><ListItem><a href="http://www.thegamesjournal.com/articles/WhatIsaGame.shtml">What Is a Game?</a> – Wolfgang Kramer, <i>The Games Journal</i>, December 2000 </ListItem><ListItem><a href="http://www.jstor.org.libezproxy.open.ac.uk/page/termsConfirm.jsp?redirectUri=/stable/pdfplus/186102.pdf">What Is A Game?</a> – Suits, B. <i>Philosophy of Science</i> 1967, Vol. 34(2), pp. 148-156.  </ListItem></BulletedList></InternalSection><InternalSection><Heading>Links </Heading><BulletedList><ListItem><a href="http://www.pixelate.de/games/understanding-games/episode/1">Understanding Games, Episode 1</a> </ListItem></BulletedList></InternalSection></SubSection><SubSection><Title>My observations on Topic exploration 1A </Title><Paragraph>Although definitions of what constitutes a game differ, there are several distinguishing features that seem to appear in the majority of games: for example, <i>rules</i> limit what players can and can't do, and one or more <i>goals</i> are often specified in order to provide a motivating reason for performing a particular task. In many games, a pitch, board or other marked out area identifies that part of the world in which the game is played and within which the game rules apply. In addition, obstacles may feature in the game in order to obstruct a straightforward progression from the starting state to the goal. </Paragraph><Paragraph>Games differ from each other along a wide range of dimensions. For example, ‘sports games’ or ‘adventure games’ identify a theme or ‘thematic dimension’, arcade games and ‘first-person shooter’ games identify both different styles of ‘gameplay’. These dimensions might also be thought of as defining different game genres. By categorising a game in a particular way, we might also set up different expectations about the aesthetics of a game (that is, how the games look and feel) based on convention, or an understanding achieved through familiarity of how previous games in that genre were presented. </Paragraph><Paragraph>The number of players in a game – and how they relate to each other – can also be used to distinguish different sorts of game; in some cases players might cooperate with each other, in others they might compete directly against each other. Competitive games might be further broken down to consider cases where players are in direct conflict or competition with each other – such as one player fighting another – or competing ‘alongside’ or in turn with one another. For example, in a rally driving game each player might take it in turn to drive round the circuit. In this case, the actions of one player are independent from the actions of the other. In some games, the relationships or affiliations between players may shift over time, with players sometimes cooperating or sometimes competing depending on the current state of the game. </Paragraph><Paragraph>The Magic Circle is one way of describing the strange state of affairs that applies in many games – the 'suspension of disbelief' that allows the game world to take on a particular sort of reality, with a particular set of ‘physical laws’ defined by the game rules. This ability of games to immerse the player in some sort of ‘closed world’ or ‘alternative reality’, where they happily conform to a set of arbitrary rules, and even go so far as to moderate their own behaviour so as to act within those rules, is one of the most powerful features of games. In many cases, the ability to provide the player with the actual experience of living out a fantasy as if for real, within the game world, is what makes games so compelling. </Paragraph><Paragraph>In a computer game, the game rules are implemented by software, and may actually be built into the very fabric of the game world as the ‘physics’ of that world – the computer enforces the rules and illegal ‘moves’ are not just disallowed but may actually be impossible to make (unless there is a flaw in the way the game has been programmed); a good example of this is computer chess, where players are typically prevented from making illegal moves. In contrast, in many 'real world' games, the game players may actually enforce the rules themselves, or call on the assistance of an umpire or referee to enforce the rules and stop infringements of them. </Paragraph></SubSection></Section><Section><Title>Topic exploration 1B – The history of gaming: how did we get here, and where is here anyway? </Title><Paragraph/><Paragraph>In this topic, you will start to explore the world of computer games <font val="Verdana"> </font>in a little more detail, getting a feel for what's possible in today's games, compared to what was possible in the earliest days of computer gaming, and exploring just how big an industry it is today. (‘<font val="Verdana">Computer games’ is a clumsy label, but it's the best one we've got. I do sometimes wonder whether we should be calling them screen games, or screen-based games, because we experience them through a screen?!)</font></Paragraph><Activity><Question><Paragraph>If you watch advert breaks on television, you will almost definitely see adverts for computer games that are reminiscent of film trailers. So (to use a well-worn catchphrase) here's your starter for ten: for a big summer release of a major Hollywood film, what would you expect the first weekend's cinema receipts to be on the opening weekend? How many times <i>bigger</i> is this figure likely to be in terms of revenue than the first weekend receipts for a blockbuster computer game? </Paragraph><Paragraph>Before you peak at the answer, write it down (no cheating). </Paragraph><Paragraph>What do you reckon? A major league film might take <i>ten</i> times as much as a major game release? <i>Twenty</i> times as much? <i>Fifty</i> times? A <i>hundred</i> times? </Paragraph><Paragraph>Bear in mind that a film release in the UK might take anything from £2 million to £15 million in its opening weekend if it's a major film franchise. </Paragraph></Question><Answer><Paragraph>So how does <i>half as much</i> sound, as this quote from an article on TimesOnline dating back to May 2008 suggests? </Paragraph><Quote><Paragraph><i>Grand Theft Auto IV</i> sold a record 609,000 copies on its first day of release, generating an estimated £24.4 million at the tills — nearly double the box-office takings of a blockbuster film.</Paragraph><Paragraph>The higher-than-expected UK sales figure, compiled by Chart-Track, eclipsed the record of 501,000 held by the previous instalment in the <i>Grand Theft Auto</i> series, <i>San Andreas</i>, in October 2004.</Paragraph><Paragraph>It also comes hard on the heels of the success of Wii Fit, on the Nintendo console, which sold 240,000 in its first two days — more than the 200,000 that retailers had been predicting. Wii Fit is the sixth-best seller ever, generating £16.8 million at the tills.</Paragraph><Paragraph>Last weekend the highest-grossing film was <i>Forgetting Sarah Marshall</i>, which generated £2.1 million at the box office. <i>Casino Royale</i> and <i>Pirates of the Carribbean: Dead Man’s Chest</i> each generated just over £13 million on their opening weekends. </Paragraph><SourceReference>‘<a href="http://technology.timesonline.co.uk/tol/news/tech_and_web/gadgets_and_gaming/article3856081.ece">Grand Theft Auto IV records 609,000 first-day sales</a>, Dan Sabbagh, TimesOnline, May 1, 2008 </SourceReference></Quote><Paragraph><font val="Verdana"><language val="EN-US">In more recent months, the game Call of Duty: Modern Warfare 2 was estimated to take $550m worldwide in its first 5 days on sale (</language></font><a href="http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/technology/8457335.stm"><font val="Verdana"><language val="EN-US">Call of Duty: Modern Warfare 2</language></font><font val="Verdana"><language val="EN-US"> took</language></font><font val="Verdana"><language val="EN-US"> $1bn in sales</language></font></a><font val="Verdana"><language val="EN-US">). </language></font>Not bad for just a game, methinks? </Paragraph><Paragraph>If you know of any recent blockbuster game releases, see if you can find out how much they took in first day sales compared to the opening weekend receipts of a major film released at a similar time. Post the details to the module forums.</Paragraph><Paragraph><olink targetdoc="General Discussion Forum">Go to the forum now.</olink><InlineFigure><Image src="\\dog\PrintLive\nonCourse\design_templates\ICONS\Web\png's\32_pixels\forum_32.png" height="" width="100%" alt="" id="" webthumbnail="" x_imagesrc="forum_32.png" x_imagewidth="32" x_imageheight="32"/></InlineFigure></Paragraph></Answer></Activity><SubSection><Title>Questions and suggested resources</Title><Paragraph>Try to answer the following questions based on your reading of the suggested resources (that is, the Digital Worlds resources, the Readings and the recommended Links).</Paragraph><NumberedList><ListItem>What games might claim to be the first digital computer games, when were they invented, and what equipment did they run on? To what extent were they ‘designed’ as games?</ListItem><ListItem>To what extent might an understanding of the techniques of classical animation have influenced the early evolution of computer games?</ListItem><ListItem>What themes, or genres, if any, dominated the earliest computer games?</ListItem><ListItem>When did games consoles first start to appear and in what form? How did the players control the game action? How does this compare to the rise of personal computing and PCs in the home?</ListItem><ListItem>What sorts of game and gaming platform dominate the current digital interactive entertainment marketplace? What is the size of that market compared to other forms of entertainment? </ListItem></NumberedList><Paragraph>As before, make notes as you work through the material summarising key points related to the guiding questions. Bookmark any interesting or relevant sources that complement (or challenge) the resources I’ve suggested to your Delicious, or RefWorks, account, tagged with ‘T151’ and any other tags that seem useful to you. </Paragraph><Paragraph><b>Spend 1.5–2 hours exploring this topic.</b>  </Paragraph><Paragraph>When you’ve finished, read My observations on Topic exploration 1B.</Paragraph><InternalSection><Heading>Digital Worlds resources </Heading><BulletedList><ListItem><a href="http://digitalworlds.wordpress.com/2008/03/19/oscilliscopy/">Oscilloscopy </a></ListItem><ListItem><a href="http://digitalworlds.wordpress.com/2008/03/21/the-history-of-computer-games/">The History of Computer Games</a> </ListItem><ListItem><a href="http://digitalworlds.wordpress.com/2008/03/17/making-pictures-move/">Making Pictures Move</a></ListItem></BulletedList></InternalSection><InternalSection><Heading>Readings</Heading><BulletedList><ListItem><a href="http://www.prospect-magazine.co.uk/article_details.php?id=10209">Rage against the machines</a>, Tom Chatfield, Prospect Magazine, 29 June, 2008.</ListItem><ListItem><a href="http://dlib.ukoln.ac.uk/dlib/february02/kirriemuir/02kirriemuir.html">Video Gaming, Education and Digital Learning Technologies </a>– <a href="http://dlib.ukoln.ac.uk/dlib/february02/authors/02authors.html#KIRRIEMUIR">John Kirriemuir</a>, D-Lib Magazine, Vol 8(2), Feb 2002 </ListItem></BulletedList></InternalSection><InternalSection><Heading>Video resources</Heading><BulletedList><ListItem><a href="http://www.ted.com/index.php/talks/david_perry_on_videogames.html">TED</a>:<font val="Arial"> </font><font val="Arial">Will videogames become better than life? </font></ListItem></BulletedList></InternalSection><InternalSection><Heading>Digital Worlds custom search engine example searches:</Heading><Paragraph><font val="Verdana">If you would like to extend your research to include further resources, </font><a href="http://ouseful.open.ac.uk/digitalworlds/search/"><font val="Verdana">the Digital Worlds custom search engine</font></a><font val="Verdana"> searches over a wide variety of games related websites and resources. To get you started, you might find the following search queries useful.</font></Paragraph><BulletedList><ListItem>Information about games console sales volumes: <i>consoles sales data 20</i><i>10</i></ListItem><ListItem>The size of the computer games market: first day game sales; casual games market size  </ListItem></BulletedList></InternalSection><InternalSection><Heading>Links</Heading><BulletedList><ListItem><a href="http://www.atarimagazines.com/cva/v1n1/spacewar.php">The Origin of Spacewar!</a> – J.M. Graetz, <i>Creative Computing Video &amp; Arcade Games </i>Vol. 1, No. 1, Spring 1983, Page 78. </ListItem><ListItem><a href="http://www.time.com/time/covers/1101050523/console_timeline/">A history of video games consoles</a> (timeline)</ListItem><ListItem><a href="http://www.axess.com/twilight/console">Video Game Controller Family Tree</a> </ListItem><ListItem><a href="http://www.engadget.com/2006/03/03/a-brief-history-of-handheld-video-games/">A Brief History of Handheld Video Games</a>, Donal Melanson, engadget, 3 March, 2006.</ListItem><ListItem><a href="http://www.chart-track.co.uk/index.jsp?c=p/software/uk/latest/index.jsp">Game Charts</a> (GfK Chart Track) </ListItem><ListItem><a href="http://www.eraltd.org/content/stats.asp">Entertainment Retailers Association – Statistics</a></ListItem><ListItem><a href="http://www.xtimeline.com/timeline/The-History-of-Video-Games">The History of Video Games (interactive timeline)</a> <font val="Verdana"><language val="EN-US">(see also this </language></font><font val="Verdana"><language val="EN-US">Google timeline view of a search for ‘game controller</language></font><font val="Verdana"><language val="EN-US">’).</language></font></ListItem></BulletedList></InternalSection></SubSection><SubSection><Title>My observations on Topic exploration 1B </Title><Paragraph>What could loosely be termed the first electronic screen-based game, <i>Tennis for Two</i>, first appeared in 1958 as an entertaining way of demonstrating the use of electronics equipment such as oscilloscopes in electronics development labs. The idea? To ‘bat’ a digital ball from one side of an oscilloscope screen to the other. Artistic explorations of the same medium in the early 1960s resulted in several electronic screen-based interactive artworks, such as John Whitney's oscilloscope based work. </Paragraph><Paragraph>Arguably the first real <i>computer</i> game – <i>SpaceWar!</i> – appeared in 1962. According to <a href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/dna/h2g2/A656831">‘SpaceWar! – the First Computer Game</a>’ three guidelines informed its development: </Paragraph><NumberedList><ListItem>It should demonstrate as many of the computer's resources as possible, and tax those resources to the limit.</ListItem><ListItem>Within a consistent framework, it should be interesting, which means every run should be different.</ListItem><ListItem>It should involve the onlooker in a pleasurable and active way. </ListItem></NumberedList><Paragraph>Obviously, the technological angle was the one being pushed here. The game elements presumably arose from the desire to satisfy the second and third criteria – variety and pleasure! The evolution of the game appears to have been the pursuit of ever more realism. So for example, ‘[t]<font val="Trebuchet MS">he desire of another level of strategy led Dan Edwards to incorporate gravity calculations</font>’, and Peter Samson's creation of the ‘“<font val="Trebuchet MS">Expensive Planetarium” to provide a true to life backdrop of real constellations’</font> (BBC, 2003).</Paragraph><Paragraph>The first 'general-purpose' computer games consoles capable of playing different cartridge-based computer games started to appear in the mid-1970s (television-based 'hard wired' gaming systems had been around for several years prior to that). In the earliest days, games consoles came equipped with physical user interface devices (also known as controllers!), most notably the two axis joystick, with a ‘fire’ button, but these soon evolved into precursors of the ‘gamepad’ type interface devices that are familiar peripherals for today’s game consoles. (I also remember special add-on peripherals from very early on – infra-red guns for use with a TV video game, and simple steering wheels and accelerator pedals for use with driving games.) </Paragraph><Paragraph>In terms of implementation, and the extent to which computer games rely on computer-based animation, games designers and developers were able to draw on lessons learnt from traditional animators as they developed their craft. However, computer memory and processor speed limitations of all but the most recent generations of games consoles meant that the number of frames available to animate a character in a computer game were limited compared to the number of frames – or individual drawings – that could be used to animate a character in an animated film. In many cases, animated sprites in computer games might be limited to two different frames to represent a character. If you have ever looked at a two or three page flip-book, you'll appreciate that this doesn't give much leeway to the artist wanting to animate a wide range of movements, even if you can rapidly flip backwards and forwards between the two frames! </Paragraph><Paragraph>The very earliest computer arcade games tended to be themed as 'science fiction' games (such as <i>SpaceWar!</i>, <i>Space Invaders</i> or <i>Asteroids</i>) or very crude sports simulations (such as <i>Pong</i> and its like). Large cabinet arcade games introduced classic game types – such as the maze game mechanic popularised by <i>Pac-Man</i>, or the early platform games. Driving simulations were another common theme, coming complete with steering wheel and accelerator pedal in the arcade cabinet versions. My own memory of early cabinet arcade games throws up two more popular themes: 'street fighting' games (where the idea was to kick and punch your way past opponents in a 2D sidescrolling game), and first person shooters, where the controller was a gun and the aim was to shoot as many things as possible as quickly as possible! On the personal computer side, textbased adventures and simulated wargames complemented the arcade game clones, with the home consoles concentrating more on bringing the arcade games into the home. </Paragraph><Paragraph>Cartridge-based consoles lasted for about 20 years, when they started to be overtaken by CD-ROM based consoles such as the original Sony PlayStation in 1995. CD-ROM consoles soon found themselves superceded by DVD-based consoles, such as the PlayStation 2 (PS2) in 2000, with current generation consoles looking to the internet – and downloadable content  – as well as DVDs as the next distribution channel. </Paragraph><Paragraph>Handheld consoles arrived in force in 1980, with Nintendo's single dedicated ‘Game and Watch’ devices. The cartridge based Nintendo Game Boy stole the show in 1990 and was one of the dominant players until it was replaced by the Game Color in 1998. The next generation of handhelds arrived in 2004 in the form of the Nintendo DS and Sony PSP, but as smartphones get ever more powerful, and with ever bigger screens, they could well herald the next step in mobile gaming. </Paragraph><Paragraph>Personal Computers (PCs) appeared en masse in the mid 1980s, and provided a parallel games world to the world of computer game consoles, in part because of the more rapid technical evolution of the PC (new models would come on-stream every few months, as processors got faster and computer memory got cheaper), and in part (I believe) because of a different relationship users have with their PC – PCs tend to be on desks or tables, and people ‘sit-up’ to use them; games consoles are far more ‘laid back’ and often plug-in to a TV screen with the player ‘leaning back’ on a settee or comfy chair! Other major differences are that games can take a long time to install on a PC,  as well as the fact that PCs could save large amounts of ‘state’ (that is, large amounts of game-related information or data) between playing sessions, compared to games consoles, which often had limited facilities for storing large amounts of data. </Paragraph><Paragraph>Currently, the Nintendo Wii console appears to be the biggest selling home games console, followed by Microsoft's Xbox 360 and the Sony PlayStation 3 (PS3), as well as the older Sony PS2 (see the <a href="http://www.eraltd.org/_attachments/Resources/yearbook.pdf">Entertainment Retailers Association Yearbook</a> (PDF)). Many recent games have pushed the idea of additional peripherals, such as the guitar and drum controllers in the <i>Rock Band</i> style games, and the physical action controllers being pushed to support the Wii (such as the Wii Balance Board, and the Wiimote). Many of the original game themes are still evident – ultra-violent first-person shooters and sports simulation games (such as driving games, golf or football), as well as fantasy adventure themed games and arcade style games (many of the contemporary arcade styled games being extensions of quite old franchises, such as Mario or Sonic the Hedgehog). </Paragraph><Paragraph>In terms of sales volumes, the computer games market now rivals other forms of home entertainment (<a href="http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/technology/7709298.stm">Games 'to outsell' music, video</a>, Rory Cellan-Jones, BBC Technology blog, November 2008). If you've walked past an HMV store lately, you'll know that you're more likely to see DVDs or computer games advertised in the window or the aisles nearest the door, rather than music CDs. And if you ever walk around your local large supermarket, it's likely that as much, if not more, space will be given over to retailing computer games as it is to books or music. </Paragraph></SubSection></Section><Section><Title>Week 1 Game Maker activities</Title><Paragraph>In order to gain an appreciation of how games are developed, as well as see what sort of computing principles are involved in getting a computer game to actually work, T151 will provide you with an opportunity to learn how to create some simple games of your own. </Paragraph><Paragraph>The software package you will be using is called Game Maker. You should have downloaded this already - if not, instructions can be found on <olink targetptr="" targetdoc="Study resources">the Study resources section of the website</olink>.  <a href="http://gmc.yoyogames.com/">A thriving community exists around the application</a>. You are free to join that community whilst you are studying T151, but we will not be able to support you on those forums, nor do we moderate them. </Paragraph><Paragraph>Additional support materials can be found from the Game Maker <i>Help</i> menu, <a href="http://www.yoyogames.com/gamemaker/docs">the official Game Maker documentation</a> and on <a href="http://wiki.yoyogames.com/index.php/Main_Page">the official Game Maker wiki</a>. </Paragraph><Paragraph>In this first set of activities, you will learn how to use the Game Maker editor in order to create, and customise, a simple game of your own. In the second activity (that is, the Game Maker activities for week 2), you'll add a little more polish to your game, adding a points-scoring mechanic and Start Screen and Game Over screen. </Paragraph><Paragraph>You will develop each game in several stages. If you want to keep a copy of a game from each stage, simply save your game with a new file name at each step – for example, by using the number of the corresponding activity as part of the filename. I will also provide you copies of games at an appropriate stage of development for each activity for those (im)possible times when you just can't get your game to work and can't see why! </Paragraph><Paragraph>So let's get started – the key things to learn from this week's activity are: </Paragraph><BulletedList><ListItem>how to find your way around the Game Maker interface </ListItem><ListItem>how to create ‘sprites’ that can move around the game world independently of each other </ListItem><ListItem>how the game player can interact with game objects through mouse or keyboard commands. </ListItem></BulletedList><SubSection><Title>Game Maker Activity 1.1</Title><Paragraph>In this first activity, you will learn to create a very simple game using one of the official Game Maker tutorials. (In later activities, we will use our own tutorials.) An important part of this first activity is that you will learn how to find your way around Game Maker. But as well as that, you'll also get to build your first game and start to learn how computer programmes can be used to implement interactive games, including <font val="Lucida Grande">how to:</font> </Paragraph>  <BulletedList><ListItem>create the wall and clown <i>sprites</i> </ListItem><ListItem>create the fixed wall, and moving clown, <i>objects</i> </ListItem><ListItem>create and decorate a <i>room</i>, including the addition of a <i>background image</i> </ListItem><ListItem>add a <i>background soundtrack</i> to the game </ListItem><ListItem>use an <i>alarm</i> to add a bit of uncertainty to the game </ListItem><ListItem>add a short help/description page to your game. </ListItem></BulletedList>  <Activity><Question><Paragraph>DO: work through the activity described in the post: <a href="http://digitalworlds.wordpress.com/2008/03/07/getting-started-with-game-maker/">Getting Started with Game Maker</a>.</Paragraph><Paragraph><b>You should expect to spend up to 2 hours on working through this activity.</b> </Paragraph></Question></Activity></SubSection><SubSection><Title>Game Maker Activity 1.2 </Title><Paragraph>If you have not already done so, extend your clown game by adding a second and maybe even a third clown to the room. Simply select the clown object in the room’s object panel, and click within the room to add an additional clown. To what extent does increasing the number of clowns in the room make the game more or less exciting? </Paragraph><Paragraph>Can having too many clowns be too much of a good thing? Play through your game with increasing numbers of clowns. As you do so, try to monitor your own experience of the game. Does increasing the number of clowns in the game give you any ideas about how you might develop the game further?</Paragraph><Paragraph>Remember, this is <i>your</i> game that is being developed here. The activities are designed to help you develop the skills you need to use Game Maker effectively to create your own games; so feel free to experiment and try out things using your own initiative once you are confident with what I have shown you! </Paragraph><Paragraph><b>You should expect to spend no more than 30 minutes working through this activity. </b></Paragraph></SubSection><SubSection><Title><b>Game Maker Activity 1.3</b></Title><Paragraph>Hopefully, you have already started customising your game, and now have a number of clowns to catch. To make the game a little more rewarding it would be nice to be able to award points for catching each clown, and maybe even award different amounts of points for catching different sorts of clowns. (Maybe catching some clowns could even result in a penalty score?) But how would we identify which clown was which? By changing their visual appearance, perhaps, so we can distinguish between them? </Paragraph><Paragraph>In this activity, you will learn how to change the appearance of different characters within your game. If you have time to do so, you may even like to try editing some of the other image assets within your game to change how it looks, and as a result, maybe even how it feels to play? Feel free to explore using other sprites too: for example, changing the clown sprite to a wolf can very easily change the theme of the game from a paranoid circus fantasy to a reimagining of Little Red Riding Hood! </Paragraph><Activity><Question><Paragraph>DO: work through the activity described in the post: <a href="http://digitalworlds.wordpress.com/2008/03/08/editing-a-sprite/">Editing a Sprite</a>.</Paragraph><Paragraph><b>You should expect to spend no more than 1.5 hours on working through this activity. </b></Paragraph></Question></Activity></SubSection><SubSection><Title>Week 1 Game Maker Summary</Title><Paragraph>Phew... that was an in-at-the-deep-end start, but hopefully you've come out of those activities feeling a little more comfortable about how to find your way around the Game Maker environment, and also having produced your very first game. You should also have seen how it's possible to derive new image assets from old ones by simply recolouring existing sprites and other image assets. Maybe you even tried introducing different character sprites altogether, changing the theme from ‘Catch a Clown’ to a ‘Catch a Thief’, or ‘Catch a Wolf’, maybe?! </Paragraph><Paragraph>In next week’s activities, you'll find how to keep track of how well your players have done within the game by adding a scoring mechanism, as well as a Start screen and Game Over screen within which to package your game. </Paragraph></SubSection></Section></Session></Unit><BackMatter><References><Reference>BBC (2003) <font val="Trebuchet MS">SpaceWar! – the First Computer Game, </font><font val="Trebuchet MS"/><a href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/dna/h2g2/A656831"><font val="Trebuchet MS">http://www.bbc.co.uk/dn</font><font val="Trebuchet MS">a/h2g2/A656831</font></a><font val="Trebuchet MS">, accessed March 2009.</font></Reference></References></BackMatter><settings><numbering><Session autonumber="false"/><Section autonumber="false"/><SubSection autonumber="false"/><SubSubSection autonumber="false"/><Activity autonumber="false"/><Exercise autonumber="false"/><Box autonumber="false"/><CaseStudy autonumber="false"/><Quote autonumber="false"/><Extract autonumber="false"/><Dialogue autonumber="false"/><KeyPoints autonumber="false"/><Reading autonumber="false"/><StudyNote autonumber="false"/><Example autonumber="false"/><Verse autonumber="false"/><SAQ autonumber="false"/><ComputerDisplay autonumber="false"/><Summary autonumber="false"/><ProgramListing autonumber="false"/><ITQ autonumber="false"/><Tables autonumber="false"/><Figures autonumber="false"/><MediaContent autonumber="false"/><Chemistry autonumber="false"/></numbering><discussion_alias>Discussion</discussion_alias><session_prefix/></settings></Item>
